<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="discourse.v4_cn.css"?><html xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://wkwsci.ntu.edu.sg/discourse# discourse.v4_cn.xsd">
 <head><title> When Religion Hurts: Structural Sexism and Health in Religious Congregations</title>
 </head>
 <body>
  <l1> When Religion Hurts: Structural Sexism and Health in Religious Congregations</l1>
 <abstract>
  <l2>
   Abstract
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e61">
   <s id="d1e66">
    <arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="topic_centrality">An emerging line of research has begun to document the relationship between structural sexism and health.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e71">
    <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-define">This work shows that structural sexism — defined as systematic gender inequality in power and resources —</arg> <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="research_objective" comments_Arthur="research_result">within U.S. state-level institutions and within marriages can shape individuals’ physical health.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e81">
    <arg argID="004" type="support" supportType="method" comments_Arthur="OK, 建議要增加research subject(在research scopeInfD01)">In the present study, we use a novel dataset created by linking two nationally representative surveys (the General Social Survey and the National Congregations Study)</arg> <arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">to explore the health consequences of structural sexism within another setting: religious institutions.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e86">
    <arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="research_issue">Although religious participation is generally associated with positive health outcomes, many religious institutions create and reinforce a high degree of structural sexism, which is harmful for health.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e91">
   <arg argID="007" type="claim" claimType="research_gap"> Prior research has not reconciled these seemingly conflicting patterns.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e96">
    <arg argID="008" type="claim" claimType="result">We find that among religious participants, women who attend sexist religious institutions report significantly worse self-rated health than do those who attend more inclusive congregations.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e101">
    <arg argID="009" type="claim" claimType="result">Furthermore, only women who attend inclusive religious institutions exhibit a health advantage relative to non-participants.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e106">
    <arg argID="010" type="claim" claimType="result">We observe marginal to no statistically significant effects among men.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e111">
    <arg argID="011" type="claim" claimType="general_result" comments_Arthur="OK, 如果此一結果與以往不同, 則為research suggestions">Our results suggest the health benefits of religious participation do not extend to groups that are systematically excluded from power and status within their religious institutions.</arg>
   </s>
  </p>
 </abstract>
<intro>
  <p id="d1e120">
   <s id="d1e122">
    <arg argID="001" type="context" contextType="practical_background">Despite the gains made by women over the past 50 years, gender inequality remains a persistent problem in the United States.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e124">
    <arg argID="002" type="context" contextType="historical_background">In 2017, the United States ranked only 49th (out of 144 countries) for gender equity (World Economic Forum 2017).</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e126"><arg argID="003" type="context" contextType="historical_background">Women have made significant progress—particularly in the educational realm, where their college graduation rates now exceed men’s (Goldin, Katz, and Kuziemko 2006)—but they remain underpaid in the labor market and underrepresented in positions of political and economic power.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e128">
    <arg argID="004" type="context" contextType="historical_background">On average, women’s earnings were 81 percent of men’s, among full-time, year-round workers in 2018 (U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics 2019).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e130"><arg argID="005" type="context" contextType="historical_background">In 2019, the average percentage of state legislature seats held by women was 28.9 percent, with some U.S.states as low as 13 percent (CAWP 2019), although women comprise more than half of the U.S. population.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e132"><arg argID="006" type="context" contextType="historical_background">Furthermore, only 5.2 percent of S&amp;P 500 company CEOs were women as of December 2019 (Catalyst 2019).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e134"><arg argID="007" type="context" contextType="historical_background">Even in media and entertainment, where women are somewhat better represented than in other sectors, only 27 percent of executive-level management (i.e., C-suite) positions are held by women (Beard et al. 2020).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e136"><arg argID="008" type="context" contextType="historical_background">After becoming more egalitarian for more than two decades, U.S. gender role attitudes have changed little since the mid-1990s, suggesting a stalled gender revolution (Cotter, Hermsen, and Vanneman 2011; England 2010).</arg></s>
  </p>
<p id="d1e200">
   <s id="d1e202"><arg argID="020" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">This persistent gender inequality in large-scale social institutions is only one manifestation of a discriminatory gender system.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e204"><arg argID="021" type="context" contextType="topic_classification_structure">Contemporary sociological perspectives characterize gender as a multilevel social struc- ture or system that produces difference and inequality in large-scale social institutions at the macro level, in interactional settings at the meso level, and in individual identi- ties, beliefs, and bodies at the micro level (Ridgeway and Correll 2004; Risman 2004; Scarborough and Risman 2018).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e206">
    <arg argID="022" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-define">Structural sexism refers to the degree of systematic gender inequality in power and resources characterizing a given gender structure, and it can manifest in processes occurring at each level (Homan 2019).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e209">
    <arg argID="023" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">Structural sexism is distinct from overt sexist behaviors and interpersonal discrimination</arg> <arg argID="023" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration" comments_Ivanka="or established_knowledge" comments_Arthur="OK-elaboration">because it is systemic and does not require individual actors with awareness or intent (Bonilla-Silva 1997; Homan 2019; Krieger 2014).</arg></s>
 <s id="d1e212"><arg argID="023" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">Individuals may not necessarily perceive structural sexism, or they may not conceptualize it as unfair, unequal, or discriminatory, because observed gender inequalities in power and resources are often rationalized as natural results of inherent gender differences (Fen- stermaker Berk 1985; West and Zimmerman 1987).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e214"><arg argID="029" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration">Nevertheless, the unequal distribution of power and resources characterizing a society’s gender structure can have consequences for the health and well-being of its members.</arg></s>
    <s id="d1e216"><arg argID="029" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">Recent research has developed measures of structural sexism at the macro (U.S. state) and meso (marital dyad) levels and shown that structural sexism exposure at each level is associated with both men’s and women’s physical health (Homan 2019).</arg></s>
</p>
  <p id="d1e300">
   <s id="d1e302">
    <arg argID="030" type="support" supportType="method">In the present study, we use a novel dataset created from two nationally representative surveys (the General Social Survey and the National Congregations Study)</arg> <arg argID="030" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">to explore the health consequences of structural sexism in another meso-level setting: religious institutions.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e304">
    <arg argID="030" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">This setting is particularly instructive because research suggests religious institutions are beneficial for health and well-being (Ellison and Levin 1998; Hill, Burdette, and Idler 2011; Koenig, King, and Carson 2012; Strawbridge et al. 1998),</arg> <arg argID="031" type="support" supportType="motivation/justification">yet many have rigid gender-based status hierarchies that generate a type of meso-level structural sexism that is likely harmful for women’s health.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e306"><arg argID="031" type="claim" claimType="research_gap">Previous research has not yet considered how these seemingly contradictory patterns relate to one another.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e310"><arg argID="032" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">Therefore, we examine how structural sexism within religious congregations shapes women’s and men’s self-rated health and how their health compares to that of non-participants.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e316"><arg argID="033" type="claim" claimType="result">Our results indicate that the long-recognized health benefits of religious participation are contingent on equal access to power and status within religious institutions.</arg></s>
  </p>
</intro>
  <l1>
   StRuCtuRAl SexiSm And HeAltH
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e361">
   <s id="d1e366">
    Gender scholars have long explored the con- tours and consequences of gender inequality in the United States, but the measurement of structural sexism and its health conse- quences is a relatively recent development.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e371">
    A structural sexism approach combines con- temporary gender theory with the emerging racism and health literature to look beyond perceived individual mistreatment (e.g., sex- ual harassment and other overt behaviors) to investigate how discriminatory social systems affect health (Homan 2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e376">
    Individuals may not directly perceive structural sexism, but it has the potential to powerfully influence population health by shaping the distribution of health-promoting resources and health- harming risk factors.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e381">
   <s id="d1e386">
    Because women are the marginalized group, living in a society with a high degree of structural sexism can restrict their access to quality health care, material resources, and psychosocial resources (e.g., self-esteem, sense of control, autonomy, social support) (Homan 2019; Krieger 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e391">
    High levels of structural sexism may also increase women’s exposure to violence, harassment, perceived discrimination, low subjective social status, and stress (Aizer 2010; Homan 2019; Krieger 2014).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e396">
   <s id="d1e401">
    and Phelan 1995; Marmot 2005, 2006; Pas- coe and Richman 2009; Pearlin et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e406">
    1981; Yang, Schorpp, and Mullan Harris 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e411">
    The impact of structural sexism on men’s health is more complex and likely to be mixed.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e416">
    As the dominant group, men stand to benefit from greater status, power, and resources in more sexist environments; however, research and theory also indicate that patriarchal social structures promote toxic versions of mascu- linity that undermine men’s health (Connell 2012; Courtenay 2000).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e421">
   <s id="d1e426">
    In a multilevel examination of the relation- ship between structural sexism and health, Homan (2019) measured systematic gender inequality in power and resources within U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e431">
    state-level political, economic, and cultural institutions at the macro level, and within het- erosexual marriages at the meso level.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e436">
    Homan identified two distinct patterns in the health effects of structural sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e441">
    In state-level institutions, structural sexism exhibited a pat- tern of universal harm because it was nega- tively associated with physical health among both men and women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e446">
    However, within mar- riages, the relationship between sexism and health exhibited a zero-sum pattern, with women experiencing worse health and men experiencing better health in more sexist mar- riages.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e451">
    It remains unclear whether this zero- sum pattern extends to meso-level settings that are not characterized by a dyadic rela- tionship where the gains of one partner can directly translate to losses for the other.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e456">
   <s id="d1e461">
    to examine structural sexism and health in other meso-level contexts such as neighbor- hoods, workplaces, and organizations.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e466">
   <s id="d1e471">
    In the present study, we therefore exam- ine the association between self-rated health and meso-level structural sexism in religious congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e476">
    A focus on religious congrega- tions is particularly illuminating for several key reasons.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e481">
    First, religious congregations provide an opportunity to examine a middle ground in terms of scale between marriages and U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e486">
    states, where the balance of costs and benefits to subordinating women may be unique.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e491">
    Second, religious beliefs, practices, and organizations are deeply gendered.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e496">
    Much variation exists across religious traditions and institutions, but religious organizations have historically disadvantaged women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e501">
    Finally, religious participation influences health in varied and significant ways.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Religion, HeAltH, And gendeR inequAlity
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e506">
   <s id="d1e511">
    Over the past three decades, numerous stud- ies have shown that religious involvement— indicated by observable feelings, beliefs, activities, and experiences in relation to spiri- tual, divine, or super-natural entities—tends to favor health and longevity across the life course.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e516">
    These general patterns can be seen across a range of outcomes, including depression, anxiety, cellular aging, allostatic load, physical functioning, and all-cause and cause-specific mortality (Ellison and Levin 1998; George, Ellison, and Larson 2002; Hill, Bradshaw, and Burdette 2016; Idler 2004; Koenig et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e521">
    2012; Krause and Hayward 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e526">
    More recently, scholars have focused on the dark side of religion.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e531">
    For example, research shows that religious involvement may also contribute to morbidity and mor- tality when individuals experience religious struggles, such as doubts about God, social conflicts within religious groups, or threaten- ing beliefs about the devil (Ellison and Lee 2010; Exline and Rose 2013; Hill et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e536">
    2017; Hill and Cobb 2011; Krause and Wulff 2004; Pargament et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e541">
    2001).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e546">
   <s id="d1e551">
    There is also compelling evidence that the association between religion and health may vary by gender.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e556">
    A few exceptions exist (e.g., McFarland 2010), but the general weight of the evidence suggests religion has a greater impact on women’s health than on men’s health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e561">
    Several studies show that church attendance is more strongly associated with better mental health (Mirola 1999; Norton et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e566">
    2006; Schieman, Bierman, and Ellison 2010; Strawbridge et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e571">
    2001) and physical health (Koenig 1999; McCullough et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e576">
    2000; McCullough and Laurenceau 2005; Straw- bridge et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e581">
    1998) among women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e586">
    Research also suggests institutional factors may con- dition gender differences in the impact of religious involvement on health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e591">
    Maselko and Kubzansky (2006) show that religious activ- ity is negatively associated with psychological distress among Catholic men and positively associated with psychological distress among Catholic women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e596">
    They also report that reli- gious activity is associated with better self- rated health, higher levels of happiness, and lower levels of psychological distress among evangelical Protestant men but not among evangelical Protestant women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e601">
    Maselko and Kubzansky (2006) speculate that women may benefit less from regular religious activity because religious institutions, like most insti- tutions, are often sexist in nature.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e606">
   <s id="d1e611">
    How might sexism in religious institutions disproportionally undermine women’s health? Religion may differentially affect the health of men and women through several insti- tutional and non-institutional mechanisms.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e616">
    Indeed, religious institutions often dictate that men and women occupy separate domains both inside and outside of the church.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e621">
    Despite making up the majority of religious affili- ates (Baker and Whitehead 2016), women are often prohibited from top organizational leadership positions, particularly within gender-traditional religions like conserva- tive Protestantism, Orthodox Judaism, and Mormonism (Burke 2012).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e626">
    Currently, only around 15 percent of U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e631">
    congregations are led by a woman (Chaves 2017; Chaves and Anderson 2008).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e636">
   <s id="d1e641">
    congregations are within the mainline Protes- tant tradition, which includes denominations such as The United Church of Christ, The United Methodist Church, American Baptist Churches USA, The Episcopal Church, the Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.), and the Chris- tian Church (Disciples of Christ) (Ferguson 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e646">
   <s id="d1e651">
    Some religious traditions may be “femin- ized” in terms of valorizing traits associated with femininity (e.g., cultivating relation- ships, sharing, comforting) (Perry 2019:92), but most are “gendered” masculine because men control access to resources and dominate positions of power (adams 2007; Baker and Whitehead 2016; Cadge 2004; Whitehead 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e656">
    Feminist scholarship has examined reasons why women participate in conserva- tive religious groups—often asking why women subscribe to religious regimes, tradi- tions, ideologies, and practices that reproduce gender inequalities and undermine personal agency (Avishai 2016)—yet few studies have examined the impact of religious institutional sexism on the health of religious adherents.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e661">
   <s id="d1e666">
    Within conservative Christian traditions, those who argue that congregational leader- ship should not be accessible to women fre- quently draw support from the Bible (adams 2007; Chaves 1997); and the Bible transla- tions most likely to be read in these churches contain language endorsing the subordination of women (Perry 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e671">
    To justify excluding women from church headship, some religious leaders read certain passages as supporting the submissiveness of women within the con- gregation (e.g., 1 Corinthians 14:34; Timothy 2:11–12).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e676">
    These gendered interpretations of sacred texts are rooted in notions of comple- mentarianism, which are prominent within conservative Christian congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e681">
    Com- plementarianism is centered on the idea that gender is essential, that is, gender is funda- mental and inherent (Diefendorf 2019; Perry 2020).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e686">
   <s id="d1e691">
    part of God’s grand plan (Perry 2019:90).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e696">
    Part of this complementarian conviction includes the belief that men are particularly suited for leadership, whereas women are designed to serve as helpers (Bartkowski and Shah 2014; Ellison and Bartkowski 2002).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e701">
    The two gen- ders complement one another because they are fundamentally different.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e706">
    In the evangeli- cal Protestant view, God had a practical pur- pose in making men and women diverse, with women intended to be supporters for their spouses, as well as men more generally (Perry 2019:91).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e711">
    Thus, complementary gender roles are necessary for the proper functioning of the family, the church, and society at large (Diefendorf 2019; Griffith 1997).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e716">
   <s id="d1e721">
    Complementarianism provides a clear guide for the acceptable roles of men and women within gender-traditional religious groups, but the reality is more complicated.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e726">
    Rather than being simple-minded victims of patriarchy, numerous studies show that con- servative religious women display a great deal of agency within church and home (Avishai, Gerber, and Randles 2013; Bartkowski 2001; Burke 2012; Gallagher 2004a, 2004b).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e731">
    The conflict between adherence to religiously based traditional gender ideologies and com- mitment to the gender egalitarian ideals held by broader U.S society leads to a high degree of “messiness” within conservative religious congregations (Diefendorf 2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e736">
    Although few religious conservatives identify as femi- nist, qualitative research clearly shows that many evangelical Protestants uphold certain aspects of gender equality, such as equity in pay and employment opportunities (Gal- lagher 2004a, 2004b).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e741">
    Thus, within many evangelical Christian churches there is an apparent tension between deep-rooted beliefs in gender essentialism and beliefs in gender equality (Diefendorf 2019).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e746">
   <s id="d1e751">
    This tension between egalitarian ideals and gender essentialist beliefs is not confined to conservative religious institutions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e756">
    Indeed, scholars have noted that the belief that men and women are innately and fundamentally different is common in the U.S.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e761">
   <s id="d1e766">
    (England 2010; Pepin and Cotter 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e771">
    Cot- ter and colleagues (2011) show that after becoming more egalitarian for more than two decades, gender role attitudes among U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e776">
    adults plateaued during the mid-1990s.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e781">
    They attribute this trend to the rise of a new cul- tural frame, “an egalitarian essentialism that blends aspects of feminist equality and tra- ditional motherhood roles.” Although beliefs in gender essentialism are part of the broader culture in the United States, they are more pronounced within conservative religious institutions and are imbued with a sacred quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e786">
    Furthermore, conservative religious institutions contribute to the stalled gender revolution by sanctifying these traditional gender role ideologies.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e791">
   <s id="d1e796">
    Given that both broader cultural ideals of gender equality and gender essentialism influ- ence members of conservative religious organ- izations, what does this mean for the health of women situated within gender-traditional religious groups? Women who are members of conservative religious groups are more likely to experience religious structural sexism, meaning they are denied access to key lead- ership roles and decision-making within the organization.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e801">
    Exposure to religious structural sexism may undermine women’s mental and physical health by creating a stressful source of internal conflict.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e806">
    Women who are members of gender-traditional churches may espouse the beliefs of strict gender roles and hierarchy.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e811">
    Yet, many of these women are also committed to ideals of gender fairness.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e816">
    It may be fundamen- tally distressing to be denied access to the most basic levels of organizational decision-making, as is the case in the most structurally sexist congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e821">
    Structural sexism may be par- ticularly detrimental to women’s health within religious organizations, given that churches are “greedy” institutions that often demand high levels of time, energy, and commitment (Ellison and Lee 2010).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e826">
   <s id="d1e831">
    Religious institutions can also reinforce gender inequality in ways that undermine health via other institutional domains.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e836">
   <s id="d1e841">
    pronounced within the family.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e846">
   <s id="d1e851">
    U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e856">
    history, religion and family have been linked through relationships of dependency and control (Edgell 2013).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e861">
   <s id="d1e866">
    2002; Ghazal Read 2004).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e871">
    Consequently, housework and childcare become ideologi- cally defined as the natural providence of women, and there is little incentive for men to participate in mundane household tasks.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e876">
    As a result, women within conservative religious institutions may face a significant degree of work-family conflict, given that most evan- gelical Protestant women work outside of the home (Ellison and Bartkowski 2002).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e881">
   <s id="d1e886">
    Similarly, women in gender traditional churches are unequally tasked with main- taining and enforcing sexual morality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e891">
    These gendered notions of sexuality may under- mine health and well-being when translated into unrealistic standards of sexual purity or undesired sexual encounters within mar- riage (DeRogatis 2015).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e896">
    For example, in his work on pornography use among evangelical Christians, Perry (2019) notes that women in conservative religious communities often do not feel free to discuss topics like lust, pornography, or masturbation because these are assumed to be masculine issues.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e901">
    There- fore, women in these communities may feel shame for both violating community norms of sexual morality and not living up to ideals of femininity.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e906">
    In more extreme cases, reli- gious institutional sexism may contribute to intimate partner violence, given evidence that men who hold more conservative theological views than their partners are especially likely to perpetrate violence against their partners (Ellison, Bartkowski, and Anderson 1999), and women in very closed religious commu- nities are especially vulnerable when abused (Nason-Clark 2000).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e911">
   <s id="d1e916">
    disproportionally undermine women’s mental and physical health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e921">
   <s id="d1e926">
    In summary, although religious participa- tion has been linked to improved health and well-being, many religious institutions have rigid gender-based status hierarchies that prohibit women from occupying meaning- ful leadership roles.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e931">
    This religious structural sexism is likely to harm women’s health in a variety of ways.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e936">
    Scholars have speculated that women may benefit less than men from regu- lar religious activity because institutions of religion are sexist (Maselko and Kubzansky 2006), but this assertion has not been explic- itly tested.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e941">
    Thus, it remains unclear whether the health benefits of religious participation are contingent on equal access to power and status within congregations.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e946">
   <s id="d1e951">
    Is attending a sexist religious institu- tion that excludes women from power and leadership associated with health among women and men?
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e956">
   <s id="d1e961">
    If so, how does the health of attendees at inclusive religious institutions and sexist religious institutions compare to that of individuals who do not regu- larly participate in organized religion?
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e966">
   <s id="d1e971">
    Based on previous research and theory, we expect that among women who attend reli- gious services, congregational sexism will be associated with worse self-rated health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e976">
    We also expect that women who attend inclusive churches will have better self-rated health than both attendees of sexist churches and non-attenders because they enjoy the health- promoting benefits of religious participation without the potentially harmful exposure to additional sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e981">
    Depending on the extent to which congregational sexism negates the benefits of religious participation, we may expect that women who attend sexist churches have equal or worse self-rated health than non-attenders.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e986">
   <s id="d1e991">
    Previous scholarship suggests clear expec- tations for how congregational sexism may affect women’s health as the marginalized
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e996">
   <s id="d1e1001">
    group, but this work is theoretically and empirically ambiguous as to how religious institutional sexism may affect men’s health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1006">
    On one hand, because men are the dominant group in sexist congregations, they may ben- efit from greater status, power, and resources in ways that improve their health and well- being.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1011">
    If this is the case, congregational sexism may be associated with better self- rated health among men who attend religious services.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1016">
    On the other hand, congregational sexism may promote toxic versions of mascu- linity that undermine men’s health and cause strife within other institutional domains.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1021">
    If this is true, congregational sexism may be associated with worse self-rated health among men, although perhaps to a lesser degree than among women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1026">
    Finally, it is also possible that exposure to congregational sexism benefits men in some ways and harms them in others such that the net effect is zero.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   metHodS
  </l1>
  <l2>
   Data and Sample
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e1031">
   <s id="d1e1036">
    To answer these questions, we draw on a unique dataset created by linking two large nationally representative studies: the Gen- eral Social Survey (GSS) and the National Congregations Study (NCS).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1041">
    The GSS is an individual-level survey of attitudes, behaviors, and characteristics of U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1046">
    residents conducted yearly by NORC since 1972 (Smith et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1051">
    2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1056">
    The NCS is a hypernetwork1 sample of religious congregations in the United States conducted in conjunction with the GSS in 1998, 2006, and 20122 (Chaves, Anderson, and Eagle 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1061">
    The NCS sample was generated by asking GSS respondents how frequently they attended religious services in the past year.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1066">
    Individuals who attended more than once in the previous year were asked to provide the name and location of their congregation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1071">
    This process generated nationally representative congregation-level samples for each of the three waves of the NCS.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1076">
    The NCS interviewed one key informant (usually a priest or rabbi) from each congregation in the sample.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1081">
   <s id="d1e1086">
    This sampling procedure allows us to link3 individual-level data from the GSS (i.e., health, demographics, and religious attend- ance) with contextual data about respond- ents’ religious congregations from the NCS to assess how exposure to structural sexism within a religious group may affect attendees’ health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1091">
    To date, only two studies have used data created by this linkage.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1096">
    Ellison and col- leagues (2009) used linked GSS-NCS data to examine the relationship between church characteristics (e.g., size) and participants’ social interactions; Cobb, Üsküp, and Jef- ferson (2017) examined the link between congregational composition and beliefs about racial inequality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1101">
    For the present study, we use two cross-sectional waves of GSS-NCS linked data in 2006 and 2012 because the baseline wave of the NCS (i.e., 1998) did not include the questions we use to measure the role of women in congregational leadership.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1106">
    We pool the linked GSS-NCS data from these two waves to derive a nationally representa- tive sample of individuals within religious congregations in 2006 and 2012.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1111">
    Sixty per- cent of cases in our sample are from the year 2006 (N = 1,354), and 40 percent are from 2012 (N = 880).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1116">
    The sample size is reduced in 2012 because the GSS switched to a rotat- ing panel design with smaller cross-sectional samples beginning in 2010.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1121">
   <s id="d1e1126">
    To answer our research questions, we examine two subsamples of GSS respond- ents: a sample of religious attenders and a non-attenders sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1131">
    Figure 1 is a flow chart illustrating our sample selection criteria.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1136">
    The religious participant subsample (i.e., respond- ents who indicated they attend religious ser- vices more than once a year) is limited to individuals who have complete data for focal variables in both the NCS and GSS (N = 1,390).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1141">
    Because the NCS response rate is 73 to 78 percent for both waves, there are some GSS respondents who indicated they attend religious services more than once a year but are missing congregation information (N = 744, which is 32 percent of attenders).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1146">
   <s id="d1e1151">
    All GSS respondents 2006 and
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1156">
   <s id="d1e1161">
    2012 (cross-sectional)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1166">
   <s id="d1e1171">
    N = 6,484
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1176">
   <s id="d1e1181">
    GSS respondents randomly assigned to Ballots A &amp;C
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1186">
   <s id="d1e1191">
    N = 3,311
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1196">
   <s id="d1e1201">
    Dropped all GSS respondents randomly assigned to Ballot B (lacks health measure) and Ballot D (not part of hypernetwork sample for NCS)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1206">
   <s id="d1e1211">
    Non-attenders Did not attend church
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1216">
   <s id="d1e1221">
    &gt; 1 time in past year
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1226">
   <s id="d1e1231">
    N = 969
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1236">
   <s id="d1e1241">
    Attenders Matched with an NCS
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1246">
   <s id="d1e1251">
    congregation
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1256">
   <s id="d1e1261">
    N = 1,586
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1266">
   <s id="d1e1271">
    Attenders
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1276">
   <s id="d1e1281">
    Did NOT match with an NCS congregation
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1286">
   <s id="d1e1291">
    N = 744
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1296">
   <s id="d1e1301">
    Dropped from main sample but retained via imputation in
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1306">
   <s id="d1e1311">
    supplemental analysis (see online supplement)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1316">
   <s id="d1e1321">
    Non-attender Subsample Complete data for study variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1326">
   <s id="d1e1331">
    N = 844
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1336">
   <s id="d1e1341">
    Attender Subsample Complete data for study variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1346">
   <s id="d1e1351">
    N = 1,390
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1356">
   <s id="d1e1361">
    FINAL SAMPLE TOTAL N = 2,234
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1366">
   <s id="d1e1371">
    Figure 1.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1376">
   <s id="d1e1381">
    have equivalent levels of self-rated health and are generally similar to the non-missing reli- gious attenders with the exception of being
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1386">
   <s id="d1e1391">
    2.6 years younger, having .5 fewer years of education, and earning $200 less per year in annual household income.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1396">
    Attenders missing congregation information also attend places of worship less frequently than religious par- ticipants who are not missing congregation information.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1401">
    In fact, attenders who are miss- ing congregational information most likely did not attend regularly enough to accurately name a congregation, and thus excluding them is unlikely to introduce meaningful bias.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1406">
    Nevertheless, to test the robustness of our results to potential non-response bias, we conducted additional analyses in which we used multiple imputation with chained equa- tions to impute the missing congregational data (i.e., church structural sexism variables and church setting: urban, suburban, or rural) for this group based on respondents’ other characteristics.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1411">
    Results of these supplemental analyses are substantively identical to those we present (see Tables S1 and S2 in the online supplement).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1416">
   <s id="d1e1421">
    than once in the past year and have complete data for the relevant study variables (N = 844).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1426">
    Item missingness was minimal (less than .2 percent for all variables except for income, which was missing in 12 percent of cases) and is therefore handled using listwise deletion.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1431">
    However, we also replicated our main analyses using multiple imputation for income and found similar results (see Tables S1 and S2 in the online supplement).
   </s>
  </p>
  <l2>
   Measures
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e1436">
   <s id="d1e1441">
    Self-rated health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1446">
    Our key dependent vari- able for both samples is self-rated health (SRH).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1451">
    Decades of research have established SRH as a valid and reliable indicator of cur- rent health status as well as a strong predictor of mortality (Idler and Benyamini 1997; Jylhä 2009).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1456">
    Self-rated health is measured yearly in the GSS by asking respondents, “Would you say your own health, in general, is excellent, good, fair, or poor?” Responses are coded on a four-point scale where 1 is poor and 4 is excellent.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1461">
    For ease of interpretation, we show results from OLS models, which treat this outcome as linear.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1466">
   <s id="d1e1471">
    similar results for all analyses (see Tables S1 and S2 in the online supplement), and Brant tests indicate that the proportional odds assumption is not violated.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1476">
   <s id="d1e1481">
    Church structural sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1486">
    We concep- tualize structural sexism as systematic gender inequality in power and resources within religious congregations, and we measure it with three different congregation-level vari- ables based on a series of questions answered by each congregation’s leader.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1491">
    First, we use a dichotomous measure (labeled “board”) indicating whether an “otherwise qualified woman” in the congregation would be permit- ted to “serve as a full-fledged member of the congregation’s main governing body or coor- dinating committee” (0 = yes, 1 = no).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1496">
    This measure of women’s representation in gov- ernance is particularly important for assessing the relationship between structural sexism and health given the accumulating evidence showing women’s political representation is vital for population health both in the United States and in the developing world (Homan 2017; Quamruzzaman and Lange 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1501">
    Fur- thermore, although restricting women from governing boards is less common than other forms of religious institutional sexism, it is perhaps the most dangerous for health as it indicates a complete lack of decision-making power for women within the congregation.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1506">
   <s id="d1e1511">
    Second, we use another dichotomous
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1516">
   <s id="d1e1521">
    measure (labeled “leader”) indicating whether an “otherwise qualified woman” would be permitted to serve as the head clergyperson or primary religious leader of the congregation (0 = yes, 1 = no).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1526">
    Restricting women from the top rung on the congregational leader- ship ladder is a potentially powerful form of religious institutional sexism, as head clergy hold a great deal of power within a congrega- tion.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1531">
    Additionally, much of the scholarship on gender inequality within places of wor- ship centers on the gender-based prohibition on clergy positions, or what has been termed “the stained-glass ceiling” (e.g., adams 2007; Bartkowski and Shah 2014).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1536">
   <s id="d1e1541">
    measure, which is a summary measure indi- cating how many of the following things women are prohibited from doing in the con- gregation: teaching co-ed classes, preaching at a main worship service, serving on the gov- erning body, and being the head clergyperson/ leader.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1546">
    Scores range from 0 (indicating no restrictions on women’s roles) to 4 (indicating women are prohibited from all four activities).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1551">
   <s id="d1e1556">
    .71, indicating that the index reflects a valid construct.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1561">
    In addition to this straightforward index approach to creating a sexism scale, we also conducted supplemental analyses using a latent variable approach with structural equation modeling (see Tables S4 and S5 in the online supplement).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1566">
    Results from these supplemental analyses did not meaningfully differ from the main results presented here.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1571">
    We chose the sum index approach using OLS as the main model for simplicity, ease of interpretation, and compatibility with other analyses conducted herein.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1576">
   <s id="d1e1581">
    All three structural sexism measures are coded such that high values indicate greater sexism in congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1586">
    Our first two meas- ures are important because they center on the most salient and perhaps most detrimental forms of religious institutional sexism and allow us to individually evaluate their effects.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1591">
    Our scale measure is useful because it combines these measures with two additional indicators to provide a more comprehensive assessment of the degree to which women are excluded from a variety of meaningful leadership roles within places of worship.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1596">
    Including all three measures allows us to account for women’s power and status in governance, clergy, and across a range of leadership positions.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1601">
   <s id="d1e1606">
    Other covariates.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1611">
    Our models include several individual and congregation-level covariates.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1616">
    At the individual level, we adjust for age, race (White = 1, non-White = 0), education (in years), household income (in thousands of inflation adjusted U.S.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1621">
   <s id="d1e1626">
    base year 2000), marital status (married = 1, not married = 0), and frequency of church attendance (on a nine-point scale ranging from 0 = never to 8 = more than once a week).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1631">
    At the congregation level, we adjust all estimates for church regional setting (urban, suburban, or rural).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1636">
    In supplemental models (see Table S6 in the online supplement), we investigate the role of congregational adher- ence to the doctrine of biblical inerrancy (0 = no, 1 = yes) and religious tradition, with dummy variables for each of the following categories: Conservative Christian, Roman Catholic, other Christian, and non-Christian.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1641">
    Conservative Christian includes evangelical Protestants and Mormons.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1646">
    Other Christian includes several liberal, mainline, and Black Protestant denominations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1651">
    Non-Christian includes Jewish, Muslim, and other religious traditions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1656">
    Note that only 3 percent of our sample (N = 41) attended a non-Christian congregation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1661">
    To adjust for time, all mod- els also include a dummy variable for the year 2012 (with 2006 as the reference year).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1666">
    Because prior research and theory suggest each of these factors may vary by gender and differentially affect health along gender lines (Denton, Prus, and Walters 2004; Geronimus et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1671">
    2007; McCullough and Laurenceau 2005; Ross, Masters, and Hummer 2012; Umberson and Kroeger 2016), all analyses are stratified by gender.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1676">
    We also include, for comparison, models that combine the sam- ples of men and women and include a gender by sexism interaction term.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l2>
   Analytic Approach
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e1681">
   <s id="d1e1686">
    To answer our first research question, we estimated a series of linear regression models among our subsample of religious participants predicting individuals’ self-rated health as a function of the levels of sexism in the congre- gation they attended (and other covariates).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1691">
    We estimated separate models for each of the three religious institutional sexism measures.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1696">
   <s id="d1e1701">
    of sexist congregations, or attendees of inclu- sive congregations, and again used linear regression to predict self-rated health based on these categories and other covariates.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1706">
   <s id="d1e1711">
    In these models, we categorized congrega- tions as sexist or inclusive based on the fol- lowing criteria.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1716">
    For the dichotomous “board” and “leader” measures, congregations are defined as sexist if they do not allow women to serve in these roles.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1721">
    For the sexism index measure, congregations are defined as sex- ist if they score higher than 2 on our scale, meaning women are prohibited from serving in more than two of the four possible roles.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1726">
    Forty-two percent of religious participants in our sample attended a church categorized as sexist based on this metric (compared to 14 percent for “board” and 59 percent for “leader”).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1731">
    All models use robust standard errors clustered by congregation4 to account for heteroskedasticity.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1736">
   <s id="d1e1741">
    We conducted a series of robustness checks that can be found in Tables S1 to S6 in the online supplement.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1746">
    These analyses dem- onstrate that our results are robust to alterna- tive modeling strategies (OLS versus ordered logistic regression), alternative missing data handling (multiple imputation versus list-wise deletion), alternative weighting approaches (GSS weights versus unweighted), alterna- tive measurement approaches (SEM latent variable versus sum index), and the inclusion of additional congregation-level variables (“inerrancy” and religious tradition).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1751">
    Sup- plemental analyses (not shown) also indicated that the health effects of congregational sex- ism do not vary according to respondents’ race or frequency of attendance.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1756">
   <s id="d1e1761">
    To better understand the pattern of results among men, we also conducted Bayesian lin- ear regression modeling using a random-walk Metropolis-Hastings sampling algorithm (MCMC sample size = 10,000; burn-in = 2,500).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1766">
    We conducted three Bayesian analy- ses, one for each sexism measure, all with separate slopes for the effects of sexism for women and for men, similar to a combined- gender model with an interaction term for sexism × male.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1771">
   <s id="d1e1776">
    normal priors with zero mean and variance of 10,000 for regression coefficients and an inverse-gamma prior with shape and scale parameters of .01 for the variance.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   ReSultS
  </l1>
  <l2>
   Descriptive Statistics
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e1781">
   <s id="d1e1786">
    Descriptive statistics are shown in Table 1.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1791">
    The average age of the sample is 47, with religious attenders being slightly older than non-attenders.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1796">
    The average level of educa- tion is roughly 14 years, with attenders being slightly more educated than non-attenders.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1801">
    The average family income of the sample is $49,700, with attenders and men hav- ing higher incomes than non-attenders and women, respectively.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1806">
    The average SRH score is 2.96, with religious attenders reporting bet- ter health than non-attenders.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1811">
    There are no statistically significant gender differences in SRH.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1816">
    The religious participant subsample has fewer White individuals, more women, and more married individuals, compared to the non-attending sample.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1821">
   <s id="d1e1826">
    The average frequency of attendance in the religious participant sample is 5.2, which cor- responds to slightly above two to three times per month.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1831">
    Women attend religious services more frequently than men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1836">
    The majority of respondents attend congregations in locations classified as urban (68 percent); 13 percent attend suburban congregations and 18 percent attend rural congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1841">
    Fourteen percent of the sample of religious attenders are in congregations that prohibit women from serv- ing on the leadership/governing board, and the remaining 86 percent attend congregations that allow women to serve in this role.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1846">
    Fifty-nine percent of religious service attenders are in congregations that prohibit women from being the head clergyperson/leader, and the remain- ing 41 percent attend congregations that would allow a woman to serve as the primary leader.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1851">
    Finally, the mean score on the sexism scale is 1.30 (SD = 1.23), which represents the number of restrictions (out of four possible) on women’s roles in the average congregation.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l2>
   Do Attendees of Sexist Congregations Have Worse Health Than Attendees of Inclusive Congregations?
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e1856">
   <s id="d1e1861">
    Table 2 shows the results of regression models predicting self-rated health among women and men who are religious participants.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1866">
    Models 1 through 3 are identical except that each uses a different measure of religious institutional sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1871">
    First, in gender stratified models, all three measures of structural sexism have statistically significant negative effects on women’s self-rated health, such that women who attend more sexist congregations have worse health than women who attend less sexist congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1876">
    The effects of congre- gational sexism among men are not statisti- cally significant for any of the three sexism measures.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1881">
    Sensitivity analyses suggest that the relatively smaller size of the men’s sample does not drive this lack of significant findings through diminished statistical power, as a ran- dom sample of the same size produced similar or larger statistically significant effects for women compared to those we report in Table 2 (see Table S7 in the online supplement).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1886">
   <s id="d1e1891">
    The same patterns are evident in the com- bined models with a gender by sexism inter- action term.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1896">
    For all three sexism measures, we see a significant effect of sexism on health among women, but not among men.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1901">
   <s id="d1e1906">
    .05 level.5 Thus, the effect of sexism among
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1911">
   <s id="d1e1916">
    men does not significantly differ either from zero or from women’s effect, which does sig- nificantly differ from zero.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1921">
   <s id="d1e1926">
    What then can we conclude about whether sexism in religious congregations is related to men’s self-rated health? Depending on which null-hypothesis we consider most important (i.e., does men’s effect differ from zero or does men’s effect differ from women’s) we would come to different conclusions (i.e., sexism is not associated with men’s health in
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1931">
   <s id="d1e1936">
    table 1.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1941">
   <s id="d1e1946">
    Total Attender Non-attender Women Men
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1951">
   <s id="d1e1956">
    Note: Income is inflation adjusted family income in thousands of U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1961">
    dollars.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1966">
    Self-rated health is measured on a four-point scale (1 = poor, 4 = excellent).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1971">
    Church attendance is measured on a nine-point scale (0 = never, 8 = more than once a week).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1976">
    Bold denotes differences between church categories or gender categories that are significant at the p &lt; .05 level (two-tailed tests).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1981">
   <s id="d1e1986">
    table 2.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1991">
   <s id="d1e1996">
    Women Men Combined Gender Interaction Models
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2001">
   <s id="d1e2006">
    (.084)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2011">
   <s id="d1e2016">
    Leader –.128∗
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2021">
   <s id="d1e2026">
    (.056)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2031">
   <s id="d1e2036">
    Sexism scale –.061∗∗
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2041">
   <s id="d1e2046">
    (.023)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2051">
   <s id="d1e2056">
    (.094)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2061">
   <s id="d1e2066">
    –.124
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2071">
   <s id="d1e2076">
    (.066)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2081">
   <s id="d1e2086">
    –.049
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2091">
   <s id="d1e2096">
    (.026)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2101">
   <s id="d1e2106">
    (.082)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2111">
   <s id="d1e2116">
    –.136∗ (.055)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2121">
   <s id="d1e2126">
    –.060∗∗ (.023)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2131">
   <s id="d1e2136">
    Board × Male .094
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2141">
   <s id="d1e2146">
    (.123)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2151">
   <s id="d1e2156">
    Leader × Male .033
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2161">
   <s id="d1e2166">
    (.086)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2171">
   <s id="d1e2176">
    (continued)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2181">
   <s id="d1e2186">
    table 2.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2191">
   <s id="d1e2196">
    Note: Standard errors are in parentheses.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2201">
    Income is inflation adjusted (to year 2000) family income in thousands of U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2206">
    dollars.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2211">
    Church attendance is measured on a nine-point scale (0 = never, 8 = more than once a week).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2216">
    Each of the three models uses a different measure of sexism.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2221">
   <s id="d1e2226">
    ∗p &lt; .05; ∗∗p &lt; .01; ∗∗∗p &lt; .001 (two-tailed tests).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2231">
   <s id="d1e2236">
    Figure 2.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2241">
   <s id="d1e2246">
    the first case; sexism is associated with men’s health in the second).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2251">
    This type of situation reveals the limits of frequentist statistics, with its somewhat arbitrary cut-off points and hypothesis testing procedures.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2256">
    A Bayesian approach can provide more information about the possible effects among men.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2261">
   <s id="d1e2266">
    Figure 2 shows the posterior distributions (MCMC sample size = 10,000) of coefficient estimates for the effects of sexism on self- rated health among women and men from the Bayesian linear regression analyses (see Tables S8a, S8b, and S8c in the online sup- plement).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2271">
    These distributions clearly show a negative effect of sexism on health among women, given that 0 is outside the distribu- tions of likely values.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2276">
    The distributions indi- cate the most likely scenario for men is that they also exhibit a negative effect of sexism on health, but the magnitude of the effect is smaller than that of women.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2281">
    Based on these distributions, the probability that the effect of sexism among men is less than zero is 99 per- cent for the board measure, 99 percent for the leader measure, and 98 percent for the sexism scale.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2286">
   <s id="d1e2291">
    84 percent, and 79 percent for the board, leader, and sexism measures, respectively.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l2>
   Are the Health Benefits of Religious Participation Contingent on Congregational Sexism?
  </l2>
  <p id="d1e2296">
   <s id="d1e2301">
    To answer this question, we focus on women because they exhibit an unambiguous negative
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2306">
   <s id="d1e2311">
    effect of congregational sexism on health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2316">
    Figure 3 shows the predicted self-rated health of non-religious women compared to women who attend sexist congregations and women who attend inclusive congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2321">
    These estimates were produced using OLS regres- sion of SRH on the religious attendance cat- egory holding other covariates (age, education, income, race, marital status) constant at their means (see Table S9 in the online supplement for complete regression results).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2326">
    Women who attend inclusive congregations have better self- rated health than non-attenders and women who attend sexist congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2331">
    There is no statistically significant difference in self- rated health between non-attenders and women who attend sexist congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2336">
    These results indicate that women only experience a health benefit from religious participation when they attend religious institutions that are gender inclusive and allow women to hold meaningful leadership roles within the congregation.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   diSCuSSion
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e2341">
   <s id="d1e2346">
    As researchers are beginning to take seriously the impact of structural sexism on health (e.g., Homan 2019), it is important to under- stand how institutional sexism works at vari- ous levels.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2351">
    Religious institutions are prime for scholarly exploration at the meso-level given that research touts the salubrious effects of religious participation on health and well- being, yet studies consistently highlight the rigid gender-based status hierarchies within certain congregations.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2356">
   <s id="d1e2361">
    Figure 3.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2366">
   <s id="d1e2371">
    Note: Estimates were produced using OLS regression of SRH on congregation category holding other covariates (age, education, income, race, marital status) constant at their means.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2376">
    Each panel represents a separate analysis with the definition of “sexist” based on one of the three sexism measures.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2381">
    Estimates shown with 84 percent confidence intervals, which are the appropriate intervals for determining significant differences between the estimates at the p &lt; .05 level based on the ratio of their standard errors.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2386">
    Thus, groups are significantly different from one another if their confidence bands do not overlap.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2391">
    Accordingly, the figure shows that for all three sexism measures, attenders of inclusive congregations have better self-rated health than do the other two groups (who do not significantly differ from one another).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2396">
   <s id="d1e2401">
    religious institutional sexism and health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2406">
    Our findings indicate that the accepted health ben- efits of religious involvement do not extend to all groups, but are contingent on equal access to power and status within religious institutions.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2411">
   <s id="d1e2416">
    Consistent with previous research on structural sexism (Homan 2019) and our theoretical expectations, our findings sug- gest religious structural sexism undermines women’s health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2421">
    Our findings are perhaps most striking for our most restrictive measure of structural sexism: being able to serve on a congregation’s governing body.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2426">
    Women who are members of the most sexist congregations in our sample lack basic decision-making authority within their congregations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2431">
    Alienat- ing women from even rudimentary forms of institutional power appears to be particularly damaging to physical health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2436">
   <s id="d1e2441">
    Religious structural sexism likely affects health via a number of pathways—for exam- ple, undermining psychosocial resources, increasing psychological distress, and increas- ing sexism in other structural domains—but additional scholarship is needed to under- stand how religious institutional sexism influ- ences mental and physical health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2446">
   <s id="d1e2451">
    not be the most important mechanism directly linking congregational sexism and health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2456">
   <s id="d1e2461">
    Instead, participation in a sexist church may be an indicator of exposure to a whole system of structural sexism because it is part of a constellation of positions within various other institutions and relationships.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2466">
    The family may function as a particularly important domain by providing institutional support for gender- stratified roles within the home.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2471">
    To the extent that structural sexism in religious congrega- tions encourages a traditional gender division of household labor, such sexism may be par- ticularly harmful in the context of the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2476">
    Social distancing has limited the social support and engagement normally provided by religious congregations, and the lack of childcare has exacerbated existing gender inequalities in domestic labor and overburdened women, undermining their careers and mental health (Collins et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2481">
    2020; Hamel and Salganicoff 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2486">
    Thus, explor- ing the connections between structural sexism across varied structural domains and levels of analysis represents an important next step in understanding the mechanisms linking reli- gious structural sexism and health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2491">
   <s id="d1e2496">
    Decades of research have documented the salutary effects of religious participation for individual health and well-being (Ellison and Levin 1998; Hill et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2501">
    2011; Koenig et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2506">
    2012; Strawbridge et al.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2511">
   <s id="d1e2516">
    that the health of women who attend sexist congregations is not significantly different from the health of non-attenders.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2521">
    This finding suggests the negative effects of marginaliza- tion offset the beneficial impact of church attendance in the form of social support and advantageous health behaviors.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2526">
    Conversely, women active in inclusive religious groups, where they can serve on governing boards and lead the congregation, display better self- rated health than do women in sexist groups and non-attenders.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2531">
   <s id="d1e2536">
    Why are women in inclusive congrega- tions more likely to report better self-rated health than non-attending women? Our results suggest opportunities for leadership may be a central mechanism for understanding why women in inclusive churches benefit from religious involvement in ways that women in sexist churches or non-attenders do not.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2541">
    Sociologists of religion have long argued that church attendance benefits health in part because it allows individuals to be valued for non-material or non-physical qualities, that is, for their inherent uniqueness, service to others, and wisdom and morality (Ellison and Levin 1998).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2546">
    Key to displaying and being val- ued for these qualities may be assuming lead- ership roles within the church, be it through leading formal church services, religious study classes, or serving on governing boards.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2551">
    Scholars have also noted that opportunities for leadership within a church may be most beneficial to health and well-being for people who do not have opportunities to take on leadership roles in other domains of their lives (Ellison and Levin 1998).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2556">
    Women’s opportu- nities for leadership in inclusive congregations may ameliorate effects of the exclusion they encounter in other domains (e.g., at work) or due to other social statuses (e.g., older adults).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2561">
    In summary, the results among women sug- gest the purported health benefits of religious attendance may only extend to those who have agency within religious institutions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2566">
    Future scholarship in this area should examine the influence of religious institutional factors on the health of other marginalized groups (e.g., sexual minority populations).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2571">
   <s id="d1e2576">
    Consistent with previous research sug- gesting that religion has a greater impact on women’s health than on men’s health (Mirola 1999; Norton et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2581">
    2006; Schieman et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2586">
    2010; Strawbridge et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2591">
    2001), we find marginal to no statistically significant effect of religious structural sexism for men’s self-rated health across the three measures.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2596">
   <s id="d1e2601">
    U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2606">
    state-level institutions, which harms men’s health, or structural sexism within mar- riages, which benefits men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2611">
    We do not find clear evidence that sexism in religious con- gregations is either harmful or beneficial for men’s health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2616">
   <s id="d1e2621">
    Future research should examine why sex- ism within religious institutions may affect men’s health differently than do other forms of structural sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2626">
    As meso-level institu- tions, sexism within religious congregations may not erode men’s health via similar mech- anisms as state-level institutional sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2631">
    Unlike macro-level structural sexism, con- gregational sexism does not decrease invest- ment in state-level social programs that may improve population health, nor does it likely increase masculine risk-taking behaviors (par- ticularly given religious prohibitions).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2636">
    Con- versely, men may not directly benefit from religious institutional sexism, as this form of sexism does not confer the dyadic qualities of marital relationships on health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2641">
    Finally, although the health effects of congregational sexism appear unlike those of either state- level sexism or inter-marital sexism, con- gregational sexism likely contributes to both of these countervailing influences on men’s health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2646">
   <s id="d1e2651">
    (1) creates and sustains gender inequality within marriages, and (2) upholds the ideal of male leadership, thereby perpetuating gender inequality in large-scale political and eco- nomic institutions outside the religious realm.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2656">
   <s id="d1e2661">
    reinforces these other types of sexism, their respective benefits and harms may cancel out.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2666">
    Sociologists of religion have increasingly called for scholars to take an intersectional approach that views religion as providing cul- tural repertories that individuals invoke dif- ferently depending on their location within the social hierarchy (Edgell 2012).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2671">
    As Yukich and Edgell (2020) note, religious beliefs and prac- tices are developed within a specific institu- tional context and acted upon in various ways in different social settings and by people from different social locations (Yukich and Braun- stein 2014; Yukich, Fulton, and Wood 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2676">
    Yet sociologists of religion often ignore how religious repertories are chiefly about race, and this dominant approach reinforces White privilege (Yukich and Edgell 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2681">
    We did not find compelling evidence in our data of a difference in the relationship between reli- gious institutional sexism and health along racial lines, but this may have been a function of the relatively small sample sizes.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2686">
   <s id="d1e2691">
    with an intersectional lens.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2696">
   <s id="d1e2701">
    We centered our study on the United States and thus it is unclear whether our findings would be similar outside of this context.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2706">
    Scholarship on evangelicalism in Colombia suggests a complex relationship between religion, gender, and health, whereby some women and men may benefit from gender traditional religious communities because they stand in opposition to “machismo” cul- ture (Brusco 1995).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2711">
    Within this context, as within the United States, some women may embrace gender traditional religious groups because they require their husbands to abstain from substance use, infidelity, and violence (Brusco 1995; Garcia et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2716">
    2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2721">
    Because some conservative religious institutions lead men to avoid these risky health behaviors, particularly when they stand in contrast to the dominant culture, participation may yield health benefits for certain men and women associated with these traditions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2726">
    Future research on congregational sexism, gender, and health should examine these relationships in a variety of international contexts.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2731">
   <s id="d1e2736">
    Additionally, although we find no evi- dence of an interaction between frequency of attendance and structural sexism, indicat- ing that even minimal exposure to religious structural sexism is harmful to health, service attendance is but one measure of religious involvement.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2741">
    Other indicators of involve- ment within religious institutions may yield different results.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2746">
    For example, people who regularly participate in other activities at their place of worship (e.g., singing in the choir, attending Bible studies, or holding informal leadership positions) may be particularly affected by structural sexism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2751">
    Future research in this area should examine the interaction between congregational sexism and other forms of religious participation on health, and studies should include additional meas- ures of gendered institutional involvement.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2756">
    Our study includes a range of measures of institutional sexism, but there are certainly additional indicators of religious structural sexism that would shed light on the gendered nature of the religion–health connection.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2761">
   <s id="d1e2766">
    There are two important limitations to the current study.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2771">
    First, our data are cross- sectional, so we cannot infer causality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2776">
    Sec- ond, it is important to consider the influence of omitted variables on our key results.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2781">
    For example, Hill and colleagues (2011) note that if individuals with certain conventional and risk-averse personality types are attracted to or selected into religious activities, personality selection processes could account for at least some of the effects of religious attendance.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2786">
    In our case, it may be that women who select into sexist religious environments are in some way different from women who opt out of these contexts in ways that influence their physi- cal health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2791">
    However, it is also likely that the women whose health would be most harmed by sexist institutional arrangements are those who perceive them as particularly unfair and oppressive and who therefore are likely to leave this type of congregation or never select into one to begin with.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2796">
    In that case, our esti- mates of the relationship between institutional sexism and health would be conservative.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2801">
   <s id="d1e2806">
    Despite these limitations, our study pre- sents novel evidence regarding the relationship
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2811">
   <s id="d1e2816">
    between structural sexism and health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2821">
    Even in religious congregations, where engagement has well-known health benefits, structural sexism can undermine women’s well-being.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2826">
    Scholars should continue to examine the con- nections between religious structural sexism and health.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l3>
   Acknowledgments
  </l3>
  <p id="d1e2831">
   <s id="d1e2836">
    We would like to thank Mark Chaves, Miles Taylor, Dawn Carr, John Reynolds, Michael McFarland, Ter- rence Hill, Matt Hauer, Scott Lynch, Lauren Valentino, Simon Brauer, and the Florida State University ARCHI working group for their support of this project.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l3>
   oRCid id
  </l3>
  <p id="d1e2841">
   <s id="d1e2846">
    Patricia Homan https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3609
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2851">
   <s id="d1e2856">
    -8188
   </s>
  </p>
  <l3>
   notes
  </l3>
  <p id="d1e2861">
   <s id="d1e2866">
    Hypernetwork sampling is a technique used to gen- erate a random sample of organizations for which no sampling frame exists by beginning with a ran- dom sample of individuals and asking them to name organizations to which they are connected (see McPherson 1982, 2001; National Congregations
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2871">
   <s id="d1e2876">
    Study 2019).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2881">
   <s id="d1e2886">
    An additional wave was conducted in 2018 to 2019.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2891">
   <s id="d1e2896">
    Linked data used in this analysis are derived from Sensitive Data Files of the NCS, obtained under special arrangements designed to minimize the risk that participating congregations will be pub- licly identified.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2901">
    These data are not available from the authors.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2906">
    Persons interested in obtaining NCS Sensitive Data Files should contact Mark Chaves at mac58@soc.duke.edu.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2911">
   <s id="d1e2916">
    The majority of congregations contained only one GSS respondent, but some contained more.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2921">
    Our sam- ple of attenders contains 814 women representing 770 unique congregations, with an average of 1.4 women per congregation (range = [1, 4]), and 575 men rep- resenting 557 unique congregations, with an average of 1.0 men per congregation (range = [1, 3]).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2926">
   <s id="d1e2931">
    Chow test results: t = –.82, p = –.56 for board;
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2936">
   <s id="d1e2941">
    t = –.05, p = .97 for leader; and t = –.35, p = .79 for sexism scale.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2946">
   <s id="d1e2951">
    .59, p = .44 for board; F = .15, p = .70 for leader; and F = .19, p = .66 for sexism scale.
   </s>
  </p>
 </body>
</html>