<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="discourse.v4_cn.css"?><html xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://wkwsci.ntu.edu.sg/discourse# discourse.v4_cn.xsd"> 
 <head><title>
  Better sleep, better trip: The effect of sleep quality on tourists' experiences
 </title>
 </head>
 <body>
  <l1>
   Better sleep, better trip: The effect of sleep quality on tourists' experiences
  </l1>
<abstract>
  <p id="d1e191">
   <s id="d1e196">
    <arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="research_gap">Given the importance of sleep to travelers and the scarcity of tourism research on this topic,</arg> <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">our study presents a pioneering attempt to explore the relationship between sleep quality and tourists' experiences.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e201"><arg argID="003" type="support" supportType="method">We employed an instrumental-variable three-way ﬁxed-effects regression model to estimate this relationship using TripAdvisor review data from three U.S.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e211"><arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="result">Results suggest that sleep quality signiﬁcantly and positively inﬂuences the tourist experience.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e216"><arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="result">Other travel-related variables, such as demographic, trip-related, and destination-related factors, are also found to moderate the effect of sleep quality on the tourist experience.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e221"><arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Our study provides theoretical and practical implications around managing sleep quality to enhance tourists' experiences.</arg></s>
  </p>
</abstract>
<intro>
<l2>intoduction</l2>
  <p id="d1e251">
   <s id="d1e256">
    <arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-define">As an essential biological and physiological mechanism, sleep in humans can be deﬁned as an active, repetitive and reversible state of perceptual disengagement from and unresponsiveness to the environment (Carskadon &amp; Dement, 2005).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e261">
    <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">Although questions remain regarding the function and mechanisms of sleep, sleep plays a crucial role in one's daily functions, including behav- ior, emotion, and attention as well as long-term aspects such as health and biological processes (Medic, Wille, &amp; Hemels, 2017).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e266">
    <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="general_statement" comments_Arthur="OK, literature_highlight_claim也OK?">Sleep is a form of recuperation involving the reorganization of neural activity and restoration of organism functions (Hobson, 2005).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e271"><arg argID="003" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">When people enjoy sound sleep, their bodies and brains rest and recover, leading to increased physical, cognitive, and psychological well-being (Hamilton, Nelson, Stevens, &amp; Kitzman, 2007; Pallesen, Larsen, &amp; Bjorvatn, 2016).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e276">
    <arg argID="003" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">Conversely, suboptimal sleep can result in affective, cognitive, and psychological impairment; poor physical health; sedentary behavior and inactivity; and a greater risk of disease (Brand &amp; Kirov, 2011; Yoo, Gujar, Hu, Jolesz, &amp; Walker, 2007), all of which can compromise one's quality of life.</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e281">
   <s id="d1e286">
    <arg argID="010" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">It is not uncommon for tourists to encounter unfamiliar sleeping environments and potentially suffer from insomnia or other sleep disorders while traveling (Pallesen et al., 2016).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e291">
    <arg argID="010" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">A good night's sleep is essential for many travelers enjoying the travel experience (Valtonen &amp; Moisander, 2012).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e296">
    <arg argID="011" type="claim" claimType="topic_centrality">Sleep quality is a crucial predictor of hotel guests' satisfaction and overall experience.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e301">
    <arg argID="012" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">Whereas sound sleep can facilitate tourists' experiential enjoyment, sleep deprivation may hinder travel activities and elicit negative feelings such as frustration and fatigue, ultimately leading to a generally unfavorable travel experience (Crompton, 1979).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e306">
    <arg argID="012" type="claim" claimType="topic_centrality">As such, sleep quality appears to be a vital factor in individuals' overall travel experiences.</arg></s>
  </p>
  
  <p id="d1e381">
   <s id="d1e386">
    <arg argID="019" type="claim" claimType="topic_centrality">Given the importance of sleep to travelers and the role of lodging as the sole business to provide sleep for travelers,</arg> <arg argID="020" type="claim" claimType="research_gap">there is surprisingly little research on sleep and sleep quality in the tourism and hospitality literature, particularly from the tourist perspective.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e391">
    <arg argID="021" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">Extant research has just unveiled antecedents of sleep quality for tourists (Mao, Yang, &amp; Wang, 2018).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e396">
    <arg argID="022" type="claim" claimType="research_gap">However, to the best of our knowledge, no studies have yet considered the consequences of sleep quality for travelers and tourists' experiences.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e401"><arg claimType="research_objective" argID="023" type="claim">To ﬁll this research gap, we aim to (a) uncover the effect of sleep quality on tourist experience and (b) empirically inves- tigate factors moderating the effect.</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e406">
   <s id="d1e411">
    <arg argID="030" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Our study enriches the current knowledge base in the following ways.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e416">
    <arg argID="031" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">First, we provide a general literature review on sleep quality and the tourist experience and propose a research framework under the sleep restriction paradigm.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e421">
    <arg argID="032" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Second, our study represents a pioneering effort to empirically evaluate how sleep quality inﬂuences tourists' experiences based on online review data,</arg> <arg argID="033" type="claim" claimType="literature-compare/relate" comment="OK">which is different from most other sleep-related studies that use diaries, questionnaires, and experimental approaches.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e426">
    <arg argID="034" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Third, we contribute to the overall sleep literature by examining sleep consequences in a non-routine environment, a largely unexplored setting.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e431">
    <arg argID="035" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Finally, our ﬁndings offer practical guidelines and suggestions to enhance tourists' experiences through sleep quality.</arg></s>
  </p>
</intro>
  <p id="d1e436">
   <s id="d1e441">
    Literature review
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e446">
   <s id="d1e451">
    Sleep quality
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e456">
   <s id="d1e461">
    Sleep quality refers to how well one sleeps regardless of sleep duration (Crain, Brossoit, &amp; Fisher, 2018); in other words, the term captures a person's sleep experience based on an evaluation of their sleep condition (Hon &amp; Fung, 2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e466">
    To measure sleep quality, scholars have used objective methods, such as measuring interbeat intervals and the number of awakenings (Harvey, Stinson, Whitaker, Moskovitz, &amp; Virk, 2008), and subjective methods including one's difﬁculty falling to sleep and staying asleep throughout the night (Crain et al., 2018; Harvey et al., 2008).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e471">
    Considered a more signiﬁcant and manifest measure than its objec- tive counterpart (Polo-Kantola &amp; Erkkola, 2004), subjective sleep quality relates to one's perception of sleep quality and inﬂuences one's activity-related motivation the following day (Fung &amp; Hon, 2019).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e476">
   <s id="d1e481">
    A main research stream on sleep focuses on understanding how sleep quality affects human activities (Dewald, Meijer, Oort, Kerkhof, &amp; Bögels, 2010; Halson, 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e486">
    A growing body of literature suggests that low sleep quality could exert substantial neg- ative consequences on human performance.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e491">
    For adults, adolescents, and children, the ramiﬁcations of poor sleep quality include impaired sustained attention, deﬁcits in learning and memory, lower school performance, and unusual neurobehaviors (Durmer &amp; Dinges, 2005; Shochat, Cohen-Zion, &amp; Tzischinsky, 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e496">
    In the sport literature, while better sleep quality can contribute to high mental and physical performance as well as faster physical and emotional recovery among athletes (Kölling et al., 2016), poor quality sleep can trigger an imbalance of the autonomic nervous system and cognitive functioning (Halson, 2014) that results in mediocre performance.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e501">
    It can be, therefore, concluded that sleep quality can have signiﬁcant effects on human performance.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e506">
   <s id="d1e511">
    Tourist experience
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e516">
   <s id="d1e521">
    Tourism primarily represents an intangible commodity with utility accumulated from one's experiences and memories related to travel.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e526">
    No consensus has been reached regarding a precise deﬁnition of travel experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e531">
    Nevertheless, many researchers have sought to deﬁne this concept over the decades.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e536">
    For instance, Clawson and Knetsch (1966) proposed tourist experiences as com- prising inﬂuences and personal outcomes that begin before a trip and persist even after a tourist returns from a destination.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e541">
    Otto and Ritchie (1996) framed the tourism experience as tourists' subjective state during a service encounter.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e546">
    Tung and Ritchie (2011) deﬁned the term as an individual's subjective evaluation of and experience with events related to tourist activities beginning be- fore, during, and after a trip.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e551">
    In essence, the tourist experience comprises everything a tourist experiences at a destination, includ- ing activity, cognition, emotion, perception, and behavior (Oh, Fiore, &amp; Jeoung, 2007).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e556">
   <s id="d1e561">
    Scholars have identiﬁed an array of factors that inﬂuence the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e566">
    In general, tourists' experiences are shaped by individual characteristics (e.g., health, culture, previous visits, and demographic features), perceived human interactions in the destination (e.g., the host community's attitude, friendly interpersonal relationships, and service quality), the physical environ- ment (e.g., scenic beauty and landscape, weather, accommodations, and transportation), and situational factors (e.g., the purpose of a trip and one's travel companions) (Walls, Okumus, Wang, &amp; Kwun, 2011).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e571">
    The effect of sleep on tourists' experiences can be simply contextualized as the interaction between individual characteristics and the physical environment, although this interac- tion has not been empirically tested.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e576">
   <s id="d1e581">
    Sleep quality research in tourism and hospitality
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e586">
   <s id="d1e591">
    Tourism studies have acknowledged the importance of sleep in travel (e.g., Fung &amp; Hon, 2019; Mao et al., 2018; Valtonen &amp; Veijola, 2011).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e596">
    Research in travel and mobility has revealed that jet lag and trip distance can impair travelers' sleep quality due to fatigue and changes in space and time zones (Silva, Pascoal, Silva, &amp; Paiva, 2016; Stone &amp; Turner, 1997).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e601">
    Recently, scholars have explored sleep in tourism and hospitality more systematically with qualitative and quantitative approaches.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e606">
    Table 1 presents a brief summarized review of the topics and key ﬁndings of prior sleep quality research in tourism and hospitality.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e611">
   <s id="d1e616">
    Mao et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e621">
    (2018)'s seminal work on hotel sleep quality is central to our current study.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e626">
   <s id="d1e631">
    sleep quality determinants for travelers by emphasizing the signiﬁcance of personal differences and highlighting the importance of sleep environment changes, which could serve as a foundation for sleep research in unfamiliar sleeping environments.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e636">
   <s id="d1e641">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark4">
    </span>
    Table 1
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e646">
   <s id="d1e651">
    Review of previous sleep quality studies in tourism and hospitality.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e656">
   <s id="d1e661">
    Furthermore, their research provided empirical insight on how travel- and hotel-related factors affect hotel sleep quality, contrib- uting to a systematic understanding of factors shaping travelers' sleep quality in hotels.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e666">
    Although their study has substantiated our knowledge on hotel sleep quality's antecedents, it does not examine hotel sleep quality's consequences, especially in the domain of tourist experience, which leaves the other door open.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e671">
    In sum, our review of the hospitality and tourism studies revealed no evidence of comprehensive and systematic probes of sleep quality and its impacts on the tourist experience exclusive of a possible exception by Fung and Hon (2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e676">
    The paucity of insights on consequences of sleep in travel stresses the need to unravel the possible effect from sleep quality to the tourist experience, which could signiﬁcantly advance our knowledge of tourists' sleep quality on subsequent tourist experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e681">
   <s id="d1e686">
    Research framework
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e691">
   <s id="d1e696">
    Sleep quality and tourist experience
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e701">
   <s id="d1e706">
    Sleep quality and tourist experience tend to be mutually inﬂuential; in general, good sleep leads to a satisfactory tourist expe- rience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e711">
    As indicated by Oh et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e716">
    (2007), activity, affect, and cognition are essential components of the travel experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e721">
    Therefore, we developed our research framework by linking sleep quality to distinct experiential components based on studies in the liter- ature related to sleep (Colten &amp; Altevogt, 2006; Hamilton et al., 2007) and tourism (Larsen, Brun, &amp; Øgaard, 2009; Oh, Parks, &amp; Demicco, 2002) under the research framework of sleep restriction paradigm (Dinges, Pack, Williams, Gillen, Powell, Ott, Aptowicz, &amp; Pack, 1997).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e726">
    According to neuroscience research, a vital set of neocortical structures in the prefrontal cortex are part of a brain network that have the capacity to control emotions, hinder cognition, and inhibit behaviors (Miller, 2000).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e731">
    Sleep restriction will impair the prefrontal cortex by reducing glucose metabolism (Dahl &amp; Lewin, 2002), and thereby disturbing the subsequent behavior, emotion and cognition.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e736">
    Additionally, poor sleep will impede the body's stress systems and the release of stress hormones, which may have negative functional consequences for the way people deal with everyday challenges (Meerlo, Sgoifo, &amp; Suchecki, 2008).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e741">
   <s id="d1e746">
    Better sleep quality contributes to greater motivation for physical activity due to the increased energy levels commonly asso- ciated with better-quality sleep (Holfeld &amp; Ruthig, 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e751">
    Many tourist activities involve some degree of physical intensity, and without a baseline level of energy, poor physical performance may compromise tourists' experiences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e756">
    Sleep quality also inﬂuences individuals' affect and cognition the next day.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e761">
   <s id="d1e766">
    reactivity such as enthusiasm, energy, and joy and increasing emotional coping; comparatively, poor sleep may exacerbate negative affect such as tension, depression, anxiety, anger, displeasure, fatigue, and lethargy (Kahn, Sheppes, &amp; Sadeh, 2013; Scott &amp; Judge, 2006).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e771">
    As outcomes of tourism events (Oh et al., 2007), these emotions drive tourists' perceptions and memories of their travel experiences (Trauer &amp; Ryan, 2005).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e776">
   <s id="d1e781">
    Likewise, studies have shown that sleep signiﬁcantly inﬂuences cognitive functioning including motivation, attention, judgment, and memory (Banks &amp; Dinges, 2007; Gerber, Brand, Holsboer-Trachsler, &amp; Pühse, 2010; Yoo et al., 2007), which are used to process travel experiences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e786">
    Negative cognition including deﬁcits in concentration, alertness, vigilance, reaction, and recollection (Colten &amp; Altevogt, 2006), which result from poor sleep, may compromise positive thinking and beliefs and subse- quently deteriorate tourists' experiential evaluations (del Bosque &amp; San Martín, 2008).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e791">
    In sum, sleep deprivation may reduce the executive function of the brain, yield expected increase in fatigue, and compromise attention, activity, emotion, and cognitive efﬁciency Acheson et al., 2007).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e796">
    When measures of behavior, mood, and cognition are combined, evidence shows that the mean level of functioning for sleep deprived individuals reaches 90% of non-sleep-deprived individuals (Pilcher &amp; Huffcutt, 1996).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e801">
   <s id="d1e806">
    Our study attempts to test and reveal the effects of sleep quality on the tourist experience through the aforementioned func- tioning in an implicit way.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e811">
    Sleep is related to neural processes that may inﬂuence one's physical, emotional, and cognitive func- tioning the following day (Dewald et al., 2010).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e816">
    Accumulating evidence suggests that poor sleep quality reduces the overnight brain activity needed for somatic and neurocognitive functioning (Brand &amp; Kirov, 2011).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e821">
    To ensure a pleasant travel experience, sleep quality is essential for tourists on the road because sleep can help them recover from their journey.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e826">
    Thus, sleep quality is a powerful determinant of hotel guests' satisfaction, happiness, and tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e831">
    In other words, sleep quality affects the tourist experience in a positive manner.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e836">
   <s id="d1e841">
    Moderators of sleep quality-tourist experience relationship
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e846">
   <s id="d1e851">
    Scholars have suggested that the tourist experience may vary according to a multitude of factors such as individual character- istics, trip-related characteristics, and destination-related characteristics (Walls et al., 2011).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e856">
    We propose that the interplay of these factors and sleep quality may exert signiﬁcant effects on the tourist experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e861">
   <s id="d1e866">
    Demographic features such as age may interact with sleep quality to inﬂuence the tourist experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e871">
   <s id="d1e876">
    erature, we contend that the inﬂuence of sleep quality on tourists' experiences depends on age.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e881">
    Studies have reported that seniors experience sleep deterioration due to aging, illness, and pain (Ancuelle et al., 2015); accordingly, sleep quality can be more critical for them compared to other age groups while traveling.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e886">
    Other age groups can more easily adjust their sleep patterns while at home or on the road due to their daily routines.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e891">
    Conversely, senior travelers may ﬁnd it challenging to cope with the changing sleep environments, making sleep quality a vital factor in their travel.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e896">
    As such, sleep quality exerts a more substantial effect on the tourist experience for older travelers.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e901">
   <s id="d1e906">
    Trip-related factors, including travel type, trip distance, and past travel experience, are also hypothesized to moderate the ef- fects of sleep quality on the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e911">
    Studies have revealed travel types as possible inﬂuencers for the tourist experience on important characteristics such as quality of sleep (Liu, Law, Rong, Li, &amp; Hall, 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e916">
    Travel types are typically classiﬁed into ei- ther business or leisure, the latter of which can be further divided into traveling alone, as a couple, with family, or with friends (Xiang, Du, Ma, &amp; Fan, 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e921">
    Business travelers are expected to encounter high levels of stress and fatigue as they are more likely to undertake work-related activities in destinations (Chen et al., 2018); therefore, these travelers need better sleep to recover for the next day's activities.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e926">
   <s id="d1e931">
    Among leisure travelers, solo travelers must navigate travel barriers and issues independently without travel companions, which may lead to a suboptimal tourist experience with inferior sleep quality (Zhu &amp; Fan, 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e936">
    The effect of sleep quality on the tourist experience should be strengthened for the travel types that are more prone to stress and fatigue.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e941">
    Thus, some travelers (e.g., business and solo travelers) may rely more on other factors such as sleep quality to reduce stress and tiredness and achieve an overall favorable tourist experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e946">
   <s id="d1e951">
    Trip distance presents a barrier to sleep quality and the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e956">
    Long-haul travel can adversely affect tourists' ex- periences due to fatigue, jet lag, and negative emotions (Silva et al., 2016; Zhu &amp; Fan, 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e961">
    Sleep can be used to mitigate tourists' negative experiences and recover their energy as an effective means.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e966">
    In addition, long-distance travel would take up more trans- portation time and suppress the time for sleep, which may negatively inﬂuence sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e971">
    A good night's sleep is essential to surmounting these challenges.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e976">
    There is a heightened effect from sleep quality to the tourist experience for long-distance travel.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e981">
    Sleep quality thus becomes an important factor in enhancing the tourist experience when people participate in long-distance travel.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e986">
   <s id="d1e991">
    In terms of past travel experience, well-traveled tourists may enjoy better-quality tourist experiences given their accumulated travel knowledge and strategies for handling inconvenience and risk (Li, Cheng, Kim, &amp; Petrick, 2008; Lo, Law, &amp; Cheung, 2011).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e996">
    For example, experienced travelers may get used to the often-changed sleeping conditions and know how to mitigate potential sleep problems in new sleeping environments.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1001">
    The more travel an individual has, the more gained experience and knowledge that person attains to deal with potential sleep issues during the trip.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1006">
    This implies a reduced need of sleep quality for well- traveled individuals to retain their tourist experiences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1011">
    As a result, sleep quality presumably plays a lesser role in the tourist ex- perience for veteran travelers.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1016">
   <s id="d1e1021">
    The attraction types could also moderate the relationship between sleep quality and the tourist experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1026">
   <s id="d1e1031">
    (b) level of engagement.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1036">
   <s id="d1e1041">
    attraction types.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1046">
    The signiﬁcance of the association between activities and sleep quality depends on activity features such as level and type, with a moderate level being optimal (Hellström et al., 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1051">
    In addition, bright light in the daytime has been tied to sleep-promoting effects (Hood, Bruck, &amp; Kennedy, 2004).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1056">
    More physical intensive and higher engagement types of tourist attrac- tions demand more arousal and stimulation for tourists, which are highly dependent on with their sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1061">
    Accordingly, the effect of sleep quality on the tourist experience may be relatively low for indoor attractions with less physically intense activities compared to outdoor attractions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1066">
    Therefore, the effect of sleep quality on the tourist experience is expected to be more important for attractions requiring a high level of engagement.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1071">
   <s id="d1e1076">
    Research method
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1081">
   <s id="d1e1086">
    Data collection
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1091">
   <s id="d1e1096">
    We collected our dataset from TripAdvisor, focusing on tourists' sleep quality and travel experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1101">
    The sleep quality score was derived from tourists' ratings of sleep quality in hotel reviews, whereas the tourist experience rating was collected from the rating of each visited attraction.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1106">
    Three U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1111">
    urban destinations (New York City [NYC], Las Vegas [LV], and Orlando) were se- lected to represent three destination types.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1116">
    A web crawler was developed to crawl TripAdvisor information in July 2019.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1121">
    We ob- tained 317,025 hotel reviews and 106,175 attraction reviews for NYC, 382,542 hotel reviews and 63,667 attraction reviews for LV, and 439,407 hotel reviews and 254,664 attraction reviews for Orlando.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1126">
    TripAdvisor only asked some reviewers to leave a sleep quality rating; therefore, the subset of sleep quality data was smaller than the original crawled dataset.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1131">
   <s id="d1e1136">
    We then matched hotel sleep quality data with attraction experience data (a one-to-many mapping), using two key data points for merging: (1) user name and (2) hotel check-in month and attraction experience month.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1141">
    Due to the design of the TripAdvisor platform, some attraction rating posts, especially those posted quite some time ago, did not contain information on experience month.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1146">
    We could not merely use the posting date to match review information, as the date on which a review was posted may differ substantially from the actual travel date (Yang, Wu, &amp; Yang, 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1151">
    Under this stringent matching criterion, our ﬁnal dataset included 7721 observations: 1899 for NYC, 730 for LV, and 5092 for Orlando.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1156">
    Fig.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1161">
    1 presents the maps on the number of observations from each hotel and attraction in these three cities.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1166">
   <s id="d1e1171">
    (Note: NYC in the top, LV in the middle, and Orlando in the bottom.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1176">
   <s id="d1e1181">
    Empirical model
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1186">
   <s id="d1e1191">
    We used a three-way ﬁxed-effects regression to understand the effect of sleep quality on the travel experience:
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1196">
   <s id="d1e1201">
    experienceijkt ¼ sleepikt • γ þ Xitβ þ μj þ τk þ δt þ εijt
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1206">
   <s id="d1e1211">
    where i indexes each tourist, j indexes the attraction where the experience was evaluated, k indexes the hotel stayed, and t indi- cates the month of travel.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1216">
    The dependent variable, experience, captures the tourist experience at a particular attraction; the major variable of interest, sleep, measures tourists' sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1221">
    A set of tourist-speciﬁc control variables were also obtained from TripAdvisor, including sociodemographics and tripographics.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1226">
    The three ﬁxed-effects, μj, τk, and δt, represent attraction-speciﬁc, hotel-speciﬁc, and year–month speciﬁc effects in the model, respectively.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1231">
   <s id="d1e1236">
    experienceijkt ¼ sleepikt • γ þ sleepikt • Zit • ρ þ Xit β þ μj þ τk þ δt þ εijt
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1241">
   <s id="d1e1246">
    experienceijkt ¼ sleepikt • γ þ sleepikt • Zj • ρ þ Xitβ þ μj þ τk þ δt þ εijt
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1251">
   <s id="d1e1256">
    The three-way ﬁxed-effects regression possesses several advantages.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1261">
    First and foremost, the three ﬁxed-effects terms are able to capture the confounding factors that are time-speciﬁc (e.g., weather, seasonality, and event), attraction-speciﬁc (e.g., facilities, infrastructure, and location), and hotel-speciﬁc (e.g., location and neighborhood serenity).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1266">
    After embracing these factors, the model can better unveil the sleep-experience relationship by alleviating the omitted variable biases.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1271">
    Second, compared to the al- ternative model, hierarchical linear models that specify the random effects for attraction- and hotel-speciﬁc effects, the ﬁxed- effects model does not require the ﬁxed effects to be independent of the error terms, and therefore, the model can generate more reliable estimates.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1276">
   <s id="d1e1281">
    In the econometric model, the variable of interest, sleep, can suffer from the endogeneity issue, which ultimately leads to a biased and inconsistent estimate of γ The endogeneity concern stems from two aspects.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1286">
    First, satisfying tourist activities and ex- periences can also contribute to the exceptional quality of sleep (Filep, 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1291">
    Sleep quality and human activity can affect each other through complex, reciprocal interactions including multiple physiological and psychological pathways (Chennaoui, Arnal, Sauvet, &amp; Léger, 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1296">
    As such, this bidirectional relationship induces a simultaneity endogeneity to the equation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1301">
    Second, the variable sleep can highly correlate with the equation's error term, which covered tourist-speciﬁc factors that were not incorpo- rated into the model of travel experience, such as physical and mental health conditions (Mao et al., 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1306">
   <s id="d1e1311">
    instrumental variables should be considered, and an instrumental-variable estimator, such as Two-Stage Least Squares (2SLS), can be used to estimate the model (Greene, 2007).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1316">
    To handle the high-dimensional ﬁxed-effects model in a more efﬁcient way, we further implemented the full Gauss-Seidel algorithm, which generates identical estimation results to 2SLS estimators with dummy variables capturing the ﬁxed effects (Guimaraes &amp; Portugal, 2010).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1321">
   <s id="d1e1326">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark5">
    </span>
    Fig.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1331">
    1.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1336">
    Location map of matched attractions and hotels.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1341">
   <s id="d1e1346">
    Fig.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1351">
    1 (continued).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1356">
   <s id="d1e1361">
    Variable deﬁnitions and descriptive statistics
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1366">
   <s id="d1e1371">
    The dependent variable, experience, conveys the 5-point TripAdvisor rating of a tourist's travel experience at a speciﬁc attrac- tion.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1376">
    The independent variable, sleep, is the major variable of interest and indicates tourists' self-reported 5-point sleep quality from the matched hotel review of the same tourist on the same trip.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1381">
   <s id="d1e1386">
    <ul>
     <p>
      same_month: a dummy variable indicating whether an attraction review was posted in the same month of travel.
     </p>
     <p>
      member_age: the number of years a tourist has been a TripAdvisor member.
     </p>
     <p>
      age: the age group reported by the tourist in their TripAdvisor proﬁle.
     </p>
    </ul>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1391">
    Five groups exist: 18–24, 25–34, 35–49, 50–64, and 65+.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p>
   travel: the travel type reported by the tourist in the hotel review.
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1396">
   <s id="d1e1401">
    We included the moderating variable Z.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1406">
    For example, age, travel, lndistance, and lncities_visited were each used as a moderator to test the moderating roles of demographic feature, trip-related factor, and past travel experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1411">
   <s id="d1e1416">
    <ul>
     <p>
      type: the attraction type of the attraction a tourist visited.
     </p>
    </ul>
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1421">
   <s id="d1e1426">
    To handle the endogeneity issue associated with sleep quality, we introduced an instrumental variable, sleep_others.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1431">
    It is de- ﬁned as the average sleep quality rating of other hotel guests in the same hotel.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1436">
    First, sleep_others is highly correlated with sleep quality, and this high correlation can be explained by the inﬂuence of hotel facilities, infrastructure, and location on all hotel guests (Mao et al., 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1441">
    Second, sleep_others is not expected to inﬂuence the travel experience, and therefore, can serve as a potential instrumental variable to tackle simultaneity endogeneity.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1446">
    Third, sleep_others does not associate with the uncontrolled individual characteristics of tourists (e.g., health conditions) in the error term of the equation.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1451">
   <s id="d1e1456">
    Table 2 presents the descriptive statistics of variables included in the model.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1461">
    The average experience rating was 4.476 out of 5, higher than the average rating of sleep quality (4.282).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1466">
    Within our sample, 54.7% of visitors posted the review in the same month as their trip.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1471">
    The average duration of TripAdvisor membership was 5.091 years.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1476">
    For categorical variables, the sample was domi- nated by middle-aged tourists, with 44.55% between 35 and 49 and 32.17% between 50 and 64 years old.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1481">
    In terms of travel type, more than half traveled with family, accounting for 52.62% of the sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1486">
    Another 28.55% traveled as a couple.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1491">
    Regarding attraction types, amusement park experiences dominated the sample, encompassing 52.52% of observations.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1496">
   <s id="d1e1501">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark6">
    </span>
    Descriptive statistics of variables in empirical model.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1506">
   <s id="d1e1511">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark7">
    </span>
    a Only the last half-year data was used for this variable).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1516">
   <s id="d1e1521">
    Empirical ﬁndings
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1526">
   <s id="d1e1531">
    Estimation results
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1536">
   <s id="d1e1541">
    Table 3 presents the instrumental-variable estimation results of our empirical models with all observations in the sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1546">
    We conducted underidentiﬁcation and weak identiﬁcation tests to test the validity of our instrumental variable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1551">
    Across all models, the Kleibergen-Paap rk L.M.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1556">
    statistic for underidentiﬁcation test was statistically signiﬁcant, suggesting the equation is identiﬁed.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1561">
    Re- garding the weak identiﬁcation test, the Cragg–Donald Wald F-statistic and the Kleibergen-Paap rk F statistic were greater than the ‘rule of thumb’ of 10, rejecting the null hypothesis of weak instruments (Baum, Schaffer, &amp; Stillman, 2007).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1566">
    The only excep- tions were the weak identiﬁcation test results in Models 6 and 8 with limited sample size.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1571">
    While the Kleibergen-Paap rk F statistic of Model 6 was slightly below 10, Model 8 had a the Cragg–Donald Wald F-statistic close to 0 after introducing an interaction term with the endogenous model.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1576">
   <s id="d1e1581">
    Reviewer-related information was incomplete in many reviews.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1586">
    Therefore, we added each variable one by one to gauge the stability of our results.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1591">
    Note that we added three ﬁxed-effects into the model, and a small number of singleton observations were dropped from the model.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1596">
    Model 1 was taken as the baseline model, excluding variables with missing values.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1601">
    With a sample size of 7721, the R-square was 0.293, and the adjusted R-square was 0.201.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1606">
    The coefﬁcient for sleep was 0.139, which was statis- tically signiﬁcant; that is, a 1-point increase in a tourist's 5-point sleep rating would elicit a 0.139-point increase in their 5-point experience rating.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1611">
    For the control variable, same_month was negative and signiﬁcant, indicating that reviews posted in the same month as a trip were associated with a lower rating.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1616">
    The other control variable, member_age, was also negative and signiﬁcant; a longer TripAdvisor membership was associated with a lower rating, suggesting that experienced travelers have more stringent ex- pectations of their experience.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1621">
   <s id="d1e1626">
    Based on Model 1, Model 2 included the categorical variable of age group, Model 3 contained the categorical variable of travel type, and Model 4 integrated travel distance (in log).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1631">
    The sample size of each model differed due to missing values in each addi- tional variable; sample sizes ranged from N = 3141 (Model 2) to N = 7620 (Model 3).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1636">
    Across these three models, sleep was con- sistently estimated to be positive and signiﬁcant.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1641">
   <s id="d1e1646">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark8">
    </span>
    Instrumental-variable estimation results of empirical models on the effect of sleep quality.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1651">
   <s id="d1e1656">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark9">
    </span>
    a Only the last half-year data was used for this model.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1661">
    IV test 1 indicates the Kleibergen-Paap rk LM statistic for underidentiﬁcation test, IV test 2 indicates the Cragg- Donald Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test, and IV test 3 indicates Kleibergen-Paap rk Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1666">
    Clustered standard errors
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark10">
    </span>
    based on attractions were presented in parentheses).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1671">
   <s id="d1e1676">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark11">
    </span>
    ⁎⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.01 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1681">
   <s id="d1e1686">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark12">
    </span>
    ⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.05 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1691">
   <s id="d1e1696">
    ⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.10 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1701">
   <s id="d1e1706">
    that age group information barely helped explain the experience rating.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1711">
    The results of Model 3 show that compared to couple travelers (travel = COUPLES), solo travelers reported lower experience ratings whereas family travelers and those traveling with friends posted higher ratings.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1716">
   <s id="d1e1721">
    In Model 4, lndistance was estimated to be negative but insigniﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1726">
    In Model 5, into which all the above-mentioned variables were incorporated, the coefﬁcient of sleep was also positive and statistically signiﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1731">
    In Model 6, because we could not track a reviewer's precise travel experience (e.g., the number of cities visited) when their review was posted, we limited the sample to reviews posted within the last 6 months (N = 475), so current information could be used as a proxy.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1736">
    The effect of past travel experience, lncities_visited, was not statistically signiﬁcant in this model, whereas the major variable of interest, sleep, was pos- itive and signiﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1741">
    Based on the results of Models 1–6, the positive and signiﬁcant effect of sleep quality on the tourist experi- ence was conﬁrmed under different model speciﬁcations.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1746">
   <s id="d1e1751">
    In Models 7 and 8 of Table 3, we introduced the interaction term sleep*lndistance and sleep*lncities_visited, respectively, to examine if travel distance and past travel experience moderate the effect of sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1756">
    The coefﬁcient of sleep*lndistance is insigniﬁcant, indicating that the moderating role of travel distance was not supported by the result.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1761">
    The coefﬁcient of sleep* lncities_visited was estimated to be positive but insigniﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1766">
    Therefore, travel experience was not found to be a moderator of sleep quality-tourist experience relationship.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1771">
   <s id="d1e1776">
    We further estimate the model for different age and travel type sub-groups.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1781">
    Table 4 presents the instrumental-variable estima- tion results.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1786">
    Models 9 to 11 estimate the model for three different age groups.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1791">
   <s id="d1e1796">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark13">
    </span>
    Table 4
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1801">
   <s id="d1e1806">
    Instrumental-variable estimation results of empirical models with different age and travel type groups.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1811">
   <s id="d1e1816">
    IV test 1 indicates the Kleibergen-Paap rk LM statistic for underidentiﬁcation test, IV test 2 indicates the Cragg-Donald Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test, and IV test 3 indicates Kleibergen-Paap rk Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1821">
    Clustered standard errors based on attractions were presented in parentheses).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1826">
   <s id="d1e1831">
    ⁎⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.01 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1836">
   <s id="d1e1841">
    ⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.05 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1846">
   <s id="d1e1851">
    ⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.10 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1856">
   <s id="d1e1861">
    “age = 18-24” and “age = 65+,” we merged these age groups into the closest one.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1866">
    Models 9 to 11 estimate the model for three different age groups.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1871">
    The positive effect of sleep quality was largest and signiﬁcant for old travelers (age = 50+).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1876">
    This result high- lights a more substantial impact of sleep quality on the senior generation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1881">
    Therefore, age turns out to moderate the impact of sleep quality on the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1886">
    Models 12 to 15 estimate the model for tourists of different travel types.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1891">
    Note that the model for “travel = SOLO” cannot be estimated due to small sample size.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1896">
    Business travelers (travel = BUSINESS) were found to witness the largest effect of sleep quality, followed by family travelers (travel = FAMILY).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1901">
    Therefore, the effect of sleep varied by travel type.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1906">
    As indicated in the research framework, the impact of sleep quality on tourists' travel experience can vary across different attraction types they visited.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1911">
    Table 5 presents the instrumental-variable estimation results for different types of attrac- tions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1916">
    The coefﬁcient of sleep was estimated to be signiﬁcant and positive in outdoor attractions, such as Sights &amp; Landmarks and Amusement Parks.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1921">
   <s id="d1e1926">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark14">
    </span>
    Table 5
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1931">
   <s id="d1e1936">
    Instrumental-variable estimation results of empirical models with different attraction types.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1941">
   <s id="d1e1946">
    IV test 1 indicates the Kleibergen-Paap rk LM statistic for underidentiﬁcation test, IV test 2 indicates the Cragg-Donald Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test, and IV test 3 indicates Kleibergen-Paap rk Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1951">
    Clustered standard errors based on attractions were presented in
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark15">
    </span>
    parentheses).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1956">
   <s id="d1e1961">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark16">
    </span>
    ⁎⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.01 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1966">
   <s id="d1e1971">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark17">
    </span>
    ⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.05 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1976">
   <s id="d1e1981">
    ⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.10 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1986">
   <s id="d1e1991">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark18">
    </span>
    Fig.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1996">
    2.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2001">
    Estimated effects of sleep quality over different groups of tourists.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2006">
   <s id="d1e2011">
    To summarize the estimated effect of sleep quality across different samples in Tables 3 to 5, we present Fig.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2016">
    2 to display these effects on different tourist groups.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2021">
    The three largest signiﬁcant effects were observed for business travelers (travel = BUSINESS), tourists aged 50 and above (age = 50+), those experiencing sights and landmarks (type = Sights &amp; Landmarks).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2026">
   <s id="d1e2031">
    Robustness checks
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2036">
   <s id="d1e2041">
    To determine the robustness of our empirical results, we conducted a series of robustness checks, as shown in Table 6.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2046">
    First, we used the least square estimator without an instrumental variable to estimate the model, and the result was presented in Model 23.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2051">
    The estimated coefﬁcient of sleep is 0.103, which is statistically signiﬁcant at the 0.01 signiﬁcant level.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2056">
    This estimate is smaller than its counterpart in Model 1 with instrumental-variable estimation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2061">
    Second, we estimated the model using the least square estimator by treating sleep as a categorical variable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2066">
    We chose “sleep = 4” as the reference group, and the result was presented in Model 24.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2071">
    Interestingly, out of four sleep dummies, only the coefﬁcient of “sleep = 5” was estimated to be sig- niﬁcant, and its positive coefﬁcient indicates that the highest-level sleep quality leads to signiﬁcantly higher experience ratings than the second-highest-level sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2076">
    The coefﬁcients of “sleep = 1”, “sleep = 2”, and “sleep = 3” are statistically insignif- icant, albeit negative.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2081">
    This result indicates that lowered sleep quality does not necessarily lead to a lower travel experience as long as the sleep quality is not at the highest level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2086">
   <s id="d1e2091">
    Third, within the entire sample, 7721 experience ratings were contributed by 5380 unique tourist reviewers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2096">
    Although most tourists left one experience rating and one sleep rating, some tourists left many experience ratings, with some posting more than 20 such ratings for a single trip.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2101">
    Therefore, we suspected that over-represented observations from these rating enthusiasts could bias our results, and decided to apply a weighting scheme to ensure the total weight of each tourist was equal to 1.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2106">
    If a tourist left ﬁve experience ratings for different attractions during their trip, then we applied a weight of 0.2 to each observation in our three-way ﬁxed-effects model.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2111">
    Model 25 provides the results of least square estimation after re-weighting, while Model 26 provides the results of instrumental-variable estimation after re-weighting.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2116">
    The estimated coefﬁcient of sleep changed little com- pared to the counterpart without re-weighting, indicating the robustness of our results.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2121">
   <s id="d1e2126">
    Fourth, in Model 27, we applied an ordered probit model rather than linear regression because the 5-point experience rating is an ordinal measure (Park, Yang, &amp; Wang, 2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2131">
    The estimated coefﬁcient of sleep was still positive and statistically signiﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2136">
    Fifth, as shown in Table 2, the mean value of two major variables of interest, experience and sleep, are close to the maximum value, leaving little room for variation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2141">
    We converted these two variables into 0–1 dummy variables by deﬁning the value of 5 to be 1 and other values (i.e., 1, 2, 3, and 4) as 0.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2146">
    Model 28 provides the results of the probit model using the new dichotomous variable of experience, and due to identiﬁcation issues, hotel- and attraction-ﬁxed effects cannot be included.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2151">
    The dummy variable of sleep was also estimated to be positive and statistically signiﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2156">
    Therefore, our robustness checks generally conﬁrmed the robustness of our major conclusion on the impact of sleep quality on travel experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2161">
    The estimation results of additional ro- bustness checks appear online in our supplementary materials.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2166">
   <s id="d1e2171">
    Discussion and conclusion
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2176">
   <s id="d1e2181">
    Research on sleep remains under-studied in hospitality and tourism, particularly in terms of how sleep quality affects tourists' experiences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2186">
    We crafted a novel approach to investigate the consequence of tourists' sleep quality, which could pave the way for future sleep-related research in tourism and hospitality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2191">
    Under the research stream of sleep restriction protocol, we ﬁrst depicted the relationship between sleep quality and the tourist experience by drawing upon relevant sleep and tourism research.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2196">
   <s id="d1e2201">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark19">
    </span>
    Table 6
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2206">
   <s id="d1e2211">
    Robustness check with models of different estimation methods.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2216">
   <s id="d1e2221">
    Model 23 Model 24 Model 25 Model 26 Model 27 Model 28 Least square Least square Least square after re-weighting Instrumental-variable after re-weighting Ordered probit Probit
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2226">
   <s id="d1e2231">
    Sleep 0.103⁎⁎⁎ 0.0974⁎⁎⁎ 0.125⁎⁎⁎ 0.194⁎⁎⁎
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2236">
   <s id="d1e2241">
    (0.014) (0.017) (0.027) (0.016)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2246">
   <s id="d1e2251">
    Sleep = 1 −0.0812
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2256">
   <s id="d1e2261">
    (0.064)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2266">
   <s id="d1e2271">
    Sleep = 2 −0.0898
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2276">
   <s id="d1e2281">
    (0.065)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2286">
   <s id="d1e2291">
    Sleep = 3 −0.0371
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2296">
   <s id="d1e2301">
    (0.043)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2306">
   <s id="d1e2311">
    Sleep = 5 0.196⁎⁎⁎
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2316">
   <s id="d1e2321">
    (0.044)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2326">
   <s id="d1e2331">
    Sleep (dummy) 0.455⁎⁎⁎
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2336">
   <s id="d1e2341">
    (0.034)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2346">
   <s id="d1e2351">
    IV test 1 indicates the Kleibergen-Paap rk LM statistic for underidentiﬁcation test, IV test 2 indicates the Cragg-Donald Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test, and IV test 3 indicates Kleibergen-Paap rk Wald F statistic for weak identiﬁcation test.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2356">
    Clustered standard errors based on attractions were presented in
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark20">
    </span>
    parentheses).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2361">
   <s id="d1e2366">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark21">
    </span>
    ⁎⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.01 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2371">
   <s id="d1e2376">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark22">
    </span>
    ⁎⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.05 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2381">
   <s id="d1e2386">
    ⁎ Indicates signiﬁcance at the 0.10 level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2391">
   <s id="d1e2396">
    proposed a direct effect of sleep quality on the tourist experience as well as different moderators of this effect.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2401">
    Next, we empir- ically investigated these variables using TripAdvisor data from three U.S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2406">
    destinations: NYC, LV, and Orlando.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2411">
   <s id="d1e2416">
    Overall, the ﬁndings support our main proposition that sleep quality greatly shapes the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2421">
    This result is in line with prior studies revealing the prominent impacts of sleep quality on human activities and performance (Dewald et al., 2010).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2426">
    Quality sleep can help preserve energy, decrease stress and fatigue, and rest one's brain and body, effectively enhancing the tour- ist experience (Hamilton et al., 2007; Hobson, 2005; Pallesen et al., 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2431">
    Moreover, we found that three sets of variables mod- erated the relationship between sleep quality and the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2436">
    Across different age groups, sleep quality plays a more important role for senior travelers' tourist experiences, suggesting that senior travelers depend more on sleep quality to fully enjoy their tourist experiences.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2441">
   <s id="d1e2446">
    Trip-related variables also moderated the effect of sleep quality on the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2451">
    Our results revealed that the importance of sleep quality to the tourist experience was especially enhanced for business travelers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2456">
    Sleep quality apparently plays a more substantial role in the tourist experience for business travelers, and they should pay more attention to their sleep quality to enhance their tourist experiences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2461">
    In addition, this result does not show that trip distance moderate the sleep effect on the tourist experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2466">
    One possible rea- son is that the self-reported home city may not be the city of origin for the speciﬁc trip.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2471">
    As for personal travel experience, we did not ﬁnd empirical supports on the smaller effect of sleep quality on seasoned travelers' tourist experiences.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2476">
   <s id="d1e2481">
    Attraction type was shown to moderate the sleep quality-tourist experience relationship.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2486">
    Tourist experiences at casinos/gam- bling, concert and shows or museums, appeared less sensitive to sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2491">
    Travelers who visit these types of attractions gen- erally engage in less physical activity, leading to a lower inﬂuence of poor sleep quality.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2496">
   <s id="d1e2501">
    physical/leisure activities and sleep quality (Merritt, Zawadzki, Di Paolo, Johnson, &amp; Ayazi, 2017), our ﬁndings conﬁrmed that the effects of sleep quality on the tourist experience may depend on attraction types.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2506">
   <s id="d1e2511">
    Our research provides an important reference for travel-related sleep studies.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2516">
    The theoretical approach applied herein can be a catalyst for subsequent sleep studies on individuals who are on the road.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2521">
    First, we delineated the relationship between sleep qual- ity and the tourist experience within the domain of sleep restriction paradigm through the potential mediators of behavior, mood, and cognition.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2526">
    We also reviewed and integrated the sleep, social psychology, and tourism literature to present a more holistic un- derstanding of sleep on the tourist experience through interdisciplinary approaches.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2531">
   <s id="d1e2536">
    Second, our study is the ﬁrst to empirically evaluate how the direct and combined effects of sleep quality inﬂuence the tourist experience, revealing the nature and salience of sleep quality and several important travel-related moderators on the tourist ex- perience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2541">
    Our empirical evidence conﬁrms a broad yet hypothetical statement that sleep quality signiﬁcantly attributes to tourist experiences in a positive way, which marks a milestone for both sleep and tourism research.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2546">
    While sleep quality is a signiﬁcant driver of the tourist experience, other variables such as demographic factors (e.g., age), trip-related factors (e.g., traveler type), and destination-related factors (e.g., attraction type) could also moderate the effect of sleep quality on such experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2551">
    In this aspect, our study extends typical sleep research from life science inquiries in stasis to the domains of social sciences in mobility, substantiating the interplay functions of travel- and destination-related factors from one's sleep quality to travel experience.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2556">
    In fact, the ﬁndings of our study complement and extend Mao et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2561">
    (2018)’s work from the antecedents to consequences of trav- elers' sleep quality in hotels, thereby establishing a comprehensive traveler sleep quality framework.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2566">
   <s id="d1e2571">
    Our ﬁndings also provide practical insights for tourists, lodging properties and tour-organizing companies.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2576">
    Travelers can im- prove their tourist experiences by managing sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2581">
    They should maintain personal sleep hygiene practices such as partic- ipating in outdoor activities, adjusting their sleep time, maintaining a bedtime routine, arranging appropriate bedroom environments, and bringing sleep aids/gear as necessary while traveling.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2586">
    Other sleep-enhancing strategies, such as balanced travel schedule, relaxation techniques and stimulus control therapy, have been recommended for travelers along with sleep hygiene ed- ucation (Holfeld &amp; Ruthig, 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2591">
    Tour operators should consider designing tour packages and itineraries (e.g., with a combination of different attraction types) more deliberately to account for tourists' sleep quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2596">
    In addition, while tour guides cannot do much about tourists' sleep quality, they can certainly provide suggestions to help improve guests' sleep, such as how to manage dietary behaviors that promote better-quality sleep.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2601">
    More attention should also be paid to the sleep quality needs of speciﬁc groups such as seniors and business travelers based on tourist segmentation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2606">
    Hotels and their employees can be part of the equation to assist guests who need special room arrangements for better sleep.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2611">
   <s id="d1e2616">
    Our study should be evaluated in light of its limitations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2621">
    First, we did not intend to reveal the neurobiological mechanism of how sleep quality affects the tourist experience; this topic falls within physiology and life science research.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2626">
    Therefore, we did not explicitly test these mediating effects due to the design of the study and data unavailability of online reviews.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2631">
    Second, sleep quality data were obtained from online reviews, and it is measured using a ﬁve-point scale that is subject to different inter- nal interpretations by raters (Araña &amp; León, 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2636">
    More sophisticated econometric models are needed to correct this scale per- ception bias.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2641">
    Third, although the instrumental-variable method has been used to alleviate the endogeneity issue, experimental research can be more effective to draw causality conclusions (Viglia &amp; Dolnicar, 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2646">
    Future studies are recommended to em- brace objectively measured sleep quality data based on experiments (e.g., polysomnography or actigraphy) to provide further sup- port for our ﬁndings.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2651">
    Lastly, our study adopted exclusively online data without accounting for other potential inﬂuencing factors (e.g., price and value, personal health, and customer service) due to limited data availability.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2656">
    In subsequent research, scholars could conduct additional surveys and experiments to unveil additional sleep-related trends during travel.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2661">
   <s id="d1e2666">
    Declaration of competing interest
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2671">
   <s id="d1e2676">
    The authors declare that they have no known competing ﬁnancial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to inﬂuence the work reported in this paper.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2681">
   <s id="d1e2686">
    Appendix A.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2691">
   <s id="d1e2696">
    Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.annals.2021.103153.
   </s>
  </p>
 </body>
</html>