<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="discourse.v4_cn.css"?><html xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://wkwsci.ntu.edu.sg/discourse# discourse.v4_cn.xsd"> 
 <head><title>Gendered Relational Work: How gender shapes money attitudes and expectations of young adults</title>
 </head>
 <body>
  <l1>Gendered Relational Work: How gender shapes money attitudes and expectations of young adults</l1>
   <l2>
    ABSTRACT
   </l2>
<abstract>
  <p id="d1e56">
   <s id="d1e61">
    <arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-apply">We link the theory of gender performance to the perspective on the social meaning of money and relational work.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e66">
    <arg argID="002" type="support" supportType="method">Using longitudinal Panel Study of Income Dynamics data on young adult women and men, ages 18 through 24 in the US,</arg> <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">we examine survey responses to diﬀerent money-related situations.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e71">
    <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="method" comments_Ivanka="not sure">We question the expected gender-typical meanings of money, oﬀering a more contextual understanding.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e76">
    <arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="result">Speciﬁcally, we ﬁnd that when asked about the present, young women express that they worry more frequently about money than men do.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e81">
    <arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="result">However, when asked about the future – likelihood of having diﬃculty with ﬁnancially supporting one’s family and likelihood of having a job that pays well – we ﬁnd no signiﬁcant gender diﬀerences.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e86">
    <arg argID="006" type="claim" claimType="result">Instead, we ﬁnd expressions of optimism rather than worry by young women and men alike.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e91">
    <arg argID="007" type="claim" claimType="result">These results hold when controlling for psychological dispositions, ﬁnancial obligations, and demographics.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e96">
    <arg argID="008" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Overall, we note the importance of contextually situating ‘gender eﬀects’ in relation to money matters, and call for more sociological research that places gender performance centrally into the analyses of economy and examines gendered relational work across diﬀerent time orientations.</arg></s>
  </p>
 </abstract>
<intro>
  <l1>Introduction</l1>
  <p id="d1e151">
   <s id="d1e156"><arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">That money is a man’s and not a woman’s world is a persistent stereotype (Eagly 1987, Croson and Gneezy 2009, Carr and Steele 2010, Di Mauro and Musumeci 2011, Dabic 2012, Bigelow 2014, Thé- baud and Sharkey 2016).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e161">
    <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">Some analysts attribute gender diﬀerences in money-matters to psychological dispositions and gendered norms acquired during early socialization, and therefore, ﬁxed and stable features of the life course (for review, see LeBaron and Kelley 2020).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e166">
    <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">In contrast, the ‘doing gender’ sociological perspective proposes that gendered behaviors are rather malleable depending on gendered cultural scripts, or ideas about how gender should be performed or experienced in diﬀerent situations (West and Zimmerman 1987, Ridgeway 2011).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e171">
    <arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">Similarly, scholarship on the social meaning of money (Zelizer 1994) challenges the notion that money is uniform and perfectly fungible.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e176">
    <arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="literature-highlight_claim">Instead, this research points to the role of people’s cultural understandings in shaping the uses of, and attitudes about, money, uncovering relational work, or the process whereby people engage in matching of economic transactions with aligned social relations and concomitant media of exchange (Zelizer 2012, Bandelj et al. 2017b).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e186">
    <arg argID="006" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-apply">Engaging with these perspectives, our approach is to bring together social interactional theories of gender performance and economic sociology’s perspective on relational work.</arg></s>
 <s id="d1e196">
  <arg argID="019" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">Bridging these hitherto unconnected fields, we ask how young adults are ‘doing gender’ across various money situations, as reflected in the survey attitudes.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e221">
    <arg argID="020" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-compare/relate">While most quantitative research treats the categories of gender and money as stable and ﬁxed,</arg> <arg argID="021" type="claim" claimType="literature-difference_to_current" comments_Ivanka="not sure">we attempt to use survey responses across diﬀerent money and ﬁnancial questions to problematize the gender-typical meanings of money.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e226">
    <arg argID="022" type="claim" claimType="method">We oﬀer a contextual understanding by showing the importance of studying these concepts in a way that embeds them into their cultural, relational and temporal context (cf. Serido and Joseph 2014).</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e236">
   <s id="d1e241"><arg argID="040" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-define">Relational work research suggests that in diﬀerent situations, which we will refer to as money situations, money takes diﬀerent social meanings and matches diﬀerently across diﬀerent relational contexts (see Bandelj 2020 for review).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e246">
    <arg argID="041" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">We advance this research by paying attention to how gendered cultural scripts shape such money situations, or the unfolding of gendered relational work.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e251"><arg argID="042" type="support" supportType="extension_of_previous_research">We also heed Bandelj’s (2020) call to situate relational work in a temporal context.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e256">
    <arg argID="042" type="claim" claimType="hypothesis">Therefore, we propose that various money situations and diﬀerent time orientations (e.g. in the present, or in the future) will make gendered cultural scripts more or less salient in relational work.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e266">
    <arg argID="043" type="claim" claimType="hypothesis">Concretely, when asked generally about it, women may express more worry about money than men, consistent with a gender-typical script about women’s aversion to money matters.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e271">
   <arg argID="043" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration"> However, for an optimistic young adult (Arum and Roksa 2014), imagining an economic future could trump gender stereo- types so that young women and men alike would express conﬁdence in their economic prospects, such as their future ability to ﬁnancially support their family and have a well-paying job.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e276">
    <arg argID="044" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">In brief, our goal is to explore the dynamic nature of the concepts of gender, money and time orientations, as much as a quantitative analysis permits.</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e281">
   <s id="d1e286">
   <arg argID="050" type="support" supportType="method">We use Panel Study of Income Dynamics (PSID) data on young adult women and men in the US, ages 18 through 24,</arg> <arg argID="050" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">to examine our perspective on gendered relational work.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e291">
    <arg argID="051" type="claim" claimType="method" comments_Ivanka="not sure.">Based on PSID questions, we diﬀerentiate three money situations that correspond to diﬀerent gendered cultural scripts and diﬀerent temporal orientations: worry about money in the present, worry about ﬁnancially supporting family in the future, and conﬁdence in having a well-paying job in the future.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e296">
    <arg argID="052" type="claim" claimType="result">Results of ordered logit regressions question gender-typical expectations about money attitudes, which posit that women are more averse to and worried about money matters.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e301">
    <arg argID="053" type="claim" claimType="result">Instead, our results suggest malleability in how salient gendered cultural scripts are across money situations, such as those that invoke diﬀerent relational contexts (e.g. family relations, employer-employee) and diﬀer- ent time orientations (present vs. future).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e316">
    <arg argID="054" type="claim" claimType="result">Speciﬁcally, when young people are asked directly if they worry about money, one’s gender appears to be a signiﬁcant predictor, with those who identify as women expressing more frequent worry compared to those who identify as men on the survey.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e321">
    <arg argID="055" type="claim" claimType="result">However, when asked about expected diﬃculty with ﬁnancially supporting their family or the likelihood of having a job that pays well, we ﬁnd no signiﬁcant gender diﬀerences in these money attitudes about the future.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e326"><arg argID="056" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">Given that gender diﬀerences easily become reiﬁed and that reiﬁed constructs become real in their consequences (Thomas and Thomas 1928, cf. Merton 1995),</arg> <arg argID="056" type="claim" claimType="topic_centrality">it is important to recognize the dynamic nature of gender performance and similarities, not only diﬀer- ences, in how gender is performed in connection to economic matters.</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e336">
   <s id="d1e341">
    <arg argID="060" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">On the whole, our study makes three contributions.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e346">
    <arg argID="061" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">First, it extends the analyses of gender per- formance to economic attitudes and economic expectations as expressed on surveys.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e351">
    <arg argID="062" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Second, it advances economic sociology by examining gendered relational work.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e356">
    <arg argID="063" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">Third, it integrates the study of gender with the research on future economic orientations and expectations (Esposito 2013, Beckert 2016, Beckert and Bronk 2018), which is an emerging area of economic sociology.</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e361">
   <s id="d1e366">
    <arg argID="064" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">In the next section of the paper, we review interdisciplinary research on gender and money, including the literature on the role of gender in spending and earning money, gender and money in the broader perspective of capitalism and its transformations as well as the economics and psychology perspectives on gendered risk attitudes in ﬁnancial decisions.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e371">
    <arg argID="065" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">We then derive our sociological expectations about gendered relational work in diﬀerent money situations, inte- grating temporal orientations of present and future.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e376">
    <arg argID="066" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">After, we present our data from the Panel Study of Income Dynamics, methods of analysis, and results.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e381">
    <arg argID="067" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">We discuss our ﬁndings and conclude with the contributions we make to understanding the intersection of gender, economy, and temporality.</arg></s>
  </p>
</intro>
  <l1>
   Gender and money
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e386">
   <s id="d1e391">
    While the literature on the social meaning of money is extensive across disciplines (for review see Bandelj et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e396">
    2017b), as Zelizer (2010) calls out, economic sociologists have generally not paid sig-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark15">
    </span>
    niﬁcant attention to the intersection of gender and money.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e401">
    Admittedly, gender scholars have writ- ten extensively about care work (for review see England 2005), but they engage much less directly
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark14">
    </span>
    with money itself, unless money issues arise as a part of an investigation in other topics, such as the role of payments in surrogacy or egg donation (Haylett 2012, Almeling 2014, Berend 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e406">
    How- ever, there is more interdisciplinary work on the role of gender in how money is spent and earned, on gender and ﬁnance in the context of capitalism and its transformations, and on gender eﬀects on ﬁnancial attitudes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e411">
    We review these in turn.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e416">
   <s id="d1e421">
    The role of gender in money spent and money earned
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e426">
   <s id="d1e431">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark20">
    </span>
    Some sociological work on the broad topic of gender and money focuses on the diﬀerences between women and men in how they spend money.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e436">
    Zelizer (1989, 1994) noted how over time women’s
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark19">
    </span>
    earned money has been treated as ‘special money’ that is spent diﬀerently from men’s income.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e441">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark21">
    </span>
    Researchers also ﬁnd that women tend to spend more on children than men do (Thomas 1990, Zeli-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark17">
    </span>
    zer 2010), and it seems that children fare better when their mother, rather than their father, controls the family pooled income (Kenney 2008).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e446">
    When money is earmarked for children’s educational
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark16">
    </span>
    expenses, low-income mothers are often better able to safeguard it against spending on other expenses, compared to fathers (Gowayed 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e451">
    A study of money exchanged in transnational bro-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark18">
    </span>
    kered marriages shows that women negotiated money matters in their families depending on the newly reconﬁgured relationships (Kim 2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e456">
    For instance, while upon initial migration they send money home in a form of obligatory remittances, once they settle in their new destination countries, and especially when they have children of their own, these migrant women dedicate their money mostly for their children, and send remittances (which they reconceive as gifts, not obligatory payments) to their origin family only occasionally.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e461">
   <s id="d1e466">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark22">
    </span>
    Studies on charity money that examine the role of gender generally show that women tend to give more than men (Leslie et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e471">
    2013, Bandelj et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e476">
    2017a).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e481">
    In addition, women give to diﬀerent
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark24">
    </span>
    kinds of charity organizations, choosing education, health care, human services and poverty relief causes more frequently than do men (Rooney et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e486">
    2007, Einolf 2011, Mesch 2011, Willer et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e491">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark23">
    </span>
    2015).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e496">
    Research on gender and money in developing countries shows, for instance, that women
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark25">
    </span>
    have higher debt repayment in microﬁnance institutions (Boehe and Cruz 2013) and how they use digital ﬁnance to broker connections and trust (Kusimba 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e501">
   <s id="d1e506">
    A large literature on exchange bargaining in household division of labor is also related to money
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark26">
    </span>
    and gender because it presupposes that money earned by spouses determines bargaining power in spousal exchanges (Blood and Wolfe 1960, Becker 1981).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e511">
    Several empirical ﬁndings undermine bar-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark27">
    </span>
    gaining theory, however, showing that when wives earn as much as their husbands they still do the
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark30">
    </span>
    bulk of the housework (Bianchi 2000, Bittman 2003, Schneider 2012).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e516">
    Other studies problematize ﬁxed divisions of household labor, such as Horne (2018) who ﬁnds that factors such as work hours, income, marital status, and raising children aﬀect division of household labor diﬀerently at various life stages, such as the transition to adulthood, young adulthood, and midlife.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e521">
    Nonetheless, a con- sistent ﬁnding is that women do more housework than men at all life stages.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e526">
    Researchers suggest that because housework remains seen as the woman’s domain, in cases where the wives’ income
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark28">
    </span>
    surpasses the husbands’ income, women try to overcompensate for their gender deviant behavior
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark29">
    </span>
    by doing more housework (Bittman 2003, Evertsson and Nermo 2004) while men do less house- work (Brines 1994, Greenstein 2000).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e531">
    At the same time, women who are breadwinners may harbor
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark31">
    </span>
    some partner resentment by perceiving that their partners are not meeting their expectations (Men- diola 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e536">
   <s id="d1e541">
    concept of gender in a fairly uncritical way and rarely examines the contextual inﬂuences on gender performance.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e546">
   <s id="d1e551">
    Gender and money in the context of capitalism and its transformations
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e556">
   <s id="d1e561">
    Casting a wide net, we make a nod to scholarship that interrogates issues of gender and money and gender and ﬁnance in the historical context of capitalism and neoliberalism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e566">
    In the time of Fordism, gender and family issues were centered in the understanding of worker pay, given that workers, pri-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark32">
    </span>
    marily white men, were paid a family wage to support one’s family, usually consisting of a housewife and children (Adkins 2015).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e571">
    However, the growing trend of women entering the workforce called
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark33">
    </span>
    into question ‘the very normative premises of the Fordist consensus and its foundation in the family wage’ (Cooper 2015, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e576">
    404).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e581">
   <s id="d1e586">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark34">
    </span>
    Similarly, scholars have linked the (gendered) discourse of family values to free-market neoliber- alism (Cooper 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e591">
    Joseph (2013) has centered gender in the promotion of neoliberalism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e596">
    The author traced this back to the Moynihan Report (1965), noting that Moynihan links matriarchy to a ‘culture of poverty.’ While in working- and lower-class families, women usually managed household ﬁnances, this role was newer for middle- and upper-class women as they entered the workforce.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e601">
    Following this, as Joseph (2013, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e606">
    243) identiﬁes, there emerged two conﬂicting por- trayals of women and the economy.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e611">
    On the one hand, women are pathologized, portrayed as ‘impulsive shopaholics’; on the other hand, women are portrayed as ‘paralyzed non-investors’ when they are tried to be remade into entrepreneurial subjects that neoliberalism requires (Joseph
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark35">
    </span>
    2013, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e616">
    245).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e621">
    This points to the gendering of ﬁnancial attitudes and behaviors, provoking notions of a ‘proper’ feminine or masculine attitude or behavior.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e626">
    Importantly, Joseph (2013, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e631">
    263) notes that these norms of propriety are inconsistent, and ‘some of the feminine attitudes and behaviors, pre- viously portrayed as pathological, are [later] promoted as wise.’ Overall, this research troubles the categories of gender and money by situating gender stereotypes in their historical moment, urging us to also problematize gender-typical expectations in surveys on money attitudes.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e636">
   <s id="d1e641">
    Gender eﬀects on ﬁnancial decisions and risk attitudes
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e646">
   <s id="d1e651">
    In economics and psychology, the issues of gender and ﬁnance are usually tackled around risk-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark40">
    </span>
    taking behavior.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e656">
    Several economics studies have concluded that women are more risk averse
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark39">
    </span>
    than their male counterparts in making ﬁnancial decisions (Schubert 1999, Holt and Laury 2002,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark37">
    </span>
    Eckel and Grossman 2008, Borghans 2009).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e661">
    Yet, this ﬁnding is far from settled.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e666">
    For instance, for
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark38">
    </span>
    the case of fund management, Beckmann and Menkhoﬀ (2008) found that women are only slightly
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark41">
    </span>
    more risk averse when managing funds.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e671">
    In contrast, Bliss and Potter (2002) found that women take on marginally more risk than men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e676">
    Also, Iqbal et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e681">
    (2006) found that men in executive roles are
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark36">
    </span>
    more cautions with risk taking when it comes to handling their own stock option awards.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e686">
    Moreover,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark42">
    </span>
    Atkinson et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e691">
    (2003) found no signiﬁcant diﬀerence in risk taking between men and women among a similar group of mutual fund managers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e696">
    Likewise, Triana et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e701">
    (1984) found no signiﬁcant gender diﬀerences among entrepreneurs’ risk-taking behavior.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e706">
   <s id="d1e711">
    Still, a stereotype persists that men are more competent in dealing with ﬁnance and money than women (Eagly 1987, Croson and Gneezy 2009, Carr and Steele 2010, Di Mauro and Musumeci
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark45">
    </span>
    2011, Dabic 2012, Bigelow 2014, Thébaud and Sharkey 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e716">
    Similarly, entrepreneurship is con-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark43">
    </span>
    sidered a masculine pursuit (Thébaud 2015), and women are more likely to evaluate self-employ-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark44">
    </span>
    ment as a risky employment option compared to men (Dabic 2012, Bönte and Piegeler 2013, Dawson and Henley 2015).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e721">
   <s id="d1e726">
    Overall, we conclude that ﬁndings of this (mostly quantitative) literature on gender eﬀects on
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e731">
   <s id="d1e736">
    ﬁnancial decisions and risk attitudes are quite inconsistent.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e741">
   <s id="d1e746">
    those grounded in the gender socialization to those grounded in the gender performance perspec- tives.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e751">
    We review these next.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Theories of gender
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e756">
   <s id="d1e761">
    Gender socialization
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e766">
   <s id="d1e771">
    The bulk of the literature from economics and psychology on gender and risk treat gender as a sali-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark46">
    </span>
    ent status and assume that men and women have been socialized to have gendered traits and pre- ferences (Parsons 1942, Blair 1992, for review, see Kelley et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e776">
    2020, LeBaron and Kelley 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e781">
    For
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark47">
    </span>
    example, in their study of the link between risk aversion, opportunity, and entrepreneurial inten- tions, Tsai et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e786">
    (2016) postulate that men would exhibit more aggressive and competitive behavior and capitalize on entrepreneurial opportunities because these characteristics align with their expected social roles whereas women would be more risk averse and not capitalize on opportunities because this type of behavior deviates from what is typically expected of women.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e791">
   <s id="d1e796">
    Gender socialization, from early childhood and throughout adolescence, is considered to inﬂu-
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e801">
   <s id="d1e806">
    ence the formation of identities, traits, and preferences that align with gender roles, including how apprehensive women feel in relation to money and economic matters.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e811">
    Observing what their parents
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark48">
    </span>
    and other adults do, girls may internalize notions of gender norms such as in household labor (White and Brinkerhoﬀ 1981, Blair 1992), and by extension, money matters.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e816">
    As such, from a gender socialization perspective, women and men may perceive money diﬀerently and feel diﬀerently about their ability to handle money and economic matters.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e821">
    If gender norms are internalized and stable, we should, therefore, observe that women are more likely to express lack of conﬁdence in being able to handle money and economic matters, consistently across diﬀerent situations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e826">
    From a gender socialization and gender norms perspective, we would expect that women, more than men, express worry about economic issues, such as worry about money, worry about ﬁnancially supporting family, and worry about having a job that pays well.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e831">
   <s id="d1e836">
    Gender performance
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e841">
   <s id="d1e846">
    In contrast to gender socialization approach, from a symbolic and social interactionist perspective,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark50">
    </span>
    gender is constructed from ongoing interactions and processes in which men and women con- stantly work to create and recreate a sense of gender that meets others’ expectations (Goﬀman 1977, West and Zimmerman 1987).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e851">
    In other words, examining gender has less to do with what someone is or an individual-level trait that makes them male or female (or non-binary).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e856">
    Instead, it has more to do with what someone does in social situations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e861">
    As a result, Hence, gender is mutable and is constantly negotiated through social interactions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e866">
    West and Zimmerman (1987) describe this perspective as ‘doing gender.’ Typically, individuals tend to perform gender according to normative
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark49">
    </span>
    conceptions and cultural expectations of feminine and masculine behavior and self-presentation (Berk 1985, Butler 1990).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e871">
    As a result, stereotypes associated with diﬀerent expectations between genders shape an individual’s behavior.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e876">
    For example, expectations about diﬀerent levels of compe-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark51">
    </span>
    tence for men and women in organizational and labor market contexts aﬀect performance, and these diﬀerences contribute to gender inequality (Ridgeway and Correll 2004).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e881">
    Relatedly, ﬁnancial attitudes and behaviors, while gendered, are not static and may change in the course of time as people encounter, negotiate, and adopt diﬀerent gender norms over time (Serido and Joseph 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e886">
    Gendered cultural scripts also shape behavioral expectations in social relations (West and Zim-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark52">
    </span>
    merman 1987), and there are consequences to not performing gender properly in social interactions (Risman 1999).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e891">
    Risman’s study of nontraditional families also elucidates that men and women cre- ate gender and gender diﬀerences through everyday social interactions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e896">
    Therefore, they likewise have the capacity to change those gendered norms and expectations by continually constructing their lives in social interactions that do not give prerogative to gender-typical norms.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e901">
   <s id="d1e906">
    from a social interactional perspective, gender is conceptualized not as a (stable) status character- istic but as a performance that emerges from dynamic social processes.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e911">
   <s id="d1e916">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark53">
    </span>
    If gender is produced in social interactions, doing femininity and masculinity depends on the
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark56">
    </span>
    social context (Connell 1995) in which individuals try to match their behaviors according to the expectations of others gleaned from interactions (Ridgeway 1997).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e921">
    Therefore, from ‘doing gender’ perspective, ﬁnancial risk-taking or money worry has little to do with one’s status as a woman or a
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark54">
    </span>
    man.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e926">
    Rather, ﬁnancial risk itself is a gendered construct in which taking a risk is a part of, and per-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark55">
    </span>
    formance of, masculinity (Maclean 2016).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e931">
   <s id="d1e936">
    Along these lines, Marinelli et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e941">
    (2017) ﬁnd that while gender explains diﬀerences in investment decision processes, risk preferences, and portfolio characteristics, there is no diﬀerence across gen- ders in portfolio liquidity and diversiﬁcation, suggesting that gender may not be a stable feature and
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark57">
    </span>
    might diﬀer across ﬁnancial domains, contrary to the gender socialization hypothesis.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e946">
    Further, Bruni et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e951">
    (2004) show that when men and women jointly manage a ﬁrm, they symbolically con- struct gender such that entrepreneurship continues to remain as men’s domain.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e956">
    When men and women in spousal relationships jointly start a business, gendered expectations are ampliﬁed so
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark60">
    </span>
    that in such spousal joint ventures women have more limited access to power compared to women in non-spousal mixed-sex businesses (Yang and Aldrich 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e961">
    Spouses also do gender
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark58">
    </span>
    at home in managing their money when they attach diﬀerent meanings to wives’ and husbands’ incomes (see Dew 2021 for review).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e966">
    Because couples typically earmark women’s earnings as money for nonessential items, irrespective of whether those items are truly essential or not,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark59">
    </span>
    wives are less likely to be viewed as a breadwinner or a co-provider among dual-earning couples (Potucheck 1997).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e971">
   <s id="d1e976">
    Further, gender performance is evident among men and women in the same gendered occu- pation, such as care giving (Murray 2000).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e981">
    Women in care work cite feminine aspects of the occu- pation for entering the ﬁeld where they see caring as women’s natural work.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e986">
    For the same work, on the other hand, men oﬀer gender-neutral rationale.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e991">
    Instead of citing caring as part of men’s work,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark61">
    </span>
    for instance, their entry in care work is motivated by their interest in learning about human devel- opment or challenging gender stereotypes (Murray 2000).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e996">
    Combined, these studies suggest that men and women perform gender, but this performance varies depending on the nature of the par- ticular interaction.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1001">
    Each interaction (and related content and context) is subject to gender-speciﬁc expectations that shape possible outcomes, but do not solely determine them.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1006">
   <s id="d1e1011">
    An important note is in order to distinguish gender performance from perfomativity in social studies of science and political economy.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1016">
    Performativity theories question the ‘divide’ between
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark64">
    </span>
    economy, society, economics, and politics, pointing to the notion that these entities are not as sep- arate as they are made to seem (Cochoy et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1021">
    2010, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1026">
    141).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1031">
    Following Callon (1998), ‘economics
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark66">
    </span>
    performs the economy’ in a sense that how economic knowledge and technological devices create economic outcomes actually aligns with these ideas/tools (MacKenzie and Millo 2003).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1036">
    Here, the
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark63">
    </span>
    notion of performativity captures how economic knowledge ‘performs, shapes, and formats the
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark62">
    </span>
    economy, rather than observing how it functions’ (Callon 1998, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1041">
    2).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1046">
    Meanwhile, Judith Butler (2010, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1051">
    147) proposed a performative theory of gender to upend ‘the presumption that gender is a metaphysical substance that precedes its expression.’ Instead, Butler’s notion of gender per- formance emphasizes ‘how categories, such as sex, gender, and sexuality are not essences, but rather
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark65">
    </span>
    contingent outcomes of the manner in which they are reiterated in social performances of various kinds’ (du Gay 2010, p.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1056">
    171).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1061">
    Sociological theories aligned with feminist inquiry by focusing on gen- der performance and the role of gendered cultural scripts and doing gender in interaction (West and Zimmerman 1987).
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Gendered relational work
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e1066">
   <s id="d1e1071">
    Based on the gender performance, or doing gender theory, we would expect people to report diver- ging attitudes toward money matters depending on the salience of the gendered cultural scripts in
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1076">
   <s id="d1e1081">
    ﬁnancial situations presented to them.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1086">
    Research on the social meaning of money has suggested that money should not be understood as fungible and uniform across various contexts (Zelizer 1994,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark67">
    </span>
    Bandelj et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1091">
    2017b).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1096">
    People earmark money and attach meaning to various monies (in plural), diﬀerentiated, for instance, as compensation, gifts, or entitlements (Zelizer 1996).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1101">
    Moreover, people
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark68">
    </span>
    perform relational work, which involves eﬀorts to match various monies with appropriate social relations and aligned economic transactions (Zelizer 2005, 2012).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1106">
   <s id="d1e1111">
    We extend the concept of relational work to ideas about money that people hold.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1116">
    That is, we propose that, just as is the case in concrete interactive money situations, it would also be the case in expressed money attitudes that the meaning attached to money will vary across diﬀerent relational contexts, or diﬀerent money situations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1121">
    Worry about money or conﬁdence in one’s ﬁnan- cial ability will be judged according to the cultural and relational context in which it is presented.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1126">
    As such, diﬀerent money situations stand in contrast one from another on various dimensions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1131">
    Most relevant for our inquiry, money situations could diﬀer in the extent and the kind of cultural scripts they invoke about gender, implicitly or explicitly.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1136">
    Relational work will, therefore, be gendered, as
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark69">
    </span>
    people will bring diﬀerent gendered cultural scripts to bear in how they envision and behave with regards to money matters (cf.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1141">
   <s id="d1e1146">
    What are some concrete ways in which salience of gendered cultural scripts could enter into atti- tudes about money? For one, since money is traditionally considered to be a male domain (England
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark70">
    </span>
    2005) and the idea of women as risk averse or cautious investors has been around since the nine- teenth century (Maltby and Rutterford 2012), it is plausible that when women are asked about money directly and generally, gender-typical scripts will be enacted so that those who identify as women will express more worry about money than those who identify as men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1151">
    In addition, since family is traditionally considered as a female domain, it is possible that when family relations are made salient in a money-related question (such as, do you expect diﬃculty in ﬁnancially supporting your family), we might expect gender-typical performance of women required to be focused on family, so they might express more optimism on this question compared to men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1156">
    Still yet, the gen- dered cultural script may not be salient in speciﬁc money-related questions, such as about expected income opportunities, especially nowadays with high workforce participation rates for both women and men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1161">
    Therefore, we may not see gender diﬀerences in the expression of conﬁdence about hav- ing well-paid jobs.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1166">
   <s id="d1e1171">
    This said, we must also acknowledge that gendered scripts do not operate in a neutral context (Serido and Joseph 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1176">
    Rather, we may expect intersectional inﬂuences on expression of money attitudes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1181">
    In our study, given available data, we want to probe how the salience of gendered cultural scripts may be inﬂuenced by the life-course stage of the respondents (speciﬁcally, being a young adult) and also by diﬀerent temporal contexts (thinking in the present or imagining the future).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1186">
    These dimensions may complicate how doing gender works across diﬀerent money situ- ations, and it is our goal to examine how quantitative data might reveal these intersections.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Temporality in relational work: diﬀerences between present and future
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e1191">
   <s id="d1e1196">
    The relational work research has started to note the importance of temporal contexts to under- standing money situations (Bandelj 2020).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1201">
    Wherry (2016) called attention to meaningful time in,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark72">
    </span>
    what he called, relational accounting, to juxtapose with economists’ perspective on mental account- ing (Thaler 1999).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1206">
    Wherry (2016) emphasized how occasions of meaningful time impact how money allocation is prioritized noting that rites of passage and celebrations, such as graduations,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark71">
    </span>
    funerals, births, or religious holidays receive high priority in spending.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1211">
   <s id="d1e1216">
    More generally, individuals’ expectations about the future (Mische 2009) and about the econ-
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1221">
   <s id="d1e1226">
    omic future speciﬁcally (Beckert 2016) will likely matter in how they evaluate diﬀerent money situ-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark73">
    </span>
    ations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1231">
    For example, young people from disadvantaged backgrounds may actually express unfettered optimism about their future job prospects (Bandelj and Lanuza 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1236">
   <s id="d1e1241">
    lines, in her outline of the future agenda for the relational work research, Bandelj (2020, p.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1246">
   <s id="d1e1251">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark74">
    </span>
    Following these ideas, we want to take into account potential diﬀerences in how young adults imagine the present and the future (Brannen and Nilsen 2002), and how this may intersect with gendered relational work.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1256">
    Research shows a generally optimistic view of young people, even those from disadvantaged backgrounds, suggesting that imagining of the future is less a matter
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark76">
    </span>
    of rational assessment and more about identity work in which young people assert their moral
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark75">
    </span>
    worth and sense of self (Young 2004, Frye 2012, Bandelj and Lanuza 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1261">
    For instance, Frye (2012) shows that despite their unfavorable living conditions, young women from Malawi express an extensive sense of individual agency about the future, optimistically believing in the openness of the future.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1266">
    Likewise, research on young adults in the US shows that they also are generally optimis- tic about their future, and believe that things will work out for them, despite not-so-bright circum- stances (Arum and Roksa 2014).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1271">
   <s id="d1e1276">
    This research on time and young people’s optimism about the future leads us to anticipate that
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1281">
   <s id="d1e1286">
    whether a money situation presented to young people is about the present or about the future could matter signiﬁcantly in how they evaluate it.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1291">
    Concretely, the salience of gender-typical scripts about money among young adults might be more pronounced in situations about the present (e.g.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1296">
    current money worries) and less in those about the future (e.g.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1301">
    about future ﬁnancial support for family, or future well-paying jobs).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1306">
    Speciﬁcally, based on the research documenting optimism of young adults, we might expect that youth optimism would trump the salience of gender-typical scripts in money situations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1311">
    We examine these expectations quantitatively on a nationally representative sample of young adult Americans (ages 18-24), using data from the Panel Study of Income Dynamics, in the period before the 2008 ﬁnancial crisis.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Empirical analysis
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e1316">
   <s id="d1e1321">
    Data and methods
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1326">
   <s id="d1e1331">
    We used data from the Transition to Adulthood (TTA) module of the Panel Study of Income Dynamics (PSID), a nationally representative sample of individuals living in American families.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1336">
    We use the 2007 module of TTA, which will allow us to examine economic attitudes in a speciﬁc historical context of relative prosperity, before the ﬁnancial crisis.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1341">
    The age range of respondents is 18–24.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1346">
    For the 2007 TTA module, of the 1,259 eligible individuals, TTA administrators completed interviews for 1,115 respondents (88.6% response rate), which is the total sample size for analyses presented here.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1351">
    Following past practice, we utilize cross-sectional individual weights, which are a function of sample attrition in 2007 and the original Child Development Supplement (CDS) weights.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1356">
    Our results are, thus, representative of the 1997 CDS sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1361">
    We have a small percentage
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark78">
    </span>
    of missing data on our covariates (ranging from &lt;1% to 3.1%) in the analytic sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1366">
    We preserve
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark77">
    </span>
    these missing values with multiple imputation (Rubin 1987, 1996), averaging results across 20 data
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark79">
    </span>
    sets (Allison 2002).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1371">
    Following standard practice, we do not impute 2 missing values in our ‘job that pays well’ dependent variable (von Hipple 2007).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1376">
   <s id="d1e1381">
    Dependent variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1386">
   <s id="d1e1391">
    We use three questions available from the TTA module to understand economic attitudes toward money, and to diﬀerentiate situations that may invoke diﬀerent kinds and salience of gendered cul- tural scripts.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1396">
    First, we have information about money worry whereby the respondents were asked if they worry about not having enough money to pay for things.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1401">
    Values ranged from 1 ‘never worry’ to 7 ‘daily worry.’ This is a situation that speaks to the gender stereotype of women being more appre- hensive about money matters.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1406">
   <s id="d1e1411">
    In addition, we use two other questions that capture money situations, which diﬀerentially invoke cultural beliefs about gender, or could be considered neutral in terms of gendered expec- tations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1416">
    The former relates to the following question: ‘How likely is it that you will have diﬃculty supporting your family ﬁnancially?’ The latter is: ‘How likely is it that you will have a job that pays well?’ To both of these questions, respondents could answer from 1 ‘very likely’ to 7 ‘very unlikely’ but one of these indicates worry and the other indicates optimism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1421">
    Examining questions with the negative as well as the positive expressions of money-attitudes is also useful to reduce the possibility that women enact gender-typical worry script and simply answer more negatively to negatively phrased questions.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1426">
   <s id="d1e1431">
    Independent variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1436">
   <s id="d1e1441">
    Gender.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1446">
    To ascertain respondents’ self-identiﬁed gender identity, we utilize 1997 Main File’s gender information.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1451">
    Only two values are provided in these data, male or female, so we also code our data
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark80">
    </span>
    using the binary, recognizing that this is not the optimal way to classify gender categories (West- brook and Saperstein 2015).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1456">
    Still, in the dataset there are no missing data on gender, which means that those who might identify otherwise were not included.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1461">
   <s id="d1e1466">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark81">
    </span>
    Psychological Dispositions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1471">
    Research in psychology suggests that attitudinal dispositions are
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark82">
    </span>
    linked to individual psychological traits (Dweck 2006, Duckworth 2016), and psychological theories are often utilized to explain people’s tendency of worry and apprehension (Gershuny and Sher 1998).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1476">
    Consequently, we account for such psychological dispositions in our models of money atti- tudes since our data include this information.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1481">
    Speciﬁcally, we use personality-related information that parents provided about their children (our respondents) in 1997.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1486">
    Using a three-category response range – not true, sometimes true, and often true – parents indicated whether their children experienced a range of emotional and behavioral states.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1491">
    Then, we ran factor analyses to reduce the number of covariates under the assumption that the underlying factors that emerge from the data are correlated with psychological dispositions (stable personality traits).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1496">
    We found three factors with eigenvalues higher than 1, which account for 95% of the variation that all variables provide.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1501">
    The ﬁrst factor may be associated with a neurotic personality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1506">
    Factor #2 may be associated with an anxious and introverted personality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1511">
    Factor #3 may be associated with an angry/hostile person- ality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1516">
    We included predicted values from each of these factors in our models, and only anxious/ introverted and angry/hostile dimensions were consistently associated with our dependent variable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1521">
    Thus, we only included these two in the ﬁnal models to be parsimonious.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1526">
   <s id="d1e1531">
    Financial Responsibilities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1536">
    We tried to capture respondents’ current ﬁnancial obligations, which may likely exert an inﬂuence over their money attitudes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1541">
    We utilized a ﬁnancial responsibility index provided by PSID administrators in 2007.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1546">
    The index includes items that ask the respondent about how much (1) responsibility they have for earning own living, (2) responsibility they have for pay- ing own rent, (3) responsibility they have for paying own bills, and (4) responsibility for managing own money.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1551">
    Higher values suggest more ﬁnancial responsibility.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1556">
    This index was originally gener- ated by the 1992 wave of the Michigan Study of Adolescent and Adult Life Transitions (MSALT).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1561">
    Debt.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1566">
    We added another measure of respondents’ ﬁnancial situation that may impact economic
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark83">
    </span>
    expectations, in light of rising indebtedness of individuals and households, especially student debt (Carruthers and Ariovich 2010, Dwyer 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1571">
   <s id="d1e1576">
    tives?’ Using this variable we create a debt dummy (1 = yes).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1581">
   <s id="d1e1586">
    Socio-economic Background.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1591">
    Since our population includes young adults, most of whom may be still in school and not earning regular income, we consider information about their family back- ground to be most relevant to ascertain their socio-economic status, which may likely inﬂuence their money attitudes (Bandelj and Lanuza 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1596">
    Therefore, we utilize parental education, house- hold income, and parental occupation information from the Main Interview ﬁles.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1601">
   <s id="d1e1606">
    head of household (or his/her spouse – whichever was the highest) provided in the 1997 Main Inter- view ﬁle.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1611">
    If the child was 5 years or younger in 1997, we utilize the educational attainment of the head of household (or his or her spouse’– whichever was the highest) provided in the 2001, the year prior to the 2002 CDS collection eﬀorts.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1616">
    To calculate childhood household income, we utilize the same Main File years, accounting for the age of the child, as we did for the highest parental edu- cation variable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1621">
    The income variable that we utilize includes head of household’s and spouse’s tax- able income (and transfer income), taxable income from other family members in the household, transfer income of other family members in household, and social security income, where appli- cable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1626">
    PSID administrators calculated and provided this variable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1631">
    Finally, following previous research, we ascertained prestige scores for the head of household and his/her spouse.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1636">
    We utilize the highest prestige score, again, accounting for the age of the child as explained above.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1641">
    To create a socioeconomic background score we standardize the education, income (logged), and occu-
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark84">
    </span>
    pational prestige score distributions and then take the average of the three, following standard prac- tice (see Cowan et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1646">
    2012).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1651">
   <s id="d1e1656">
    Age.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1661">
    Using date of birth information provided in the 1997 Main Interview ﬁle, we created a con- tinuous age measure.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1666">
   <s id="d1e1671">
    Race.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1676">
   <s id="d1e1681">
    membership.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1686">
    We recode the measure into a dummy variable with two categories: White, non-His- panic (= 1) and everyone else (= 0).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1691">
    Note that including a more diﬀerentiated set of racial/ethnic
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark85">
    </span>
    categories does not change our results.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1696">
   <s id="d1e1701">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark86">
    </span>
    Immigrant Family.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1706">
    Given the documented optimism of immigrant children (Kao and Tienda 1995, Feliciano and Lanuza 2016), we account for immigrant family status.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1711">
    Hence, using an indi- cator provided by PSID administrators, we use a dummy indicating whether household head is an immigrant (1 = yes).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1716">
   <s id="d1e1721">
    Parents’ Marital Status: This measure takes a value of 1 if the respondents’ parent (head of house-
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1726">
   <s id="d1e1731">
    hold answering the survey) was married.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1736">
   <s id="d1e1741">
    College Enrollment.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1746">
    Respondents were asked, ‘are you currently attending college.’ Using this variable we created a college enrollment dummy (1 = enrolled, 0 = otherwise).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1751">
   <s id="d1e1756">
    Analytic strategy
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1761">
   <s id="d1e1766">
    We use descriptive as well as regression techniques to examine our research questions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1771">
    First, we examine descriptively whether, and if so how, money attitudes on our three dependent variables may vary by gender.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1776">
    In addition, we use ordered logit models in a multivariate framework to adju- dicate gender diﬀerences, since our dependent variables are ordered categories of likelihood, and because OLS assumptions are violated.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1781">
    Note, however, that OLS models provide similar results,
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark87">
    </span>
    which is in line with many econometricians’ arguments that minor violations to OLS assumptions rarely change the substantive results (Angrist and Pischke 2009), demonstrating the robustness of our conclusions across diﬀerent estimation strategies.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1786">
   <s id="d1e1791">
    Descriptive statistics
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1796">
   <s id="d1e1801">
    Table 1 shows the descriptive statistics for our analytic sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1806">
    We ﬁnd variation in all of our vari- ables of interest, including the money-attitudes questions, psychological dispositions, ﬁnancial situ- ation and demographic characteristics.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1811">
    With respect to demographics, about 53% of the sample identiﬁes as female, 48% are non-Hispanic white, 7% come from an immigrant family, 69% live in a dwelling where the head of household is married, and 48% are enrolled in college.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1816">
   <s id="d1e1821">
    Note: Descriptive statistics come from the ﬁrst of the twenty multiply imputed data, unweighted.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Findings
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e1826">
   <s id="d1e1831">
    Table 2 presents descriptive analyses on three money-related attitudes by gender.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1836">
    Here we see that there is a diﬀerence between young women and men on how they answer the money worry ques- tion, with women answering around 5 on a 1–7 scale, where 7 is everyday worry, and 1 is no worry at all, compared to men answering around 3.5 to this question, expressing notably less worry.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1841">
    How- ever, as concerns worry about ﬁnancially supporting future family, or conﬁdence in likelihood of getting a well-paying job, young women and men answer very similarly.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1846">
    Speciﬁcally, answers for women and men are, on average, around 2.5 on worry about ﬁnancially supporting future family (on a scale from 1 to 7, with lower scores indicating less worry).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1851">
    In addition, young women and young men both answer almost 6 on having a future well-paying job, expressing high optimism, given that this item is scored from 1 to 7, with 7 indicating highest likelihood of having a well-pay- ing job.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1856">
   <s id="d1e1861">
    Table 3 presents a series of ordered logit regression models with coeﬃcients predicting how often young adults worry about money.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1866">
    In response to the question about whether the respondent worries about not having enough money to pay for things, gender is statistically signiﬁcant and positively correlated with young women worrying about money more frequently.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1871">
    In Model 1 of Table 3, the logit coeﬃcient of 0.474 for gender indicates that the odds of worrying more frequently about money is 1.6 times higher (e0.474) for young women than young men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1876">
    Models 2 and 3 show that gender is signiﬁcant even after controlling for personality, ﬁnancial situation, and demographic background characteristics.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1881">
    When controlling for personality traits in Model 2 of Table 3, the gen- der coeﬃcient of 0.486 shows that the odds of women worrying more frequently about money is 1.6 times higher (e0.486) than the odds of men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1886">
    In full Model 3 of Table 3, there is a 0.503 increase in the logit of worrying more frequently about money for women compared to men.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1891">
   <s id="d1e1896">
    Notes: Statistical diﬀerences are calculated on the ﬁrst of the 20 multiply imputed data.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1901">
    If we treat ‘diﬃculty supporting family ﬁnancially’ and ‘job that pays well’ as categorical variables, Chi-Squares test also suggest that they are NOT associated with gender (p &gt; .10).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1906">
   <s id="d1e1911">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark90">
    </span>
    Table 3.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1916">
    Ordered logit models on how often respondent worries about having enough money.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1921">
   <s id="d1e1926">
    Notes: Results are coeﬃcients.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1931">
    Standard errors are in parentheses.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1936">
    +p &lt; .1, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001 (two-tailed tests).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1941">
   <s id="d1e1946">
    coeﬃcient shows that the odds of worrying more frequently about money is 1.7 times (e0.503) higher for young women than for young men.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1951">
   <s id="d1e1956">
    In terms of other relevant factors on worrying about money, the magnitude of the coeﬃcient for personality traits indicates a 0.265 increase in the log-odds of worrying more frequently about money for young adults with anxious or introverted personalities than those without these charac- teristics.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1961">
    Therefore, the odds of expressing more frequent worries about money is approximately 1.3 times (e0.265) greater for young adults with anxious or introverted personalities than young adults without those characteristics.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1966">
   <s id="d1e1971">
    0.324 decrease in the log-odds of expressing worry about money more frequently for a unit increase in the socioeconomic background measure.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1976">
    In other words, as we might expect, younger adults from higher socio-economic backgrounds worry less frequently about money.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1981">
   <s id="d1e1986">
    Table 4 shows the results of the ordered logit regression models predicting whether young adults believe that they will have diﬃculty supporting their family ﬁnancially.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1991">
    We identiﬁed several pos- sibilities about these eﬀects.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1996">
    For one, the question about family ﬁnances may invoke the gender- typical script about women as money worriers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2001">
    Alternatively, the focus on family might invoke the gender-typical script of women as caretakers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2006">
    Or, yet, and based on temporality considerations in relational work, we suggested that women could be as conﬁdent as men in their future expec- tations about supporting family, if youthful optimism about the future trumps the salience of gen- dered scripts.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2011">
   <s id="d1e2016">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark91">
    </span>
    Table 4.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2021">
    Ordered logit models predicting whether respondent worries about having diﬃculty supporting family ﬁnancially.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2026">
   <s id="d1e2031">
    Notes: Results are coeﬃcients.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2036">
    Standard errors are in parentheses.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2041">
    +p &lt; .1, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001 (two-tailed tests).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2046">
   <s id="d1e2051">
    variable on diﬃculty in ﬁnancially supporting future family.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2056">
    Given descriptive statistics (Table 2), which show low worry on this item for both women and men, we infer that gendered cultural scripts are less salient in assessing future family money situation for young adults.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2061">
    Rather, optimis- tic future hypothesis is best reﬂected in the data.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2066">
   <s id="d1e2071">
    In terms of other results from Table 4, we see that respondents’ personality traits are linked to worry about supporting their future family.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2076">
    The full model shows a 0.25 increase in the ordered log- odds of young adults with an anxious or introverted personality indicating more diﬃculty support- ing their family ﬁnancially.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2081">
    The odds of young adults with an anxious or introverted personality believing that they will have diﬃculty supporting their family ﬁnancially is 1.3 times higher (e0.250) relative to those with a stable personality.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2086">
   <s id="d1e2091">
    0.158 lower than young adults without ﬁnancial responsibilities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2096">
    In other words, young adults who say that they have ﬁnancial responsibilities indicate lowered odds of worrying about support- ing their family by 0.85 times (e−0.158) or 15% less than those without ﬁnancial responsibilities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2101">
    While this may seem counterintuitive, it makes sense if we consider that those with current ﬁnancial responsibilities are better able to anticipate their future circumstances because they have a clearer sense, from concrete experience, about what it takes to carry ﬁnancial burdens or have ﬁnancial opportunities.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2106">
   <s id="d1e2111">
    Finally, responses to a question about having a well-paying job in the future also indicate simi- larities, not diﬀerences, between answers of those young adults who identify as women to those who identify as men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2116">
    As Table 5 shows, ordered logit regression results predicting young adults’ concern about whether they will have a well-paying job indicate no signiﬁcant gender eﬀects.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2121">
    Again, high scores on optimism about a well-paying future job for both men and women (Table 2) signal opti- mistic future expectations that are not signiﬁcantly diﬀerent by gender.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2126">
    In addition, and similar to what we discovered for the previous dependent variable, it seems that having ﬁnancial responsibil- ities matters in the likelihood of being optimistic about a future job.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2131">
    A unit increase in having more ﬁnancial responsibilities, results in a 0.234 increase in the log-odds of believing that one will have a well-paying job.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2136">
    Having more ﬁnancial responsibilities, therefore, increases the odds of optimism about having a well-paying job by 1.3 times (e0.234), again, likely because having direct experiences with money as a young adult likely helps with building more conﬁdence about one’s future money situations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2141">
    The results also show that young white adults seem to worry more about having a well- paying job than non-white adults.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2146">
    The coeﬃcient in Model 3 of Table 5 shows a 0.765 decrease in the log-odds of white adults’ belief about likelihood of having a well-paying job than non-white adults.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2151">
    In other words, white young adults are about half as optimistic about having a well-paying job than non-white adults, which is notable and would require further investigation to identify
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark92">
    </span>
    potential explanations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2156">
    Perhaps, due to the experience of racism in society, people of color develop optimism as a coping strategy (Lee et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2161">
    2015).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2166">
   <s id="d1e2171">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark93">
    </span>
    Table 5.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2176">
    Ordered logit models on whether respondent believes s/he will have a job that pays well.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2181">
   <s id="d1e2186">
    Notes: Results are coeﬃcients.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2191">
    Standard errors are in parentheses.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2196">
    +p &lt; .1, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001 (two-tailed tests).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2201">
   <s id="d1e2206">
    On the whole, our analysis suggests that the salience of gender scripts varies depending on the temporal context in which money situations are envisioned and interpreted.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2211">
    We see a statistically signiﬁcant eﬀect of gender on the question asking how often respondents worry about money.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2216">
    Young women answer that they worry more frequently, and this could be interpreted as them enacting the gender-typical script of money aversion.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2221">
    However, when these respondents are asked whether they foresee having diﬃculty ﬁnancially supporting their family, or having a well- paying job in the future, one’s gender is not a signiﬁcant predictor of money-related expectations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2226">
    Young women and men express similarly optimistic attitudes about their future ﬁnances, a ﬁnding corroborated by other researchers investigating young adult attitudes about the future (Young 2004, Frye 2012, Arum and Roksa 2014, Bandelj and Lanuza 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Discussion and conclusion
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e2231">
   <s id="d1e2236">
    Gender stereotypes that women are more averse to and worried about money compared to men abound in popular discourse.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2241">
    These stereotypes are likely linked to a ‘separate spheres’ argument and gendered ideas about ﬁnance as a part of the public domain of work and provision, traditionally
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark94">
    </span>
    a man’s job, thought as separate from the private intimate sphere, traditionally a woman’s domain (Kerber 1988, England 2005, Folbre 2010).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2246">
    Notably, feminist research shows that gender stereotypes about money are historically speciﬁc and malleable (Joseph 2013).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2251">
   <s id="d1e2256">
    Still, much of economics and psychology literature pronounces that women, generally, are more risk averse than men when making ﬁnancial decisions, assuming stable gender norms that are inter- nalized during socialization and consistent across situations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2261">
    In contrast to this perspective and drawing on sociological theories of gender performance together with the perspective on the social meaning of money, we develop the concept of gendered relational work.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2266">
    We argue that how one ‘does gender’ intersects with how one ‘does money,’ that is, enacting of gendered cultural scripts varies along multiple dimensions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2271">
    Relevant for our study, it varies across diﬀerent money situations (such as general money worries, family money worries, job money conﬁdence) that variously match up with diﬀerent relational considerations (in our case, individual concerns, family concerns or employer-employee relationship) as well as across diﬀerent time orientations (present vs.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2276">
    future).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2281">
    A sociological perspective on the social meaning of money has established that money is not homogenous and uniform across situation but imbued with meaning (Zelizer 1989, 1994).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2286">
    That is, people go to great lengths to diﬀerentiate what monies or payments are appropriate for diﬀerent kinds of social relations they are involved in (Bandelj et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2291">
    2017b), what is referred to as relational work.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2296">
    While research on relational work has been ﬂourishing (for review see Bandelj 2020), it has rarely used survey data to examine the social meaning of money.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2301">
    We proceeded to conduct such an
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark95">
    </span>
    investigation by proposing that in answering about money on surveys, the relational context of the described money situations will be important for people’s answers (cf.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2306">
    Hayes and O’Brien (2020) for experimental work on money situations).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2311">
   <s id="d1e2316">
    economic attitudes and expectations.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2321">
   <s id="d1e2326">
    The analysis of the Panel Study of Income Dynamics data on economic attitudes of young adult women and men in the US in a particular historical context of economic prosperity (before 2008 ﬁnancial crisis) suggests support for the gendered relational work proposition.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2331">
    Concretely, when those young adults who identify as women are asked directly if they worry about money, we found that they express more worry than those who identify as men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2336">
    This aligns with the gen- der-typical cultural script of women being more averse to money matters than men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2341">
    However, when asked about expected diﬃculty with ﬁnancially supporting their family or likelihood of having a job that pays well, we found no signiﬁcant gender diﬀerence in economic expectations about the future.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2346">
   <s id="d1e2351">
    socio-economic background, race, education, marital status, immigrant status, and whether they currently have signiﬁcant ﬁnancial responsibilities or if they are in debt.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2356">
   <s id="d1e2361">
    Since we only have quantitative data at our disposal we cannot specify the exact mechanisms through which gendered cultural scripts inﬂuence money matters.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2366">
    One possible explanation is
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark97">
    </span>
    related to diﬀerent contextual elicitation of stereotype threat (Carr and Steele 2010).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2371">
    Another is
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark96">
    </span>
    related to third-order beliefs (Thébaud et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2376">
    2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2381">
    That is, young women may answer apprehen- sively about money worries because they believe that others would expect them to worry (Cooper 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2386">
    In some ways, this is related to the extent that performing gender operates implicitly and/or explicitly, which we cannot adjudicate in our study.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2391">
    Still, regardless of whether, in speciﬁc contexts, gendered beliefs turn out to be second or third order, implicit or explicit, in our data, we could trace their manifestation, variously, across diﬀerent money situations, capturing the eﬀects of diﬀerent temporal orientations, and pointing to the ﬂexible nature of gender performance.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2396">
   <s id="d1e2401">
    Another important contextual feature of our study is that we use data from a time of relative general optimism in economy before the 2008 ﬁnancial crisis.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2406">
    It is likely that in times of economic downturns or crises such as COVID-19, young adults would express less optimism or that gender may become more salient in future expectations as well.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2411">
    We certainly also recognize that young
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark98">
    </span>
    adults may be diﬀerent than older adults, in particular, express more optimism about their econ- omic future (Schneider and Stevenson 2000, Reynolds 2006, Alexander et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2416">
    2008, Baird et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2421">
    2008, Bandelj and Lanuza 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2426">
    In sum, when we examined how gendered cultural scripts interact with two sources of variation, that is, time (e.g.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2431">
    present, future) and money situation (e.g.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2436">
    money worry, family ﬁnancial support concerns, well-paying job prospects), we found gender-typical script salience in the present for worries about money but not in evaluation of future family ﬁnances and likelihood of well-paying jobs.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2441">
   <s id="d1e2446">
    Additional research is needed to disentangle how gendered relational work operates as well as potential diﬀerences across life course and macro-economic stability.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2451">
    In any case, engaging these important questions, researchers would be well served in problematizing the stability of both gender and money categories and tracing their contextual expression.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2456">
    Last but not least, we also hope our study will spur more economic sociologists to place gender performance centrally in analyses of money and ﬁnance, as much as we hope that the analysts of ‘doing gender’ will interrogate the role of temporality in enacting gendered cultural scripts.
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Disclosure statement
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e2461">
   <s id="d1e2466">
    No potential conﬂict of interest was reported by the author(s).
   </s>
  </p>
  <l1>
   Notes on contributor
  </l1>
  <p id="d1e2471">
   <s id="d1e2476">
    Nina Bandelj is Chancellor’s Professor, Department of Sociology, and Associate Vice Provost for Faculty Develop- ment at the University of California Irvine.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2481">
    She studies how social structures, culture, power and emotions inﬂuence economic and organizational processes, including investment and debt, inequality, globalization, postsocialist trans- formations, and ideas about economy.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2486">
    Her articles have been published in the American Sociological Review, Social Forces, Socio-Economic Review and Theory &amp;amp; Society, among others.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2491">
    Her most recent book is Money Talks: Explaining How Money Really Works (with Frederick Wherry and Viviana Zelizer, Princeton University Press, 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2496">
   <s id="d1e2501">
    Yader R.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2506">
    Lanuza is Assistant Professor of Sociology at the University of California, Santa Barbara.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2511">
    His research inter- ests include race and ethnicity, (im)migration, education, family, culture, and punishment.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2516">
    His scholarship has appeared in the American Sociological Review, Social Problems, Journal of Marriage and Family, International Migration Review, among other outlets.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2521">
   <s id="d1e2526">
    Julie S.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2531">
    Kim is Lecturer in the Department of Sociology at the University of California, Irvine.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2536">
    Her research interests are in economic sociology, gender, entrepreneurship and the life course.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2541">
    She has published articles in the Socio-Econ- omic Review and The Routledge Handbook of Behavioral Economics as well as chapters in edited volumes.
   </s>
  </p>
 </body>
</html>