<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="discourse.v4_cn.css"?><html xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://wkwsci.ntu.edu.sg/discourse# discourse.v4_cn.xsd"> 
 <head>
  <title>Youth Migration Decisions in Sub-Saharan Africa: Satellite-Based Empirical Evidence from Nigeria</title>
 </head>
 <body>
  <l1>Youth Migration Decisions in Sub-Saharan Africa: Satellite-Based Empirical Evidence from Nigeria</l1>
<abstract>
<l2>Abstract</l2>
  <p id="d1e11">
   <s id="d1e16">
    <arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">This article examines the implications of urban growth on youth migration decisions in Nigeria.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e21">
    <arg argID="002" type="support" supportType="method">We use night light intensity data combined with Living Standards Measurement Study-Integrated Surveys on Agriculture data, as an indicator of urban growth and associated economic opportunities.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e26">
    <arg argID="002" type="support" supportType="method">Employing alternative econometric approaches that exploit the spatial and temporal differences in urban growth as proxied by night light intensity,</arg> <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="result">we find that urban growth in potential migrant destinations encourages youth migration.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e31">
    <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="result">We also find heterogeneous responses to urban growth among various groups of youth as well as varying responses to different types of migration.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e36">
    <arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="result">Broadly, women and those youth with more education are more likely to migrate, while those in households with livestock are less likely to migrate.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e41">
    <arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="result">Often, however, the effects are complex and varied.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e46">
    <arg argID="006" type="claim" claimType="result">For example, land and physical asset ownership encourage temporary migration; but greater land ownership discourages permanent migration, while physical assets have insignificant effects.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e51">
    <arg argID="007" type="claim" claimType="general_result">Our results from Nigeria show that policy makers concerned about rural–urban youth exodus should adopt a differentiated, in terms of targets, and multidimensional policy approach to reap the benefits of urbanization while avoiding its negative consequences.</arg>
   </s>
  </p>
</abstract>
<intro>
   <l1>Introduction</l1>
  <p id="d1e66">
   <s id="d1e71">
    <arg argID="001" type="context" contextType="practical_background">Youth unemployment and migration to urban areas, as well as across borders, has received increasing policy attention in recent years.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e76">
    <arg argID="002" type="context" contextType="practical_background">Challenges in accelerating rural economic growth to create jobs along with a fast-growing youth population are particularly concerning in many countries in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e81">
    <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">While there are many factors that induce migration, one of the factors is urbanization and the unbalanced growth between the rural and urban areas.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e86">
    <arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="research_gap">However, the nexus between youth migration and urbanization in Africa is not well-understood (Abramitzky et al. 2013; Bezu and Holden 2014; de Brauw et al. 2014; Lambert et al. 2014; Kosec et al. 2018).</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e91">
    <arg argID="006" type="claim" claimType="research_issue">In addition, linkages between migration and urban growth overall remain a center of attention for researchers and urban development planners.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e96">
    <arg argID="007" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">While migration contributes to urbanization and so to urban growth, the latter may also attract and encourage rural–urban migration—suggesting a potential bidirectional relationship.</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e101">
   <s id="d1e106">
    <arg argID="010" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">Nevertheless, identifying the impact of migration is relatively easier</arg> <arg argID="010" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration">because there exist exogenous sources and variations inducing rural–urban migration.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e111">
    <arg argID="011" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">At the same time, while theoretically intuitive, identifying the impact of urban growth on rural–urban migration suffers from endogeneity and measurement problems,</arg> <arg argID="011" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge" comments_Ivanka="looks like a common sense, no need a citation. So I coded Established knowledge">partly because urban growth is not amenable to randomization and also because natural experiments generating variations in urban growth are rare.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e116">
    <arg argID="012" type="claim" claimType="research_issue">We also lack objective measures and markers of urbanization that can detect short-term dynamics in urban growth.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e118"><arg argID="012" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">The literature, predominantly owing to data limitations, has empirically measured urbanization as a binary phenomenon, even though urbanization is better viewed as a continuum and an ongoing process (Calì and Menon 2013; Christiaensen and Todo 2014; Abay and Amare 2018; Amare et al. 2020).</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e121">
   <s id="d1e126">
    <arg argID="020" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">In this article, we are interested in understanding the potential drivers of migration in SSA by drawing on evidence and recent trends in Nigerian urban growth on youth migration.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e131">
    <arg argID="021" type="claim" claimType="research_issue">While the economic benefits of urban growth are increasingly being recognized, there is also a general need to better understand how these have influenced further rural–urban migration influxes (Ravallion et al. 2007; Dorosh and Thurlow 2014; McGranahan and Satterthwaite 2014).</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e136">
    <arg argID="022" type="description" descriptionType="concept/theory/model-details">Since 1970, the Harris–Todaro model has focused attention on expected returns to migration.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e141">
    Youth have long been regarded as particularly sensitive to expected outcomes, given their relative flexibility and a perspective stretching across their entire working life.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e146">
    <arg argID="026" type="claim" claimType="method">To study migration decisions, we use nationally representative longitudinal data from the Living Standards Measurement Study-Integrated Surveys on Agriculture (LSMS-ISA) data for Nigeria and combine it with satellite-based night light data using the geolocalized references of the households.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e151">
    <arg argID="026" type="support" supportType="established_knowledge">Many studies (e.g., Elvidge et al. 1997; Imhoff et al. 1997; Sutton 1997; Henderson et al. 2003; Henderson et al. 2012; Storeygard 2016) argue that night light intensity per unit area may be a valuable indicator of urban growth.</arg>
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e156">
   <s id="d1e161">
    <arg argID="030" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">We then examine the implications of differences in urban growth between migrants’ destinations and origins.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e166">
    <arg argID="031" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">In particular, we exploit both the spatial and temporal differences in night light intensities between these two spatial units before migration takes place.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e171">
    <arg argID="031" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration">The temporal dynamics in the spatial differentials in night light intensities between these spatial units is expected to be exogenous to individuals’ livelihood decisions.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e176">
    <arg argID="032" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">Similarly, as we focus on premigration spatial and temporal differences in night light intensities, reverse causality effects can be ruled out.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e181">
    <arg argID="032" type="support" supportType="motivation/justification">Thus, this method helps us to isolate the causal impact of urban growth and the associated growth in economic opportunities on youth migration decisions.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e186">
    <arg argID="033" type="claim" claimType="concept/theory/model-apply">To probe the robustness of our results, we employ alternative indicators and definitions of migration.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e191">
    <arg argID="034" type="support" supportType="motivation/justification">Since the mechanisms underlying migration are likely to differ across various attributes and endowments of youth,</arg> <arg argID="034" type="claim" claimType="research_objective"> we also examine whether the responses to urban growth vary across observable attributes of youth, including by sex, education, and access to land.</arg>
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e196">
   <s id="d1e201">
    <arg argID="050" type="claim" claimType="result">As expected, we find that urban growth in neighboring migrant destination areas encourages youth migration.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e206">
    <arg argID="051" type="claim" claimType="result">Other factors being the same, youth exposed to relatively higher growth in destination zones (as proxied here by growth in night light intensity) are more likely to migrate.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e211">
    <arg argID="052" type="claim" claimType="result">The results also show that the response of youth in rural areas and towns to urban growth varies across the observable attributes of youth as well as by category of migration.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e216">
    <arg argID="052" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration">For example, older female youth with higher levels of education and coming from households with greater land holdings and more physical assets (except livestock) as well as higher night light differentials in potential destinations compared with their home are more likely to migrate temporarily.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e221">
    <arg argID="053" type="claim" claimType="general_result">Overall, this study provides insights on the role of urban growth and associated growth in economic opportunities to attract youth migration, and highlights the spillover effects of urban growth, an effect that may further burden and constrain service delivery in certain crowded urban destinations.</arg>
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e226">
   <s id="d1e231">
    <arg argID="070" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">The “Urban growth and youth migration: Review” section provides a brief literature review.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e236">
    <arg argID="071" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">“Data and variable measurement” section describes the data.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e241">
    <arg argID="072" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">“Empirical strategies” section presents our empirical strategy.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e246">
    <arg argID="073" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">In “Results and discussion” section, we present and discuss our empirical results.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e251">
    <arg argID="074" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">“Concluding remarks” section provides concluding remarks.</arg></s>
  </p>
</intro>
<lit-review>
<l2>Urban growth and youth migration: Review</l2>
  <l3>Urban growth</l3>
  <p id="d1e276">
   <s id="d1e281">
    Owing to problems with measuring urban growth, researchers and urban planners have increasingly sought alternative measures of urbanization.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e286">
    Construction of continuous and disaggregated indices capturing microlevel variation in urban growth has progressively been used to measure urbanization (van de Poel et al. 2012).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e291">
    Most recently, a collection of satellite-based night light intensity data has generated considerable interest among researchers for its ability to—at least partially—capture both short- and long-term dynamics of urbanization.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e296">
    The Operational Linescan System (OLS) sensors of the Defense Meteorological Satellite Program (DMSP) of the United States Airforce are the source of these data.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e301">
    Night light intensity data measured at a resolution of approximately 1 km2 from all over the planet are captured on a daily basis by these satellite-based remote sensors and are then processed by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e306">
   <s id="d1e311">
    At NOAA, light intensities are expressed as monthly or annual averages, after any natural dimness emanating from clouds are removed, leaving only lights from human activities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e316">
    The processed night light intensity data are freely distributed for research and public use and are mostly presented as digital numbers ranging from zero (no night light intensity) to 63 (highest night light intensity) for 1 km2 pixels.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e321">
    Night light intensity data have several advantages in measuring the dynamics of urbanization and related human activities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e326">
    They are argued to be valid markers (proxies) for urbanization, especially compared to census-based rural–urban binary indicators.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e331">
    This is partly because the availability of high spatial resolution data facilitates the construction of spatially detailed measures of urbanization (Elvidge et al. 2009; Imhoff et al. 1997; Sutton 1997; Henderson et al. 2003; Storeygard 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e336">
    The night light intensity data are observed over a long time series without compromising quality.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e341">
    This facilitates the creation of continuous indexes that can capture short-term spatial and temporal variations in urbanization that cannot be captured by the traditional dichotomous rural–urban indicators.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e346">
   <s id="d1e351">
    While the night light intensity data have increasingly been used in analysis, it is worth highlighting a few shortcomings and limitations in measuring urban growth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e356">
    To begin with, a small fraction of areas with high levels of lighting may be underestimated by the index owing to the upper censoring of light intensities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e361">
    Second, because most of the developing world remains dark, luminosity data are highly skewed to the left (Michalopoulos and Papaioannou 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e366">
    This is the case in our context because our sample consists of both rural and urban households throughout the country.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e371">
    However, as we show in our analysis, the night light intensity data for Nigeria provide reasonably sufficient variation and temporal dynamics, especially relative to the commonly used rural–urban indicators.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e376">
   <s id="d1e381">
    Youth migration in SSA and Nigeria
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e386">
   <s id="d1e391">
    Before analyzing the effects of urban growth on youth migration, it is important to understand the underlying migration decision-making process and common drivers of migration in developing countries.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e396">
    A number of factors drive outmigration decisions, and the economic literature documents several drivers based on different migration models.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e401">
    Among the key models are those that take into account wage differentials between two locations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e406">
    As urban wages are usually higher than rural wages, and opportunities are generally greater, significant rural–urban migration is expected to take place in many developing countries.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e411">
    This is partly reflected in differences in labor productivity in the urban (nonagricultural) and rural (primarily agricultural) sectors (Young 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e416">
    These models assume that migration decisions are mainly driven by economic incentives and mostly involve individual cost-benefit analysis of costs and gains from outmigration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e421">
    The implication of these models is that increased migration to urban areas increases the supply of urban labor, while at the same time reducing the supply of rural labor, which decreases urban wages and increases rural wages.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e426">
   <s id="d1e431">
    Modifications of the earlier models led to the suggestion that the differentials in expected wages, rather than actual wage differentials, influence the decision to migrate.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e436">
    Under this type of model, Harris and Todaro (1970) posit that the decision to migrate is dependent on the migrant's own perception of the wage differential over the unemployment probability and subjective discount rates.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e441">
    The most recent migration models consider migration as a strategy that households adopt to maximize expected earnings, and lower consumption risk, by diversifying their income sources over various sectors or agro-ecological zones (Mincer 1978; Stark and Bloom 1985).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e446">
    These types of models differ from the earlier ones, since they introduce a rural risk factor as a component in the migration decision and focus on a household rather than on the individual.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e451">
    The nexus between youth migration and urbanization in Africa is evolving rapidly and remains multilayered.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e456">
    Recently, there has been a paradigm shift in the structural linkage between youth livelihood choices and migration dynamics (Abramitzky et al. 2013; Bezu and Holden 2014; de Brauw et al. 2014; Lambert et al. 2014; Kosec et al. 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e461">
    Suggestions have emerged in the literature to the effect that availability of employment opportunities (agriculture or nonagriculture) and productive resources (e.g., land) for youth at their current locations can impede migration (McKenzie and Rapoport 2007; Bezu and Holden 2014), and that unavailability of these productive resources can be responsible and motivate migration (Dorosh et al. 2012; Abramitzky et al. 2013; Lambert et al. 2014; Kosec et al. 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e466">
   <s id="d1e471">
    African youth migration involves different types and patterns of mobility: rural–urban, rural–rural, seasonal and permanent, and intraregional and interregional.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e476">
    Nevertheless, irrespective of the type of movement, African youth aspire to move to urban areas where they perceive there will be greater opportunities to improve livelihood outcomes (Dorosh et al. 2012; Abramitzky et al. 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e481">
    As a consequence, urban areas in Africa are becoming enormously congested and overstrained, placing pressure on the inadequate infrastructure for housing, electricity, sanitation and water systems, health facilities, and education (Min-Harris 2010; UNECA 2017; Franklin 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e486">
   <s id="d1e491">
    Urbanization can potentially influence migration decisions for youth about whether to embark on migration, either within or across borders (Naudé 2010; Flahaux and De Haas 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e496">
    Theoretically, potential migrants may consider and weigh differences in employment opportunities and expected wages at their potential destinations and point of origin.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e501">
    Growing inequality between urban and rural areas—as well as potential differences in the provision of socioeconomic services and facilities—can also encourage youth to migrate (Naudé 2010).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e506">
    Furthermore, perceived differences in infrastructure and economic development between urban and rural areas may trigger rural–urban migration and international outmigration (UNECA 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e511">
    The deprivation of youth and women and unequal access to land particularly drive the decision to migrate in search of off-farm employment in other areas (Bah et al. 2003), while youth prospect of inheriting land can reduce the probability of embarking on permanent migration (UNECA, 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e516">
    Youth are keen to find employment in sectors other than agriculture (Bezu and Holden 2014), possibly with the hope of earning better incomes (Deshingkar and Grimm 2005; Dorosh et al. 2012; Abramitzky et al. 2013).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e521">
   <s id="d1e526">
    Even though Africa is still the least urban continent in the world (and the sub-Saharan region of Africa particularly so), its rates of urbanization compared to the rest of the world are the highest (Gwebu 2006; United Nations 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e531">
    African urban centers are not generating the required level of economic and employment opportunities, particularly compared to previous urbanization trends in Asia (Jedwab 2013; Gollin et al. 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e536">
    Thus, many African urban centers have limited capacity to absorb Africa's youth bulge.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e541">
    This is partly reflected in African cities where youth unemployment and urban poverty are already major challenges for policy makers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e546">
    In absolute numbers, youth unemployment in Africa is more prevalent in urban areas than in rural areas (Czaika and de Haas 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e551">
    This suggests that the prospects for urban youth to find decent employment may not be better than those of their rural counterparts (Min-Harris 2010; Watson 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e556">
    In these contexts, monitoring recent trends in urban growth and their implications for rural-to-urban migration should be a top priority for African governments.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e561">
   <s id="d1e566">
    As in other SSA countries, migration patterns in Nigeria exhibit some important features and drivers.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e571">
    Several recent studies show that rural–urban migration is an important mobility phenomenon in Nigeria (e.g., UNECA 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e576">
    Unemployment and lack of rural opportunities are cited as key motivating factors, especially for the youth (IOM 2016).2 Migrants look for employment opportunities in nonfarm activities and urban areas with the hope of better income livelihood (Dorosh et al. 2012; Abramitzky et al. 2013; Deshingkar and Grimm 2005).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e581">
    Evolving rapid urbanization through developmental projects, which are mostly located in the urban areas, are likely to attract young people to migrate to cities, which in turn have resulted in the over-congestion and over-stretching of urban areas such Lagos, Abuja, Enugu and Kano (IOM 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e586">
    Indeed, the Nigerian government is keen to regulate and monitor urban growth and its implications and has recently given due policy attention to urbanization trends.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e591">
   <s id="d1e596">
    Most migration movements in Nigeria are temporary or seasonal.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e601">
    Rural youth in Nigeria, like in other African countries, engage in seasonal migration due to short-term unemployment and the cost implications of permanent migration (IOM 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e606">
    In other cases, youth also migrate for longer periods and even permanently to other areas in search of employment and other livelihood opportunities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e611">
    While temporary migration is relatively easier, those migrating permanently to major urban areas are probably those with good connections and those who can cover the costs of migration (mostly travel costs) (UNDP 2009; IOM 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e616">
    Thus, seasonal or temporal migration is the most common and affordable for rural youth, as it allows households to supplement their income, smooth consumption, and protect their asset base during the lean season (UNDP 2009).
   </s>
  </p>
</lit-review>
<method>
<l2>Data and variable measurement</l2>
  <l3>Data sources</l3>
  <p id="d1e641">
   <s id="d1e646">
    We employ panel data from the LSMS-ISA for Nigeria.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e651">
    These nationally representative data include detailed information on demographic and household characteristics, agricultural production, nonfarm income and other sources of income, allocation of family labor, hiring of labor, and access to services.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e656">
    The household characteristics module includes information on household members’ migration, education, labor allocation, and health.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e661">
    We exploit the three-wave Nigerian LSMS-ISA panel survey conducted in 2010/2011 (round 1), 2012/2013 (round 2), and 2015/2016 (round 3).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e666">
    The three surveys integrate comprehensive tracking questions on the occupation and locations of migrant household members, which enables analysis of migration decisions and outcomes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e671">
    The LSMS-ISA data also provide information on geolocalized references of households, which enables merging these longitudinal data with satellite-based night light intensity, rainfall, and incidence of conflict data.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e676">
    The night light intensity data come from the OLS sensors of the DMSP of the United States Air Force.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e681">
    Long-term rainfall data are extracted from the daily Africa Rainfall Climatology Version 2 (ARC2) of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Climate Prediction Center (NOAA-CPC) (Novella and Thiaw 2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e686">
    We extracted incidence of conflict data from armed conflict location and event data project (ACLED) (Raleigh and Dowd 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e691">
   <s id="d1e696">
    Variable measurement
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e701">
   <s id="d1e706">
    Outcome variable
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e711">
   <s id="d1e716">
    We define and distinguish youth migration in four ways.3 First, we consider a more generic definition of migration that involves any type of mobility for any reason and destinations, proxied by an indicator (dummy) variable for those individuals who were present in round 1(2) but either nonresident in round 2(3) and/or have been absent for at least one month during the previous 12 months before the round 2(3) survey was conducted.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e721">
    Hence, this captures both short- and long-term migration and may be denoted as “any type of migration.” It excludes deceased individuals and those who have moved within the same village.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e726">
    Rural youth in many SSA countries often migrate in search of seasonal employment to supplement their income in periods of the year when agricultural work is not available.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e731">
    Second, we classify the migration decision based on the duration of migration into temporary and permanent migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e736">
    Temporary migrants are those individuals who are listed as members of households in round 1(2) but have been absent for at least one month during the previous 12 months before the round 2(3) survey was conducted.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e741">
    Permanent migrants are those individuals who were household members in round 1(2), but not in round 2(3) for at least 12 months.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e746">
    Finally, we differentiate migrants into short- and long-distance migrants.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e751">
    Long-distance migrants are those individuals who were present in round 1(2) but reported to be nonresident in round 2(3) and who have moved out of state inside the country.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e756">
    Finally, we apply a more conservative definition of migration: that is, mobility for economic reasons.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e761">
    This focuses on those mobilities driven by economic incentives (e.g., in search of better economic opportunities).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e766">
    These migration typologies may provide differing insights for policy making as they describe the drivers and constraints facing different groups of migrants.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e771">
   <s id="d1e776">
    Construction of key explanatory variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e781">
   <s id="d1e786">
    Using the geolocalized and nationally representative panel data from LSMS-ISA Nigeria, we merge these panel data with the satellite-based night light intensity data.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e791">
    We then generate average night light intensity at local government area (LGA) and state level.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e796">
    To construct our key variable of interest, we compute the pre-existing (before the migration) night light intensity differences between potential migrant destinations and the point of origin.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e801">
    As we are analyzing migration decisions, we have both migrants with known destinations and nonmigrants who remained in their origin (i.e., have no destination).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e806">
    Those who migrated to a specific destination are expected to have considered potential destinations, while those not migrating are also believed to have considered whether to migrate to potential destinations or not.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e811">
    We thus aim to study the implication of urban growth in potential destinations for all individuals, as both migrants and nonmigrants are expected to have had information on potential destinations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e816">
    We define potential migrant destinations in two ways.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e821">
    First, given that our data show that the most common migration is within-state, we compute temporal average night light intensity within the state, excluding the LGA where the individual is living.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e826">
    Second, relying on external data, we identify states known for attracting highest level of migrants and define these states as main potential migrant destinations and compute temporal average night light intensity in these states.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e831">
    We then generate differences between these potential migrant destinations and the LGA where the potential migrant was living.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e836">
    We then employ these differences in night light intensity between the two spatial units (potential destination and origin of migration).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e841">
    This mimics the earliest economic migration models that were built on the hypothesis that the migration decision involves comparing potential (expected) wage differentials between two spatial units.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e846">
    Spatial differences in night light intensity between these two locations, we posit, can capture wage differentials or other differences in infrastructural and social services.
   </s>
  </p>
  </method>
<result>
   <l2>Descriptive results
   </l2>
  <p id="d1e861">
   <s id="d1e866">
    Youth migration and urban growth by night light intensity are the primary variables of interest.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e871">
    Table 1 presents summary statistics of the migration outcomes, night light intensity, and individual and household characteristics of youth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e876">
    About 17 percent of youth migrated between the three survey rounds.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e881">
    The results show that about 66 percent of youth migrants were temporary migrants and 34 percent were permanent migrants.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e886">
    Of total youth migrants, 34 percent were long-distance (out of state) migrants.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e891">
    Average night light intensity across Nigeria increased by about 30 percent from 2012 to 2015.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e896">
    Table 2 provides the distribution of covariates across migrant and nonmigrant youth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e901">
    As migration decisions are endogenous outcomes, this table shows significant observable differences between migrants and nonmigrants.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e906">
    Female youth are more likely to migrate than male.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e911">
    The average age of migrants is about 23 years.4 This indicates the higher rates of mobility by young people in Nigeria—with more than three-fourths of all migrants in Nigeria being between 15 and 35 years.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e916">
    Migrants tend to have higher and better formal education.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e921">
    Married youth are less likely to migrate than those who never married.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e926">
    Migrants are more likely to come from poorer households, as measured by land size, livestock ownership, and value of total assets.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e931">
    This suggests that there seem to be push factors for youth with limited access to assets and farmland (Bezu and Holden 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e936">
    Yet, poorer people are more likely to migrate.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e941">
    The most likely to migrate appear to be those with greater probability of success in urban zones, as indicated by education level, and fewer ties to rural zones, as indicated by asset holdings such as land and livestock.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e946">
    In accordance with this view, several studies have identified potential constraints and barriers to migration, including travel expenses and search costs (Hirvonen 2016; Morten and Oliveira 2016; Franklin 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e951">
   <s id="d1e956">
    TABLE 1. Descriptive summary statistics for outcome and explanatory variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e961">
   <s id="d1e966">
    PPP, purchasing power party; TLU, tropical livestock unit.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e971">
   <s id="d1e976">
    NOTES: Deviation from the mean is deviation of a given year's precipitation during the wet season from the long-term mean.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e981">
   <s id="d1e986">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e991">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e996">
   <s id="d1e1001">
    TABLE 2. Descriptive (pooled) statistics for individuals aged 15–35: by migration status
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1006">
   <s id="d1e1011">
    *p &lt; 0.10, **p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.01.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1016">
   <s id="d1e1021">
    NOTE: Deviation from the mean is deviation of a given year's precipitation during the wet season from the long-term mean.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1026">
   <s id="d1e1031">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1036">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1041">
   <s id="d1e1046">
    The LSMS data for Nigeria track migrants’ destinations, enabling us to compute average night light intensity at the migrants’ origin and destination LGA.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1051">
    Table
    <u>
     3 provides differences in night light intensity between youth migrant origin and destination areas.
    </u>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1056">
    The results show significant differences in urban growth as proxied by night light intensity between migrant origin and destination areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1061">
    Youth migrants are more likely to migrate to more urban areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1066">
    We disaggregate the level of urbanization into four categories: areas with zero night light intensity, areas with night light intensity between 0 and 4 digital number (DN), areas with night light intensity between 4 and 13 DN, and areas characterized by night light intensity above 13 DN.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1071">
   <s id="d1e1076">
    TABLE 3. Youth migrant origins and destinations urbanization differences
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1081">
   <s id="d1e1086">
    ***p &lt; 0.01.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1091">
   <s id="d1e1096">
    NOTE: We note this table is based on the sample of only migrants.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1101">
   <s id="d1e1106">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1111">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1116">
   <s id="d1e1121">
    Figure
    <u>
     1 shows youth migration by destinations.
    </u>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1126">
    The figure indicates that although a higher proportion of youth migrants moved to more urban areas, others migrated to areas with approximately the same or lower night light intensity.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1131">
    The figure shows that about 54 percent of youth migrants moved to areas with higher night light intensity compared to their origins, while about 19 and 27 percent, respectively, moved to areas with about the same night light intensity or lower night light intensity.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1136">
   <s id="d1e1141">
    FIGURE 1
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1146">
   <s id="d1e1151">
    Open in figure viewerPowerPoint
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1156">
   <s id="d1e1161">
    Youth migration by destinations
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1166">
   <s id="d1e1171">
    NOTE: This figure is based on the sample of only migrants.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1176">
   <s id="d1e1181">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1186">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1191">
   <s id="d1e1196">
    In Figure 2, we disaggregate youth migration by types of migrations and destinations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1201">
    The results show that migrant destinations vary with types of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1206">
    While about 54 percent of temporary and permanent migrants were more likely to move to areas with higher night light intensity, more than two-thirds of long-distance migrants moved to areas with higher night light intensity.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1211">
   <s id="d1e1216">
    FIGURE 2
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1221">
   <s id="d1e1226">
    Open in figure viewerPowerPoint
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1231">
   <s id="d1e1236">
    Types of migration by destinations (units are in percentage)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1241">
   <s id="d1e1246">
    NOTE: This figure is based on the sample of only migrants.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1251">
   <s id="d1e1256">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1261">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1266">
   <s id="d1e1271">
    Table 4 provides a matrix of night light intensities at the origins and destinations of migrants.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1276">
    About 61 percent of total youth migrants from areas with zero night light intensity (first row) moved to areas with greater than zero night light intensity.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1281">
    About 71 percent of total youth migrants from areas with above zero but less than 4 night light intensity (second row) moved to areas with night light intensities greater than 4.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1286">
    Similarly, about 96 percent of total youth migrants from areas with 4–13 night light intensity (third row) moved to areas with similar and higher night light intensity.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1291">
    For potential migrants who live in zones with at least some night light, zones with zero night light are very unattractive.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1296">
    This confirms the dominant rural–urban migration we observe in Nigeria.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1301">
   <s id="d1e1306">
    TABLE 4. Migrant origins and destinations matrix by urbanization categories
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1311">
   <s id="d1e1316">
    NOTE: We note this table is based on the sample of only migrants.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1321">
   <s id="d1e1326">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1331">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1336">
   <s id="d1e1341">
    Empirical strategies
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1346">
   <s id="d1e1351">
    We conduct our analysis at individual level and employ longitudinal data that provide temporal variation in migration outcomes and decisions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1356">
    These longitudinal data allow us to follow the same households across waves.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1361">
    Thus, we exploit both the spatial and temporal variations in our measure of differences in night light intensity between potential destinations and origins.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1366">
    We then link and quantify the impact of these dynamics in urban growth on temporal trends in migration decisions of youth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1368">The literature, predominantly owing to data limitations, has empirically mea- sured urbanization as a binary phenomenon, even though urbanization is better viewed as a continuum and an ongoing process (Calì and Menon 2013; Christiaensen and Todo 2014; Abay and Amare 2018; Amare et al. 2020).</s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1371">
   <s id="d1e1376">
    Specifically, we estimate alternative fixed effect models that control for spatial (village) level effects.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1381">
    This captures time-invariant differences across villages.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1386">
    However, some types of temporally varying shocks may simultaneously affect urbanization trends and migration outcomes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1391">
    Similarly, large-scale migration trends and outcomes may shape urbanization trends, introducing potential reverse causality problems.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1396">
    To address these issues, we compute the difference for the period before migration takes place, estimating migration outcomes in time t + 1 (round 2 or 3) against the differences in night light intensity between potential migrant destinations and origin of migration in the previous periods,  (round 1 or 2).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1401">
    In this way, we ensure that urbanization as proxied by captured light intensity differentials is not affected by subsequent youth migration decisions.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1406">
   <s id="d1e1411">
    The impact of urban growth on youth migration is investigated using the following linear probability model:
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1416">
   <s id="d1e1421">
    (1)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1426">
   <s id="d1e1431">
    where  denotes alternative outcome indicators for individual i in LGA v and at time t + 1. is the difference in night light intensity between potential migrant destinations (an average across likely destinations) and the origin of migration at t. is a vector of other individual- and household-level characteristics at t that may influence outmigration decisions and outcomes, while captures a vector of village (LGA)-level geographic dummies.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1436">
    As we are controlling for LGA-level fixed effects (, the parameters  capture the impact of both spatial and temporal differences in night light intensity between potential destination and origin of migration.  stands for time dummies capturing survey waves.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1441">
    Finally, is an idiosyncratic error term, capturing other unobserved factors that may affect youth migration decisions.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1446">
   <s id="d1e1451">
    We hypothesize that these spatial differences in night light intensity may correspond to wage or labor productivity differences in these two locations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1456">
    More specifically, the spatial and temporal differences in urban growth as captured through differences in night light intensity are expected to attract youth outmigration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1461">
    Individuals living in the same village are expected to be exposed to similar urbanization shocks, implying correlation in unobserved effects across individuals in the same village.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1466">
    Because of this, we cluster standard errors at LGA level.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1471">
    As we are controlling for LGA-level fixed effects, our identifying variation comes from temporal variation in the differences in night light intensity between potential destination and origin of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1476">
    That is, likely urban growth in potential destinations relative to urban growth in origin of migration.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1481">
   <s id="d1e1486">
    As described earlier in the “data and variable measurement” section, we consider alternative definitions of youth outmigration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1491">
    We start from the broader definition of migration that involves the movement and departure of people from their previous residences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1496">
    Such migration can be for any purpose and to any destination.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1501">
    Depending on the nature of the migration outcome, we also classify migration into temporary and permanent, as well as into short-distance and long-distance.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1506">
    Finally, we employ a more conservative definition that restricts migration into those migrating for economic reasons.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1511">
    Besides quantifying the overall implication of urban growth on youth migration, we also explore heterogeneity in the impact of urban growth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1516">
    We particularly examine heterogeneity in the impact of urban growth on the youth migration decision by sex, age, education, assets, and land ownership.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1521">
    This is intuitive, given that previous studies have shown substantial heterogeneity in migration propensities across these observable characteristics.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1526">
    For instance, Kosec et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1531">
    (
    <u>
     2018) show that youth outmigration propensity is significantly correlated with access to land, with those expecting to inherit land being less likely to migrate.
    </u>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1536">
    For this purpose, we run several sample splits and estimate Equation (1) for each sample split along the above demographic and socioeconomic dimensions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1541">
    For instance, to uncover gendered responses to urban growth, we estimate Equation (1) separately for female and male youth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1546">
    We run similar disaggregation across education, land endowment and physical assets.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1551">
    Uncovering the heterogeneous responses can inform relevant youth and urban development programs and policies.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1556">
    For example, if landless individuals are more responsive to urban growth, one could argue that migration may help to transfer less utilized labor from rural areas to urban areas.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1561">
   <s id="d1e1566">
    Results and discussion
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1571">
   <s id="d1e1576">
    This section presents and discusses the main results of Equation (1).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1581">
    For simplicity, we employ linear probability models in estimating the specification in this equation.5 We then estimate both unconditional and conditional relationships between urban growth and youth mobility.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1586">
    We focus and report results for models controlling for LGA-level fixed effects.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1591">
    The main empirical specifications are estimated for all types of definitions of outmigration defined earlier in the “Data and variable measurement” section.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1596">
    Furthermore, we define two potential composite migrant destinations and compute night light intensity differences between these migrant destinations and origin of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1601">
    The first composite definition assumes within-state migration as the dominant pattern of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1606">
    For this, we compute differences in average night light intensity in the state and the LGA where the individual is living.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1611">
    The central idea is if other neighboring LGAs are urbanizing relative to the LGA the individual is living, he (she) is more likely to out-migrate to these LGAs.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1616">
    Our second definition of potential destinations identifies some states known for attracting migrants and constructs a composite of these states as a potential migrant destination.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1621">
    As we are controlling for LGA-level fixed effects in all our estimations, any time-invariant differences across the two spatial units (potential destination and origin of migration) should be captured by these fixed effects and hence are not concerns.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1626">
   <s id="d1e1631">
    Table 5 provides estimation results assuming that migration destination is within the state while Table 6 reports similar estimates using our second definition of main migration destinations.6 Both tables show that the spatial differences in night light intensity between the two spatial units (main destination and origin of migration) and the underlying associated dynamics in these differences is significantly and positively correlated with youth outmigration.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1636">
   <s id="d1e1641">
    TABLE 5. Impacts of urban growth on youth migration (within state migration)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1646">
   <s id="d1e1651">
    *p &lt; 0.10, **p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.01.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1656">
   <s id="d1e1661">
    NOTE: Deviation from the mean is standardized deviation of a given year's precipitation during the wet season from the long-term mean.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1666">
    Standard errors, clustered at LGA level, are given in parentheses.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1671">
   <s id="d1e1676">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1681">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1686">
   <s id="d1e1691">
    TABLE 6. The impacts of urban growth on youth migration (five major migrant destination states)
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1696">
   <s id="d1e1701">
    *p &lt; 0.10, **p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.01.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1706">
   <s id="d1e1711">
    NOTE: Deviation from the mean is standardized deviation of a given year's precipitation during the wet season from the long-term mean.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1716">
    Standard errors, clustered at LGA level, are given in parentheses.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1721">
   <s id="d1e1726">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1731">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1736">
   <s id="d1e1741">
    Furthermore, these results are consistent across all definitions of outmigration, with slight and intuitive differences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1746">
    For instance, the effects are stronger for short-distance migrants, who are more likely to be observing urban growth trends in their neighboring urban areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1751">
    Similarly, the effects are greater for the broader definition of outmigration, compared to the narrow definition of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1756">
    Overall, the main results in Tables
    <u>
     5 and 6 highlight that potential urban growth in neighboring areas may induce youth outmigration.
    </u>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1761">
    This may increase unemployment and result in overloaded public services in urban centers.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1766">
   <s id="d1e1771">
    The remaining covariates in Tables 5 and 6 assume expected signs.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1776">
    For instance, those with higher education, and relatively older individuals, are more likely to outmigrate.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1781">
    Livestock and land assets reduce permanent youth outmigration, while farm size encourages long-distance and seasonal temporary youth migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1786">
    The effect of land endowment in reducing permanent migration is consistent with similar findings from Ethiopia (Bezu and Holden 2014).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1791">
    In addition, youth from areas exposed to drought and shortfalls in rainfall (climate variability) and conflicts are more likely to migrate.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1796">
    This is consistent with previous evidence highlighting that vulnerabilities resulting from climate variability and weather shocks are encouraging rural–urban migration in Africa and other continents (e.g., Mueller et al. 2014; Cattaneo and Peri 2016; Baez et al. 2017; Henderson et al. 2017; UNECA 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1801">
    Unplanned and conflict-induced migration seems to result in short-distance migration, perhaps as youth look for short- and long-term opportunities in adjacent areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1806">
    This implies that in addition to the pull factors arising from urban growth in neighboring areas, push factors in the current residence, including increasing development gap and inequality, deprivation of youth access to land, persistent poverty, natural disasters, conflict, and economic and political instabilities may trigger further outmigration (Bah et al. 2003; Naude 2010; Amare et al. 2012 Min-Harris 2010; UNECA 2017; Franklin 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1811">
   <s id="d1e1816">
    Heterogeneous responses to night light intensity
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1821">
   <s id="d1e1826">
    In this section, we explore potential heterogeneities in the response of youth to potential urban growth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1831">
    Some groups are potentially more responsive to urbanization in neighboring area than are others for three reasons.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1836">
    First, individuals have different skill sets, for which there may be varying demand in urban labor markets, implying differences in responses to urban pull factors.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1841">
    For example, those individuals with a better education are more likely to expect positive returns from rural–urban migration, because educated and skilled individuals are more likely to find employment opportunities in urban areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1846">
    Second, variations in push factors in rural areas may induce heterogeneous responses.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1851">
    For instance, those youth lacking the productive resources and farm inputs (or those struggling to enter farming) may be tempted to outmigrate and so respond to neighboring urban growth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1856">
    Third, migration involves substantial costs, including travel expenses and search costs (Hirvonen 2016; Morten and Oliveira 2016; Franklin 2018), implying that these costs may constrain those youth with liquidity constraints.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1861">
    We examine potential heterogeneities in the responses of individuals with varying attributes corresponding to these three factors.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1866">
   <s id="d1e1871">
    These potential heterogeneities in the response of individuals are explored by using the interaction terms involving temporal dynamics in night light intensity and observable attributes related to gender, age, education, access to land, and asset ownership.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1876">
    The differential analysis by youth observable attributes shows stark differences in elasticity to urban growth.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1881">
   <s id="d1e1886">
    Table 7 provides the main estimates, suppressing all additional controls listed in Table 5.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1891">
    Panel A shows that females generally migrate more but they respond less to differences in night light intensity, that is, there are statistically significant differences in the responses of females to urban growth for long-distance, and economic migration (where females have a lower response).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1896">
    Panel B shows that older youth generally migrate more and they are also more responsive to night light intensity relative to younger youth cohorts except for the permanent and short-distance categories of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1901">
    This may suggest that young migrants favor traveling shorter distances to reduce moving costs and may secure nearby off-farm employment.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1906">
    Panel C shows that those individuals with higher education generally migrate more, but they are less responsive to night light intensity except for those in the economic migration category.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1911">
    This is consistent with the hypothesis that more educated rural youth expect urban demand for skilled labor to be higher than in the rural areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1916">
    This could be because educated young people do not view agriculture to be attractive.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1921">
    Educated youth and those with the means to migrate are setting their sights on urban and nonfarming sectors in the hope of securing better opportunities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1926">
    Panel D shows that those individuals with better access to land are more likely to respond to urban growth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1931">
    Panel E in Table 7, alongside the results related to access to land, suggest constraints and costs to migration may limit youth migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1936">
    Those lacking assets are less responsive to night light differentials (except for permanent and short distance) because of these constraints.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1941">
   <s id="d1e1946">
    TABLE 7. Heterogeneous responses to urban growth
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1951">
   <s id="d1e1956">
    *p &lt; 0.10, **p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.01.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1961">
   <s id="d1e1966">
    NOTE: This table reports interaction effects between urban growth and observable characteristics of youth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1971">
    In Panel A, we interact the gender individuals with urban growth in potential destinations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1976">
    Panel B entails similar interactions between age of individuals and urban growth.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1981">
    We define indictor variable for older youth, a variable that assumes a value of 1 for those above the median age of youth in our sample (i.e., 24 years old or older) and 0 for those below the median age.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1986">
    Panel C interacts education and urban growth by defining a dummy variable assuming a value of 1 for those attaining above the median educational attainment and 0 for those below the median.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1991">
    Panel D interacts landholdings and urban growth again by generating indicator variable for those households owning above and below the median landholding.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1996">
    Panel E interacts asset holdings with urban growth by defining an indicator variable for those youth owning above and below the median assets in our sample.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2001">
    Standard errors, clustered at LGA level, are given in parentheses.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2006">
   <s id="d1e2011">
    SOURCE: Authors’ calculations based on Nigeria LSMS-ISA 2010–2011, 2012/2013, and 2015/2016.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2016">
    The National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC) of the United States’ National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2021">
   <s id="d1e2026">
    Intuitively, the overall results in Table
    <u>
     7 show that youth exhibit heterogeneous behavioral responses in their migration decisions, suggesting they have varying incentives as well as push and pull factors to migrate.
    </u>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2031">
    In order to slow the influx of youth to urban areas in many SSA countries, policy makers need more tailored interventions that can address the varying incentives and responses that induce and sustain the phenomenon.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2036">
    For instance, access to farmland and productivity-enhancing investments in the agricultural sector may encourage youth to engage in agriculture (while still taking advantage of short-term opportunities to migrate).
   </s>
  </p>
</result>
<conclusion>
   <l1>Concluding remarks</l1>
  <p id="d1e2051">
   <s id="d1e2056">
    To shed light on youth rural–urban migration in SSA, we have employed nationally representative longitudinal data from Nigeria along with satellite-based night light intensity markers to assess the links between urban growth, youth migration, and rural development in an African context.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2061">
    We first examined the implication of spatial and temporal differences in levels of urban growth between migrants’ destinations and their origin of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2066">
    Using premigration spatial and temporal differences in night light intensities allows us to isolate the causal impact of urban growth on youth migration decisions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2071">
    We employ alternative indicators and definitions of migration to probe the robustness of our results.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2076">
    We further examine potential heterogeneities in the response of youth to urban growth in neighboring states and urban centers.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2081">
   <s id="d1e2086">
    The results show that urban growth in neighboring and potential migrant destination areas encourages youth migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2091">
    Urbanization and higher disparities between the points of origin in rural areas and the destinations in urban areas, as captured through differences in night light intensities, are likely to induce youth migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2096">
    These differences in night light intensities are likely indicative of rural–urban differences in infrastructure, access to services, and employment opportunities, leading to growing outmigration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2101">
    One approach to abate this phenomenon is to reduce these disparities and improve opportunities (including access to farmland) at the points of origin.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2106">
    We find that those youth with limited access to farmland are more likely to migrate permanently while farm size tends to increase all but permanent migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2111">
    Livestock ownership consistently reduces outmigration, while the more educated are likely to leave in search of better opportunities in urban areas.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2116">
    Those with higher education, and relatively older individuals, are more likely to outmigrate.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2121">
    In addition, those youth from farm households, and in areas that are exposed to drought and shortfalls in rainfall (climate variability) and conflicts, are more likely to migrate.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2126">
    We also find that youth exhibit heterogeneous responses to urban growth, suggesting variations in incentives and in the underlying causes of migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2131">
    Individuals with better access to physical assets, land, and higher education are more likely to respond to urban growth and take up seasonal and economic migration.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2136">
    Our findings are consistent with some evolving evidence on the role of urban growth in respect of the demand for and supply of rural labor (e.g., Kanbur et al. 2019).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2141">
    In terms of rural policy making, the evidence presented suggests that managing youth outmigration in many SSA countries will require more tailored interventions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2146">
    These will need to address the varying incentives, constraints, and push and pull factors that youth face at their points of origin.
   </s>
  </p>
</conclusion>
 </body>
</html>