<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="discourse.v4_cn.css"?><html xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://wkwsci.ntu.edu.sg/discourse# discourse.v4_cn.xsd"> 
 <head><title>
  Cultural productivism and public support for the universal basic income from a cross-national perspective
 </title>
 </head>
 <body>
   <l1>Cultural productivism and public support for the universal basic income from a cross-national perspective</l1>
<abstract>
   <l2>
    ABSTRACT
   </l2>
  <p id="d1e76">
   <s id="d1e81">
    <arg argID="001" type="claim" claimType="research_issue">It has been hypothesized that the capacity of universal basic income (UBI) to attract wider public support is impaired by the strength of productivist cultural norms and values, common to the majority of develope societies.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e86">
    <arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">The paper contributes to literature on attitudes towards UBI by empirically investigating this hypothesis from a multi-level cross-national perspective,</arg> <arg argID="002" type="support" supportType="method">using the European Social Survey (ESS) Round 8 data on UBI support for 23 countries.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e91">
    <arg argID="003" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">It seeks to determine whether and to what extent the strength of cultural productivism can explain cross-national variation in public support for the implementation of UBI.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e96">
    <arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="result">Two main ﬁndings are reported.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e101">
    <arg argID="005" type="claim" claimType="result">First, the results demonstrate that the public are less susceptible to supporting UBI in countries where average employment commitment is higher.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e106">
    <arg argID="006" type="claim" claimType="result">Second, the results show that, even though employment commitment is a strong predictor of cross-national variation in the public support for UBI, the eﬀect is surpassed and explained by GDP, which itself is negatively related to the outcome.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e111">
    <arg argID="007" type="claim" claimType="general_result">The study argues that the capacity of UBI to appeal to the general public is limited by the prosperity of post-industrial societies, rather than by the cultural attachment of their populations to paid work.</arg></s>
  </p>
</abstract>  
<intro>
   <l2>Introduction</l2>
  <p id="d1e146">
   <s id="d1e151">
    <arg argID="001" type="context" contextType="practical_background">In recent years, there has been renewed public and media interest in universal basic income (UBI).</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e201"><arg argID="002" type="claim" claimType="general_statement">UBI has been debated as an alternative to post-war welfare institutions in the era when employment no longer secures ﬁnancial security while human labour is under increasing risk of replacement by artiﬁcial intelligence (van der Veen and Groot 2000).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e206"><arg argID="003" type="context" contextType="practical_background">Public and media attention reached its peak between 2016 and 2018 when a campaign in Switzerland resulted in an unsuccessful referendum about the proposal, and the Finnish government launched an experiment with UBI paid to a sample of jobseekers (De Wispelaere 2016).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e211">
    <arg argID="004" type="claim" claimType="research_issue">Systematic attention has also been paid to UBI in academia (for an overview, see Widerquist et al. 2013).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e221">
    <arg argID="004" type="support" supportType="example">Researchers have investigated a wide range of UBI-related topics, including the proposal’s normative justiﬁcations (e.g. Van Parijs 1992), the technical aspects of implementation as well as the potential eﬀects on the economy and society (see Gilroy et al. 2013; Sommer 2016; Pereira 2017).</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e236">
   <s id="d1e241"><arg argID="010" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">A growing research area investigates the feasibility of UBI with respect to public support for its implementation (Andersson and Kangas 2005; Bay and Pedersen 2006; Parolin and Siöland 2020; Vlandas 2019).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e246">
    <arg argID="011" type="claim" claimType="research_gap">However, systematic attention has not yet been paid to one ideological factor traditionally perceived as hindering the proposal’s public acceptance.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e251"><arg argID="015" type="claim" claimType="literature-summarize/generalize">At a theoretical level, scholars have argued that the public are unlikely to ﬁnd UBI normatively legitimate and pointed to the contrast between the non-productivist nature of its underlying principles and the productivist normative foundations of modern societies (van der Veen 1991; Goodin 2001; Oﬀe 2001; Bauman 2005; De Wispelaere and Noguera 2012).</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e256">
    <arg argID="015" type="support" supportType="explanation/elaboration">According to the argument, citizens of modern work- societies, socialized into beliefs about the individual and collective desirability of paid work (Oﬀe 1992), are unlikely to support a welfare reform which explicitly assumes the decoupling of income and welfare entitlements from income-earning activities (Oﬀe et al. 1996).</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e260">
   <s id="d1e262">
    <arg argID="020" type="claim" claimType="research_question">But is the strength of productivist cultural norms and values really a decisive factor which impairs support for the implementation of UBI?</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e264"><arg argID="021" type="claim" claimType="research_question">Are societies where paid work carries a stronger cultural importance less prone to being sympathetic towards UBI?</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e266"><arg argID="022" type="claim" claimType="research_question">If so, does cultural produc- tivism explain the support as the most important factor, independently of other macro-characteristics associated with pro-welfare attitudes?</arg></s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e276">
   <s id="d1e281">
    <arg argID="025" type="claim" claimType="research_objective">The article aims to contribute to welfare attitudes research by empirically examining these questions from a multi-level cross-national perspec- tive,</arg> <arg argID="025" type="support" supportType="method">using the ESS Round 8 data on 23 developed societies.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e286">
    <arg argID="026" type="claim" claimType="contribution/recommendation">While not the ﬁrst analysis of ESS data on public support for UBI, the paper complements existing studies (see Parolin and Siöland 2020; Vlandas 2019) with its speciﬁc focus on cultural productivism hypothesis.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e291">
    <arg argID="030" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">The paper proceeds as follows.</arg>
   </s>
   <s id="d1e301">
    <arg argID="031" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">The first part reviews the theoretical argument about why the strength of productivist cultural norms and values may interfere with the public’s support for UBI, putting it in the context of evidence from welfare attitudes research.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e306">
    <arg argID="032" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">It then discusses cultural productivism and argues for a distinction between its normative and expressive dimensions.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e311">
    <arg argID="033" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">Alternative explanations for cross-national variation in support of UBI are considered next.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e316">
    <arg argID="034" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">The analytical part begins with a formulation of hypotheses and a description of data, together with measures of variables.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e321"><arg argID="035" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">Descriptive results are presented ﬁrst, followed by multi-variate results from mixed-eﬀects logistic models with country-level random intercepts.</arg></s>
   <s id="d1e326"><arg argID="036" type="description" descriptionType="outline_the_structure">The study is concluded by a discussion of the results in light of relevant theories.</arg></s>
  </p>
</intro>
  <p id="d1e331">
   <s id="d1e336">
    Literature review
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e341">
   <s id="d1e346">
    Cultural productivism and public support for the implementation of UBI
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e351">
   <s id="d1e356">
    UBI is generally deﬁned ‘an income paid by a political community to all its members on an individual basis, without means test or work requirement’ (Van Parijs 2004, 8).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e361">
    The main feature which distinguishes UBI from existing welfare arrangements is the non-productivist nature1 of its under- lying principles.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e366">
    While essentially all modern welfare states are producti- vist, in the sense that they are concerned with ensuring the smooth supply of labour to productive sectors of the economy (Goodin 2001) and assume that all able-bodied persons should be under economic compulsion to perform paid work (van der Veen 1991), UBI asserts a decoupling of income entitlements from income-earning activities (Oﬀe et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e371">
    1996).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e376">
    Such a decoupling has been advocated as just and necessary for the main- tenance of ﬁnancial security in precarious economic contexts (van der Veen and Groot 2000).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e381">
    On the other hand, it has been recognized as potentially problematic with respect to UBI’s feasibility.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e386">
    Since productivist norms are considered to characterize modern societies as such, it has been hypothesized that the general public may perceive a non-productivist UBI proposal as ideologically illegitimate (Oﬀe 2001; Bauman 2005; De Wispe- laere and Noguera 2012).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e391">
   <s id="d1e396">
    1Some versions of UBI advocated by the political right (e.g., Friedman 1968) may actually be perceived as productivist.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e401">
    These typically assume below-subsistence payments and the abolishment of existing social transfers (De Wispelaere 2016), thus reducing eﬀective marginal tax rates and incentivizing low-paid employment (Gorz 1999).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e406">
    This seems unlikely to be the case in the present study; the UBI conceptual- ization by ESS assumes the grant covers ‘essential living costs’ and replaces ‘many’ but not all beneﬁts.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e411">
   <s id="d1e416">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark2">
    </span>
    that the work-centred belief system has become largely immune to any revision attempts.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e421">
    In a similar fashion, De Wispelaere and Noguera (2012) assert that a widely shared belief that paid work is a core value and obligation and that beneﬁts should be restricted to those who deserve them limits UBI’s capacity to generate positive reactions among the general public.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e426">
   <s id="d1e431">
    Despite these concerns, prior representative polls have revealed that UBI enjoys substantial, albeit varying degrees of, public support in diﬀerent national contexts.2 In 2018, 48% of Americans favoured UBI to compensate workers who had lost jobs due to advances in artiﬁcial intelligence (Gallup Inc.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e436">
    and Northeastern University 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e441">
    Similarly, 49% of Britons in 2017 said they would support the UK government in introducing UBI (Ipsos MORI 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e446">
   <s id="d1e451">
    2003 (Bay and Pedersen 2006) and 46% of Swedes in 2001 (Andersson and Kangas 2005) supported the idea of UBI.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e456">
   <s id="d1e461">
    The existing studies have yet to explore whether and to what extent public support for UBI can be related to the strength of productivist cul- tural norms and values.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e466">
    Some studies have examined the eﬀect of individ- uals’ perception of deservingness of needy groups.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e471">
    Arguably, individuals who believe that neediness is a result of personal failure should also value hard work and eﬀort.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e476">
    Andersson and Kangas (2005) reported that individual blame for unemployment and poverty was the only factor which explained the variance in attitudes concerning UBI in both Sweden and Finland.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e481">
    Bay and Pedersen (2006) also showed that Norwegians who believed that the poor themselves are to be blamed for their situation were less likely to sympathize with UBI.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e486">
   <s id="d1e491">
    Useful information can be inferred from studies investigating the impact of productivist norms on preferences for welfare policies based on opposite principles, such as conditionality and targeting.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e496">
    In a Dutch study, Jeene et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e501">
    (2013) found that the work ethic measured at the indi- vidual level increased the emphasis on deservingness criteria for disability pension recipients.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e506">
    Such a relationship was also found with respect to preferences for the design of unemployment beneﬁts.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e511">
   <s id="d1e516">
    2Comparability of those polls is limited due to diﬀerent wording of the UBI question (see Online Appendix
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e521">
   <s id="d1e526">
    A, Table A1 for an overview).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e531">
   <s id="d1e536">
    <span class="anchor" id="Dimensions_of_productivism">
    </span>
    unemployment beneﬁts, which disproportionally rewards those who con- tribute to the production of welfare.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e541">
   <s id="d1e546">
    Dimensions of productivism
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e551">
   <s id="d1e556">
    Productivist cultural norms and values have been claimed to characterize virtually all modern societies so profoundly that scholars refer to these as waged-work societies (Oﬀe 1992; Bauman 2005).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e561">
    If exaggerated, this argu- mentation would imply that the implementation of UBI is equally unfea- sible in any developed society.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e566">
    However, cross-national work orientation research has demonstrated that modern societies diﬀer greatly with respect to the strength of various work-related attitudes (Gesthuizen and Verbakel 2011; Stam et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e571">
    2013; Turunen and Nätti 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e576">
   <s id="d1e581">
    This paper narrows its focus to two dimensions of work orientations, which reﬂect the main types of the cultural importance of work beyond its manifest income-producing function.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e586">
    If aggregated at the level of countries, they can be used to characterize the strength of the productivist cultural ethos of entire societies.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e591">
   <s id="d1e596">
    The ﬁrst dimension of cultural productivism reﬂects the degree to which work is considered to be normatively important, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e601">
    valued as a moral obli- gation to which individuals are subjected (Furåker 2012).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e606">
    This type of importance corresponds to the sociological category of the work ethic, that is, a conviction that work is primarily a moral duty and not a matter of personal motives, preferences or values (Stam et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e611">
    2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e616">
    The work ethic is based on values such as hard work, self-denial and avoidance of idle- ness (Highhouse et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e621">
    2010).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e626">
    Previous research has shown that there is a substantial cross-national variation in the work ethic across societies.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e631">
    In the European context, a stronger work ethic was found in countries with a Muslim and Orthodox religious heritage and in societies with a commu- nist past, while a weaker work ethic was found in economically advanced societies as well as in those with generous welfare states (Stam et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e636">
    2013).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e641">
    The second dimension of productivism reﬂects the degree to which work is expressively important, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e646">
    valued for beneﬁcial intrinsic proper- ties which motivate the willingness to engage in productive activities.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e651">
    This dimension can be captured by the concept of employment commitment, established in work orientations research.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e656">
    The concept measures people’s willingness to work by asking whether they would continue working even if the ﬁnancial need to work was removed (Furåker 2012).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e661">
   <s id="d1e666">
    <span class="anchor" id="Alternative_explanations">
    </span>
    growth and self-indulgence (Highhouse et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e671">
    2010) and which has been considered to replace the traditional work ethic of duty in post-industrial societies (Méda and Vendramin 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e676">
    Comparative research has found a stronger employment commitment in economically prosperous countries (Turunen and Nätti 2017), country contexts with generous welfare beneﬁts (Esser 2005), and high and activating social spending (van der Wel and Halvorsen 2015).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e681">
   <s id="d1e686">
    Alternative explanations
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e691">
   <s id="d1e696">
    Earlier analyses of the ESS data indicated that stronger support for UBI is found in countries with lower social spending (Parolin and Siöland 2020) and less generous welfare regimes (Vlandas 2019), suggesting that Eur- opeans welcome the scheme mainly as a way to improve their welfare stan- dards (Meuleman 2018).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e701">
    Hence, individuals’ preferences for UBI may be also shaped by factors associated with general pro-welfare attitudes.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e706">
   <s id="d1e711">
    First, the cross-national variation in UBI support could reﬂect compo- sitional diﬀerences between countries with respect to social categories prone to supporting public welfare.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e716">
    Such categories comprise individuals with utilitarian self-interest in welfare programmes, and/or those whose support reﬂects an ideological position.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e721">
    Women, young adults, individuals with low skills and income, and the unemployed are typically recognized among the supportive classes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e726">
    From an ideological perspective, personal values such as egalitarian ideology and trust have been identiﬁed among the attitudinal covariates of public welfare support (compare Blekesaune and Quadagno 2003; Gelissen 2008; Dallinger 2010).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e731">
   <s id="d1e736">
    Second, support for UBI may be aﬀected by the welfare institutions that are currently in place.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e741">
    Redistributive policies are typically less advocated in countries with high welfare spending, where high tax burdens discourage citizens from supporting further redistribution (Gelissen 2008; Pfeifer 2009).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e746">
    On the other hand, demand for redistribution is higher in societies with higher income inequalities (Midtbø 2018).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e751">
   <s id="d1e756">
    Third, cultural context could matter too.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e761">
    Support for universalistic beneﬁts in general requires cultural characteristics, such as trust and a commitment to egalitarian values (Bay and Pedersen 2006).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e766">
    High trusting countries tend to be more supportive of public welfare (Blekesaune and Quadagno 2003), while ideologically egalitarian societies are less con- ditional in terms of their solidarity with those in need (van Oorschot 2006).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e771">
    Fourth, public support for UBI can also be aﬀected by business cycle phases.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e776">
   <s id="d1e781">
    <span class="anchor" id="Contribution,_aim,_hypotheses">
    </span>
    typically higher when unemployment increases and lower in times of economic prosperity (Blekesaune and Quadagno 2003; Pfeifer 2009; Dal- linger 2010).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e786">
   <s id="d1e791">
    Finally, cross-national variation in support of UBI can also reﬂect
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e796">
   <s id="d1e801">
    diﬀerences in socio-economic development.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e806">
    Wealthy countries have a diﬀerent composition of population in terms of education, family patterns or life expectancy (Midtbø 2018), as well as with respect to the value orien- tations of their citizens, who tend to prioritize autonomy and self- expression over material security (Inglehart and Welzel 2005).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e811">
   <s id="d1e816">
    Contribution, aim, hypotheses
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e821">
   <s id="d1e826">
    Although cultural discourses about the importance of paid work have been repeatedly considered to pose a challenge for UBI’s public accep- tance, the argument has been justiﬁed mainly at the theoretical level.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e831">
    This paper aims to contribute to welfare attitudes research by empirically examining the argument from a multi-level cross-national perspective.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e836">
    Two general hypotheses are formulated.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e841">
   <s id="d1e846">
    If the theoretical logic of the argument holds, support for UBI should be lower in countries where productivist norms and values are more pro- nounced (H1).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e851">
    Since there are two diﬀerent dimensions to the cultural importance of work, there are also two alternative versions of this hypoth- esis.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e856">
    The ﬁrst version expects to ﬁnd weaker support for UBI in countries where the social norm to work is high, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e861">
    in societies with a stronger work ethic (H1a).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e866">
    The second version expects to ﬁnd lower UBI support in countries where the expressive importance of work is high, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e871">
    in societies characterized by a stronger employment commitment (H1b).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e876">
   <s id="d1e881">
    The second hypothesis investigates the relative strength and robustness of the assumed relationship (H2).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e886">
    If the main obstacle preventing UBI from gaining substantial popular support is cultural productivism, one should expect the eﬀect to be relatively stronger than the eﬀects of other macro-covariates associated with the public’s support for welfare and redistribution (H2a).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e891">
    If cultural productivism explains attitudes towards UBI as a factor sui generis, the eﬀect is also expected to be sustained when these characteristics are controlled for (H2b).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e896">
   <s id="d1e901">
    Data
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e906">
   <s id="d1e911">
    The paper uses survey data from the ESS Round 8 (ESS 2016).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e916">
   <s id="d1e921">
    <span class="anchor" id="Method">
    </span>
    samples of the following 23 countries: Austria, Belgium, the Czech Repub- lic, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Lithuania, the Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Russian Fed- eration, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland and the UK.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e926">
    Responses with missing values were list-wise deleted and the pooled sample used in the analysis consisted of 39,016 individuals clustered within 23 countries.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e931">
   <s id="d1e936">
    Method
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e941">
   <s id="d1e946">
    Given the hierarchical structure of the data and the multi-level nature of the research problem, the models were estimated as mixed-eﬀects logistic regressions with country-speciﬁc random intercepts.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e951">
    To facilitate the interpretation of results, all predictors were grand-mean centred (Enders and Toﬁghi 2007).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e956">
    Additionally, quantitative variables were stan- dardized by twice their standard deviation, to allow for direct comparison of their relative eﬀect sizes (Gelman 2008).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e961">
   <s id="d1e966">
    Measures of variables
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e971">
   <s id="d1e976">
    Dependent variable
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e981">
   <s id="d1e986">
    Respondents’ support for the implementation of UBI in their country was used as a dependent variable.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e991">
    A short introductory paragraph explaining the basic principles of UBI was presented ﬁrst, followed by a question investigating the degree of support for the scheme.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e996">
    The deﬁnition of UBI provided to the respondents is speciﬁc and makes reference to both its beneﬁts and associated costs.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1001">
    One can thus expect to obtain more realistic estimates of respondents’ support for UBI, which was found to be sensitive to the phrasing and framing of the ques- tion (Bay and Pedersen 2006; Ipsos MORI 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1006">
   <s id="d1e1011">
    Some countries are […] talking about introducing a basic income
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1016">
   <s id="d1e1021">
    scheme.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1026">
   <s id="d1e1031">
    The government pays everyone a monthly income to cover essential living costs
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1036">
   <s id="d1e1041">
    It replaces many other social beneﬁts
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1046">
   <s id="d1e1051">
    The purpose is to guarantee everyone a minimum standard of living
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1056">
   <s id="d1e1061">
    Everyone receives the same amount regardless of whether or not they are working
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1066">
   <s id="d1e1071">
    <span class="anchor" id="Main_country-level_predictors">
    </span>
    People also keep the money they earn from work or other sources
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1076">
   <s id="d1e1081">
    This scheme is paid for by taxes
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1086">
   <s id="d1e1091">
    Overall, would you be against or in favour of having this scheme in [your] country?
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1096">
   <s id="d1e1101">
    Respondents could express their support on a 1–4 scale anchored
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1106">
   <s id="d1e1111">
    according to the variants ‘Strongly against’ (value 1) and ‘Strongly in favour’ (value 4).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1116">
    Responses were recoded into a binary variable with the value 1 assigned to respondents supporting the implementation of UBI and the value 0 assigned to those who were against.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1121">
   <s id="d1e1126">
    Main country-level predictors
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1131">
   <s id="d1e1136">
    The ﬁrst predictor of cultural productivism captures the normative impor- tance of work in a country, measured as the average work ethic.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1141">
    The index is based on a battery of items from the 2008/2009 wave of the European Values Study (EVS 2015).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1146">
    For Israel, the indicator was aggregated from the 1999/2004 wave of the World Value Study (WVS 2015).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1151">
    Although rela- tively older, such attitudinal data tend to be rather stable over time and can thus still appropriately capture the work ethic.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1156">
    Respondents were asked to indicate their agreement with ﬁve statements: (a) ‘In order to fully develop your talents, you need to have a job’; (b) ‘It is humiliating to receive money without having to work for it’; (c) ‘People who do not work become lazy’; (d) ‘Work is a duty towards society’; and (e) ‘Work should always come ﬁrst, even if it means less spare time’.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1161">
    The original response scale was anchored according to the variants ‘Strongly agree’ (value 1) and ‘Strongly disagree’ (value 5).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1166">
    Reverse-coded responses were ﬁrst averaged at the individual level (Cronbach’s alpha 0.71) and aggregated at the country level using survey weights.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1171">
    The construct’s theoretic range was between 1 and 5, with higher values indicating a stronger average work ethic of a country.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1176">
   <s id="d1e1181">
    The second predictor captures the strength of the expressive evaluation of work in a country, measured as averaged employment commitment.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1186">
    The measure is based on a two-item indicator of work centrality, aggregated from International Social Survey Work Orientation data from 2015 or from the latest available wave (ISSP Research Group 2017).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1191">
    It is measured in terms of agreement with two statements: (a) ‘I would enjoy paid work, even if I did not need the money’; (b) ‘Work is just a way of earning money – nothing more’.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1196">
    Response scales for both items ranged from ‘Agree strongly’ (value 1) to ‘Disagree strongly’ (value 5).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1201">
   <s id="d1e1206">
    country level by applying survey weights.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1211">
    The values of the composite scale ranged between 1 and 5, increasing with a higher average employment com- mitment in a country.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1216">
   <s id="d1e1221">
    Individual-level controls
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1226">
   <s id="d1e1231">
    Demographic and socio-structural variables were included as controls for compositional diﬀerences in utilitarian self-interest in public welfare.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1236">
    Gender is measured with a dummy variable, where the value 1 is assigned to women and the value 0 is assigned to men.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1241">
    Age is measured in years with a linear and a quadratic term, to capture the potential nonlinearities of its eﬀect.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1246">
    Educational attainment is measured as years of completed formal education.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1251">
    Income is measured subjectively, as a feeling about the household’s income expressed on a reverse-coded 1–4 scale.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1256">
    The value 1 corresponds to the response variant ‘Very diﬃcult on present income’ and the value 4 stands for ‘Living comfortably on present income’.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1261">
    Employment status is captured with a set of three dummies based on respondents’ main activity seven days prior to the survey.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1266">
    These indicate whether respondents were in paid employment, unem- ployed or not active in the labour force.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1271">
    For each, the value 1 was given to those who reported the given activity, and 0 otherwise.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1276">
   <s id="d1e1281">
    Two value orientations associated with support for public welfare were controlled for as well.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1286">
    A measure of interpersonal trust was constructed as the average agreement with three statements regarding whether people: (a) can be trusted, (b) try to take advantage of others and (c) are helpful most of the time.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1291">
    The composite scale ranges between 0 and 10, increasing in the direction of higher trust (Cronbach’s alpha 0.76).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1296">
    The measure for egalitar- ianism is based on agreement with the statement ‘For a fair society, diﬀer- ences in the standard of living should be small’, indicated on a 1–5 scale.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1301">
    Responses were reverse-coded, so that higher values indicate a higher ega- litarian orientation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1306">
    The value 5 corresponds to the category ‘Agree strongly’ and the value 1 to the variant ‘Disagree strongly’.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1311">
   <s id="d1e1316">
    Country-level controls
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1321">
   <s id="d1e1326">
    Countries’ cultural, institutional and socio-economic characteristics con- sidered to aﬀect welfare preferences were also included as controls.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1331">
    Where possible, the values of covariates were lagged by one year, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1336">
    they corre- spond to 2015 or the latest available year.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1341">
   <s id="d1e1346">
    <span class="anchor" id="Results">
    </span>
    typically require time to manifest and impact individual attitudes and behaviours (see Schlueter et al.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1351">
    2013, 673).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1356">
   <s id="d1e1361">
    The ﬁrst two macro-controls focus on the national cultural context which is relevant to the support for universalistic beneﬁts: aggregated interpersonal trust and egalitarianism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1366">
    Both measures are based on corre- sponding individual-level variables from ESS data, weighted and averaged at the country level.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1371">
   <s id="d1e1376">
    Total social protection expenditures as a percentage of gross domestic product (GDP) obtained from International Labour Organization’s World Social Protection Report 2017–19 (ILO 2017) is used as an indicator of welfare generosity.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1381">
    Gini index of income inequality is used as a proxy for the extent of redistribution.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1386">
    Harmonized unemployment rate is indicative of a business cycle phase and GDP per head in terms of constant prices and pur- chasing power parities (currency USD) is included to control for diﬀerences in socio-economic development.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1391">
    All three measures were obtained from the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD 2019).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1396">
   <s id="d1e1401">
    Results
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1406">
   <s id="d1e1411">
    Country diﬀerences
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1416">
   <s id="d1e1421">
    Figure 1 shows the weighted proportions of individuals who are in favour of implementing a UBI scheme in their country.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1426">
    Relatively high levels of support are found in the majority of countries, albeit there is a substantial cross-national variation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1431">
    UBI is supported by more than half of the popu- lation in 11 countries, while the majority of citizens in 12 countries are against implementation.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1436">
    Countries with the highest share of those in favour are Lithuania, Russia and Hungary.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1441">
    UBI implementation is most strongly opposed in Norway, Switzerland and Sweden.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1446">
   <s id="d1e1451">
    Figure 2 suggests that the two types of work importance are related to support for UBI in opposite directions.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1456">
    Israel, Hungary and Portugal, which score highest on the normative dimension of work importance, are all countries with above 50% support for UBI.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1461">
    On the other hand, the expressive dimension of work importance is clearly dominated by countries where the majority reject the scheme, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1466">
    by Norway, Iceland and Sweden.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1471">
   <s id="d1e1476">
    Multi-variate results
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1481">
   <s id="d1e1486">
    A series of multi-level logistic regressions was ﬁtted to test the eﬀect of the cultural importance of paid work on support for UBI.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1491">
   <s id="d1e1496">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark9">
    </span>
    Figure 1.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1501">
    Support for the implementation of UBI in the 23 analysed countries (own cal- culations based on ESS 2016).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1506">
   <s id="d1e1511">
    containing only random intercepts was estimated ﬁrst (A1).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1516">
    According to the intra-class correlation (ICC), 7% of the overall variance in UBI support occurs due to respondents’ country-belonging, rather than due to their individual characteristics.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1521">
   <s id="d1e1526">
    Next, a model including individual-level controls was estimated (A2).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1531">
    With respect to socio-structural variables, individuals supportive of the implementation of UBI are, ceteris paribus, younger3, come from less aﬄuent households and/or have a weaker labour market attachment.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1536">
    Looking at the value orientations, the results show that UBI is more likely to ﬁnd support among egalitarian respondents and those who trust their fellow citizens.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1541">
   <s id="d1e1546">
    3Although the quadratic term is signiﬁcant and positive, conversion to unstandardized metric reveals that
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1551">
   <s id="d1e1556">
    the eﬀect changes from positive to negative only at 94 years of age.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1561">
   <s id="d1e1566">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark10">
    </span>
    Figure 2.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1571">
    Work ethic and employment commitment in the 23 analysed countries (own calculations based on EVS 2015; WVS 2015; ESS 2016; ISSP Research Group 2017).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1576">
   <s id="d1e1581">
    characteristics associated with UBI support are similar to the factors related to general pro-welfare attitudes (Table 1).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1586">
   <s id="d1e1591">
    In the next step, two country-level predictors of cultural productivism were added to the model containing individual-level controls, ﬁrst alone, then together in one model.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1596">
    Model B1 shows that the eﬀect of work’s nor- mative importance is surprisingly positive, albeit relatively weak and insigniﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1601">
    Nor does it have any substantial explanatory power, as the unchanged ICC value indicates.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1606">
    The results thus provide no evidence in support of H1a.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1611">
    The average strength of the normative importance of work does not seem to aﬀect cross-national variation in preferences for UBI.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1616">
   <s id="d1e1621">
    The opposite is true for the expressive dimension of work’s cultural importance.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1626">
   <s id="d1e1631">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark11">
    </span>
    Table 1.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1636">
    Eﬀects of individual-level characteristics on support for UBI; multi-level logistic regression.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1641">
   <s id="d1e1646">
    Note: Statistical signiﬁcance = * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1651">
   <s id="d1e1656">
    SE = standard error; ref.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1661">
    = reference category; ICC = intra-class correlation; N = number of countries.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1666">
   <s id="d1e1671">
    not change even when the eﬀects of both predictors are estimated together (B3).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1676">
    It also eliminates more than half of the initial share of variance at the country level.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1681">
    The results suggest that citizens living in countries where work is highly expressively valued, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1686">
    where workers are, on average, more committed to paid work, are less likely to support the implemen- tation of UBI.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1691">
    A higher expressive evaluation of work in a country seems to hinder UBI’s capacity to generate more positive reactions among the general public as expected by H1b (Table 2).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1696">
   <s id="d1e1701">
    How strong is this eﬀect, relatively speaking, compared to the eﬀects of
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1706">
   <s id="d1e1711">
    other relevant macro-covariates on UBI support? To address H2a, six country-level controls were included one by one in the model containing only individual predictors.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1716">
    Relative sizes of their eﬀects were then com- pared with the eﬀect of the employment commitment predictor from a similar model (B2).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1721">
    Table 3 shows that the public’s sympathy with UBI is lower in high trusting countries (C1), countries with compressed income structures (C4) and aﬄuent societies (C6).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1726">
    Neither the strength of aggregated egalitarianism (C2), social protection expenditures (C3) nor unemployment (C5) was found to explain country diﬀerences in support for UBI.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1731">
    When compared to the eﬀect of employment commit- ment predictor, it is only the eﬀect of GDP which is relatively stronger.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1736">
    On the other hand, its explanatory power, as indicated by a reduction in the initial ICC, is roughly similar.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1741">
   <s id="d1e1746">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark12">
    </span>
    Table 2.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1751">
    Eﬀects of main country-level predictors on support for UBI; multi-level logistic regression.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1756">
   <s id="d1e1761">
    Note: Statistical signiﬁcance = * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1766">
    SE = standard error; ICC = intra-class correlation; N = number of countries.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1771">
   <s id="d1e1776">
    Controlled for individual-level characteristics (Table 1, Model A2).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1781">
   <s id="d1e1786">
    the cultural evaluation of work is among the most inﬂuential macro- factors associated with UBI support, it is not the single most important factor.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1791">
   <s id="d1e1796">
    Finally, the robustness of the negative relationship between the expres- sive cultural importance of work and UBI support was put to a test (H2b).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1801">
    Six country-level controls from Models C1-C6 were individually added to the model including individual-level controls, together with the employ- ment commitment predictor (i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1806">
    B2).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1811">
    Since the work ethic predictor was not found to be related to the outcome, it has been omitted from this step of the analysis.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1816">
    Table 4 shows that the negative relationship between the expressive evaluation of work and UBI support holds, even when cultural context (D1-D2), social expenditures (D3), income inequal- ities (D4) and unemployment (D5) are controlled for.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1821">
    The eﬀect loses a substantial part of its strength and becomes insigniﬁcant only when socio-economic development is accounted for (D6).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1826">
   <s id="d1e1831">
    i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1836">
    trust and inequality, when added as a control to Models C1 and C4 (models not reported).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1841">
   <s id="d1e1846">
    To conclude, the results provide mixed evidence regarding the produc- tivist hypothesis.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1851">
   <s id="d1e1856">
    4Compare with ﬁgures D1 and D2 in the Online Appendix D, which show country-level relationships between public support for UBI and employment commitment, and UBI support and GDP.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1861">
   <s id="d1e1866">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark13">
    </span>
    <u>
     Table 3.
    </u>
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1871">
   <s id="d1e1876">
    Notes: Statistical signiﬁcance = * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1881">
    SE = standard error; ICC = intra-class correlation; N = number of countries.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1886">
    Controlled for individual-level characteristics (Table 1, Model A2).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1891">
   <s id="d1e1896">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark14">
    </span>
    Table 4.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1901">
    Eﬀect of employment commitment on support for UBI, controlling for country-level characteristics; multi-level logistic regression.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1906">
   <s id="d1e1911">
    Notes: Statistical signiﬁcance = * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1916">
    SE = standard error; ICC = intra-class correlation; N = number of countries.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1921">
    Controlled for individual-level characteristics (Table 1, Model A2).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1926">
   <s id="d1e1931">
    <span class="anchor" id="Discussion_and_conclusions">
    </span>
    cross-national variation in UBI support seems to be primarily driven by countries’ economic aﬄuence.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1936">
   <s id="d1e1941">
    Two sensitivity checks were conducted to test reliability of the ﬁndings.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1946">
    First, to assess whether a signiﬁcance assessment of country eﬀects was not aﬀected by a relatively low number of countries, country-level models were estimated as Bayesian with weakly informative priors, since they deliver more robust estimates in small-C cases (Bryan and Jenkins 2016).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1951">
    The results of this check were almost identical to those reported (see Online Appendix B).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1956">
    Next, the models were re-ﬁtted without Switzer- land, where viewpoints on UBI may be more salient and ﬁxed, as a result of the unsuccessful referendum from 2015.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1961">
    The only diﬀerence concerned the negative eﬀect of social expenditures, which became statistically sig- niﬁcant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1966">
    The main ﬁndings remained unaﬀected (see Online Appendix C).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1971">
   <s id="d1e1976">
    Discussion and conclusions
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e1981">
   <s id="d1e1986">
    The main aim of this paper was to contribute to comparative welfare atti- tudes research by examining the hypothesis about the negative impact of productivist cultural norms and values on public support for the implementation of UBI.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1991">
    The strength of cultural discourses about the importance of paid work has been traditionally hypothesized to impair UBI’s capacity to attract wider public support.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e1996">
    However, this claim has been justiﬁed mainly in the theoretical realm.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2001">
    The paper analysed the 2016 ESS Round 8 data on 23 European societies and empirically explored the question from a multi-level cross-national perspective.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2006">
    There were two main ﬁndings.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2011">
   <s id="d1e2016">
    First, the results demonstrated that respondents living in societies where paid work has a stronger cultural signiﬁcance are less susceptible towards supporting the implementation of UBI.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2021">
    However, it was not the strength of the normative importance of work, traditionally understood as the work ethic, which was found to aﬀect the preferences.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2026">
    The societies more sceptical with regard to UBI were those where work matters expres- sively, i.e.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2031">
    where people’s average commitment to employment was higher.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2036">
    Second, the paper sought to determine how the cultural importance of work as an explanatory factor of UBI preferences compare with other country characteristics associated with pro-welfare attitudes.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2041">
    The results showed that, even though employment commitment is a strong predictor of public support for UBI, its eﬀect is, in terms of relative size, surpassed by that of GDP, itself negatively related to the outcome.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2046">
   <s id="d1e2051">
    <span class="anchor" id="_bookmark16">
    </span>
    commitment when both were estimated in one model.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2056">
    In other words, not only are citizens of aﬄuent societies more sceptical about UBI, this aﬄuence is also likely a factor which explains their stronger expressive evaluation of work.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2061">
    According to the results, UBI’s capacity to appeal to the general public seems to be limited by the prosperity of post-industrial societies, rather than the cultural attachment of their population to paid work.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2066">
   <s id="d1e2071">
    A plausible explanation for why socio-economic development simul- taneously limits citizens’ sympathies for UBI and increases their expres- sive evaluation of work can be oﬀered by modernization theory.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2076">
    Inglehart and Welzel (2005) assert that, as the prosperity of post-industrial societies increases, individuals tend to prioritize self-expression goals and place a lesser focus on issues of material survival.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2081">
    Since aﬄuent societies have achieved relative material prosperity by other means, UBI may appear to be redundant.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2086">
    Citizens of developed welfare states may also per- ceive UBI as insuﬃciently ﬂat, more so if the question speciﬁes that it entails the partial replacement of welfare programmes that currently exist.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2091">
    A stronger expressive evaluation of work is also likely to be brought about by restructuring the labour market brought about by post-industrialization.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2096">
    As new better paid, more autonomous, and gener- ally more desirable forms of immaterial labour proliferate in the service sector of the economy, individuals’ opportunities to satisfy their self- expression needs in work become more plentiful (Inglehart and Welzel 2005).
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2101">
    Hence, the average willingness to work is likely to increase too.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2106">
    This explanation is also in line with the results from work orientation research, where it has been demonstrated that GDP is strongly related to employment commitment (Turunen and Nätti 2017), and that workers’ self-expressive work values are impacted by satisfaction of their material needs and/or of their positive experiences with beneﬁcial intrinsic properties of work (Gallie 2007).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2111">
   <s id="d1e2116">
    The ﬁndings are however not without limitations.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2121">
    The ﬁrst issue con- cerns the cross-sectional character of the ESS data, which means that the results cannot be interpreted in causal terms.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2126">
    The second issue con- cerns the reliability of the macro-predictors of cultural productivism.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2131">
    Since ESS data include no measures of work orientations, they had to be aggregated from other earlier sources and could only be used at the level of countries.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2136">
   <s id="d1e2141">
    Further research is needed to assess the extent to which the relationship between the public’s preference for UBI and the cultural importance of work is mediated by socio-economic development.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2146">
   <s id="d1e2151">
    <span class="anchor" id="Disclosure_statement">
    </span>
    shed more light on the issue by looking at the dynamics of the relationship at the individual level, that is, by examining how individuals’ work atti- tudes impact their propensity to support UBI.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2156">
    Researchers could also examine the issue by investigating preferences for other non-productivist welfare policies.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2161">
    If the explanation oﬀered in the paper holds, support for these policies too should be indirectly related to employment commitment through socio-economic development.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2166">
    Failure to observe such association would, on the other hand, provide additional support to the legitimacy of concerns regarding UBI’s speciﬁcally problematic relationship with cul- tural discourses about the importance of paid work.
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2171">
   <s id="d1e2176">
    Disclosure statement
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2181">
   <s id="d1e2186">
    No potential conﬂict of interest was reported by the author(s).
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2191">
   <s id="d1e2196">
    Notes on contributors
   </s>
  </p>
  <p id="d1e2201">
   <s id="d1e2206">
    Michal Kozák is a PhD candidate in the Department of Sociology at the University of Bergen, Norway.
   </s>
   <s id="d1e2211">
    His dissertation focuses on work orientations from a comparative perspective.
   </s>
  </p>
 </body>
</html>